[
  {
    "category": "Articles",
    "link": "articles",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "On ___ bright January morning ___ telephone kept ringing in my office.",
            "options": ["the/the", "a/the", "-/-", "-/the"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "On ___ first day they stopped at ___ river and decided to make ___ camp.",
            "options": ["the/a/a", "the/-/a", "the/an/a", "-/the/-"],
            "answer": "the/a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "At ___ first they began to look for ___ dry place.",
            "options": ["the/a", "-/a", "a/the", "an/a"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "To climb ___ tree is not to climb ___ mountain.",
            "options": ["a/a", "a/the", "the/the", "-/-"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "Where there’s ___ will, there’s ___ way.",
            "options": ["a/a", "-/-", "the/the", "a/the"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "___ man always went to ___ same bar at ___ same time every day and asked for two glasses of ___ soda.",
            "options": [
              "A/the/the/-",
              "A/the/the/a",
              "A/the/-/-",
              "-/the/the/-"
            ],
            "answer": "A/the/the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "___ weather was rainy and we made ___ bet whether you would come.",
            "options": ["The/a", "-/the", "A/a", "-/a"],
            "answer": "The/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "Are you afraid of ___ him?",
            "options": ["the/a", "-/a", "-/-", "the/-"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "___ USA is ___ country. It is in North America.",
            "options": ["-/a", "the/a", "the/", "the/the"],
            "answer": "the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "If ___ guest has to leave ___ table during ___ meal he always asks his hostess, “Will you please excuse me for ___ minute”.",
            "options": [
              "a/the/a/a",
              "-/the/a/-",
              "the/the/-/the",
              "an/the/a/a"
            ],
            "answer": "a/the/a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "___ most favorite game is cricket, which is called by ___ English “___ greatest game in ___ world”.",
            "options": [
              "the/the/the/the",
              "the/a/the/the",
              "-/the/-/the",
              "a/the/-/the"
            ],
            "answer": "the/an/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "In his childhood he lived with ___ grandfather, ___ poor tailor.",
            "options": ["a/the", "-/the", "the/a", "a/a"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "___ night being sharp and frosty, we trembled from ___ foot to ___ head.",
            "options": ["the/the/the", "the/-/-", "a/-/-", "-/a/a"],
            "answer": "the/-/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "My ___ friend likes to listen to ___ good story.",
            "options": ["-/the", "a/a", "the/the", "-/a"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "___ idea of helping ___ man was unpleasant in itself.",
            "options": ["-/the", "the/the", "the/a", "-/-"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "When I lived in Paris some years ago I used to buy ___ copy of Le Monde every evening at ___ same local newspaper kiosk.",
            "options": ["-/a", "a/the", "a/a", "the/a"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "___ death of her husband resulted in ___ loss of her home also.",
            "options": ["-/-", "-/the", "the/the", "a/-"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "Peter is on ___ night duty. When I go to ___ bed, he goes to ___ work.",
            "options": ["the/-/a", "-/-/-", "a/a/a", "the/the/-"],
            "answer": "-/-/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "R.Peary was ___ famous American polar traveler. He was ___ first to reach ___ North Pole in 1909.",
            "options": ["a/the/the", "the/the/-", "a/the/a", "-/the/-"],
            "answer": "a/the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "He likes to have ___ rest in ___ country.",
            "options": ["-/-", "-/the", "the/-", "a/-"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "Don’t stay outside in ___ cold; come in by ___ fire.",
            "options": ["the/the", "the/a", "-/a", "the/-"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "It’s ___ pity that my birthday comes only once ___ year.",
            "options": ["a/-", "the/a", "a/a", "an/the"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "___ boy was shy and always looked down when ___ grown-ups spoke to him.",
            "options": ["a/the", "the/-", "an/-", "-/a"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "There was ___ good restaurant near ___ cinema and Joan decided to have ___ dinner there.",
            "options": ["the/a/-", "-/the/-", "an/-/the", "a/a/the"],
            "answer": "a/the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "Kate ate ___ meat with ___ vegetables for ___ second course.",
            "options": ["-/-/the", "a/the/-", "the/a/the", "-/an/-"],
            "answer": "-/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "I’ll never forget ___ first time I saw ___ real American Christmas tree.",
            "options": ["a/the", "an/-", "-/a", "the/a"],
            "answer": "the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "“___ English cannot make ___ good coffee”, she thought leaving ___ restaurant.",
            "options": ["the/a/an", "an/-/the", "-/the/the", "a/-/a"],
            "answer": "the/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "At ___ first it was difficult for her to drive ___ car in ___ London.",
            "options": ["-/the/-", "the/the/-", "-/-/the", "a/-/the"],
            "answer": "-/the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "___ few days later I entered ___ reading room of ___ public library.",
            "options": ["A/the/the", "The/the/the", "-/the/-", "A/a/-"],
            "answer": "A/a/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "___ book is always ___ acceptable gift.",
            "options": ["A/an", "The/", "The/the", "An/the"],
            "answer": "A/an"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "Sofia is ___ capital of ___ Bulgaria.",
            "options": ["-/-", "the/the", "the/-", "the/a"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "Many years ago ___ Tower Bridge of London was ___ fortress.",
            "options": ["-/a", "the/the", "a/-", "the/-"],
            "answer": "the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "___ youth of Great Britain wants to have ___ better life for ___ British people.",
            "options": ["-/-/the", "the/a/the", "the/the/the", "the/-/the"],
            "answer": "the/a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "___ Moon has no ___ light. It is bright because ___ Sun shines on it.",
            "options": [
              "The/-/the",
              "The\n\n\n/a/the",
              "-/-/the",
              "The/the/the"
            ],
            "answer": "The/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "___ shortest man in ___ world and ___ tallest man in ___ world live in ___ Africa.",
            "options": [
              "The/the/the/the/-",
              "The/the/-/an/an",
              "-/the/-/an/an",
              "The/a/-/-/an",
              "The/-/-/-/-"
            ],
            "answer": "The/the/the/the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "Hope is ___ good breakfast, but ___ bad supper.",
            "options": ["a/a", "the/the", "a/the", "a/an", "a/-"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "I always wear sunglasses when I go ___ beach. ___ sun bothers my eyes.",
            "options": ["the/the", "a/the", "-/a", "an/a", "the/a"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "She ordered ___ fried chicken with ___ green salad and black coffee for ___ dessert.",
            "options": ["-/-/-", "the/-/-", "an/the/", "-/a/the", "a/an/the"],
            "answer": "-/-/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "My aunt lived on ___ ground floor of ___ old house on ___ River Thames.",
            "options": [
              "the/an/the",
              "-/the/a",
              "the/the/-",
              "-/an/the",
              "a/an/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/an/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "On the New Year Eve some of ___ pupils stayed at ___ school later than usual.",
            "options": ["the/-", "the/the", "-/the", "a/a", "the/a"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "___ best runner in the race was ___ young girl.",
            "options": ["a/an", "the/an", "-/the", "the/a", "the/the"],
            "answer": "the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "The first of ___ January is ___ great holiday in many countries.",
            "options": ["the/a", "-/an", "-/a", "the/-", "the/the"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "On ___ Sundays my father stays in ___ bed till ten o’clock reading ___ Sunday papers.",
            "options": [
              "the/the/-",
              "-/-/the",
              "an/-/-",
              "the/the/the",
              "-/-/-"
            ],
            "answer": "-/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "After ___ fourth lesson English pupils have ___ break of ___ hour and ___ half for dinner.",
            "options": [
              "a/a/a/a",
              "the/a/-/a",
              "a/the/an/a",
              "the/a/an/a",
              "-/-/an/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/a/an/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "On ___ day of___ race many people came to the skating.",
            "options": ["-/-", "a/the", "the/a", "the/-", "the/the"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "___ Sahara is in the northern part of Africa.",
            "options": ["-", "a", "an", "the", "any"],
            "answer": "the"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "___ fog was so thick that we couldn’t see ___ side of ___ road.",
            "options": [
              "a/the/a",
              "the/-/-",
              "the/the/the",
              "-/the/a",
              "the/a/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "I remember an episode in ___ my life when I had to spend ___ month in the country.",
            "options": ["a/-", "the/a", "-/an", "-/a", "an/the"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "In ___ afternoon ___ wind increased and they soon found themselves in ___ difficulties.",
            "options": [
              "the/the/-",
              "an/a/the",
              "-/the/-",
              "the/the/the",
              "the/a/the"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "They took part in ___ demonstration in ___ Independence Square.",
            "options": ["-/-", "a/a", "the/-", "-/-", "the/the"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "And what ___ beautiful picture there is over there on ___ wall!",
            "options": ["-/a", "a/the", "a/-", "the/a", "a/a"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "Roger looked at him and, without ___ word, gave him ___ ten-dollar note.",
            "options": ["a/a", "-/-", "-/the", "the/-", "a/-"],
            "answer": "a/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "___ longest river in ___ world is ___ Mississippi.",
            "options": [
              "a/the/an",
              "the/a/the",
              "he/an/the",
              "an/the/the",
              "the/the/the"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "It took us ___ hour and ___ half to do shopping and we got ___ home at 4.",
            "options": [
              "an/a/-",
              "the/an/the",
              "on/the/the",
              "an/the/a",
              "a/the/the"
            ],
            "answer": "an/a/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "___ apple ___ day keeps ___ doctor away.",
            "options": [
              "an/a/the",
              "an/-/a",
              "the/a/a",
              "a/a/the",
              "an/the/the"
            ],
            "answer": "an/a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "We had ___ good talk with him about ___ weather, ___ literature and other things.",
            "options": [
              "-/the/the",
              "a/the/-",
              "a/-/the",
              "the/the/a",
              "a/a/-"
            ],
            "answer": "a/the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "___ girl from ___ farm came once ___ week to help to clean ___ house.",
            "options": [
              "a/a/the/the",
              "the/a/the/the",
              "the/the/a/the",
              "the/a/a/a",
              "the/the/the/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "___ questions Ann asked always seemed to be ___ questions which Paul knew ___ answer.",
            "options": [
              "a/the/the",
              "the/a/a",
              "the/-/a",
              "the/-/the",
              "-/the/the"
            ],
            "answer": "the/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "Before the New Year, we usually have ___ wonderful party at ___ school.",
            "options": ["a / the", "the / the", "a / -", "an/ -", "- / the"],
            "answer": "a / -"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "There is ___ hair in my soup and ___ plate is dirty.",
            "options": ["-/-", "the/the", "a/the", "the/a", "-/the"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "Soon our team scored ___ goal and won ___ game.",
            "options": ["the/the", "a/a", "a/the", "the/a", "an/the"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "Let’s have ___ good breakfast and start the day.",
            "options": ["the", "-", "any", "a", "an"],
            "answer": "a"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "___ youngest boy has just started going to school, ___ eldest boy is at ___ college.",
            "options": [
              "the/the/-",
              "the/-/the",
              "the/-/the",
              "-/-/-",
              "a/-/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "-Did you come by ___ air?\n- No, I came by ___ sea. I had a lovely voyage on ___ Queen Elizabeth II.",
            "options": [
              "an/the/the",
              "-/-/the",
              "an/a/a",
              "the/the/the",
              "-/-/a"
            ],
            "answer": "-/-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "We have a very good train service from here to ___ city center and many people go to ___ work by train.",
            "options": ["a/a", "the/the", "-/-", "the/-", "an/a"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "- I didn’t recognize you. You look different.\n- I know I lost ___ lot of ___ weight.",
            "options": ["a/-", "an/the", "a/the", "the/a", "the/the"],
            "answer": "a/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "___ sun came out right after ___ rain and there was ___ beautiful rainbow in ___ sky.",
            "options": [
              "The/the/a/the",
              "The/a/the/the",
              "A/a/the/a",
              "The/the/the/a",
              "A/the/a/the"
            ],
            "answer": "The/the/a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "I always have ___ breakfast at 8 a.m. Today I had ___ very nice breakfast.",
            "options": ["a/the", "-/a", "-/-", "the/-", "a/-"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "He was ___ very tall man with ___ dark hair.",
            "options": ["a/the", "a/-", "the/the", "-/-", "a/a"],
            "answer": "a/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "Would you like to be ___ English teacher at ___ college.",
            "options": ["the/-", "the/the", "a/-", "an/-", "the/a"],
            "answer": "an/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "We had ___ very nice meal. ___ vegetables were especially good.",
            "options": ["-/-", "-/the", "a/-", "a/the", "the/the"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "All ___ books on ___ top of the shelf belong to me.",
            "options": ["-/a", "the/-", "the/the", "-/the", "on/with"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "If you live in ___ foreign country you should try and learn ___ language.",
            "options": ["a/the", "-/-", "-/a", "the/the", "the/a"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "Washington is situated on ___ Potomac River in ___ District of Columbia.",
            "options": ["-/-", "the/-", "-/the", "the/the", "a/an"],
            "answer": "-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "David picked up ___ nut from ___ hole.",
            "options": ["the/the", "a/an", "a/the", "the/a", "an/a"],
            "answer": "the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "Once ___ pupils of ___ fifth form read ___ book about Robin Hood.",
            "options": [
              "-/the/a",
              "a/an/the",
              "the/the/a",
              "an/a/the",
              "-/the/an"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "___ concert began with ___ song about ___ peace and ___ work.",
            "options": [
              "the/a/-/-",
              "a/the/the/the",
              "a/the/-/-",
              "the/the/a/a",
              "a/a/-/-"
            ],
            "answer": "the/a/-/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "___ Penguins live in the South Pole.",
            "options": ["a", "an", "-", "the", "some"],
            "answer": "-"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "France covers ___ area of 551,000 sq km.",
            "options": ["the", "a", "-", "an", "one"],
            "answer": "an"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "Open ___ books at ___ page 20 and read ___ text.",
            "options": [
              "-/the/the",
              "the/-/the",
              "-/-/the",
              "the/-/a",
              "-/the/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/-/the"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "You realize that ___ time to choose one job out of ___ hundreds has come.",
            "options": ["the/-", "a/the", "the/a", "an/a", "-/the"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "There were ___ three shelters on ___ cliff.",
            "options": ["-/the", "-/a", "the/the", "a/a", "a/the"],
            "answer": "-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "I saw ___ good deal of him during ___ war.",
            "options": ["-/a", "the/the", "a/a", "the/-", "a/the"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "He sat down at ___ piano and played ___ piece that he had played in the morning.",
            "options": ["a/a", "a/the", "the/the", "the/a", "the/-"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "___ doctor says ___ child must eat ___ apple ___ day.",
            "options": [
              "the/the/a/a",
              "a/a/the/a",
              "the/the/an/the",
              "a/a/an/a",
              "the/the/an/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/an/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "___ Browns invited me to ___ dinner.",
            "options": ["-/the", "the/a", "-/a", "the/-", "the/an"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "They went on ___ expedition to ___ North.",
            "options": ["a/the", "an/the", "-/the", "the/the", "the/a"],
            "answer": "an/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "___ Rome was not built in ___ day.",
            "options": ["the/a", "-/the", "-/a", "-/-", "an/a"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "The beautiful child gave Pinocchio ___ some medicine and ___ piece of sugar.",
            "options": ["a/the", "the/a", "-/a", "the/the", "a/an"],
            "answer": "-/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "Italy is in ___ South of ___ Europe, isn’t it?",
            "options": ["an/a", "the/-", "the/the", "the/an", "an/the"],
            "answer": "the/-"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "___ West End is ___ richest part of ___ capital.",
            "options": [
              "a/an/the",
              "the/a/a",
              "the/the/the",
              "the/-/the",
              "the/the/-"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "-When will ___ next bus be?\n-___ next will be tomorrow morning.",
            "options": ["-/-", "the/the", "a/a", "a/the", "the/a"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "___ Latin America is on ___ South of America.",
            "options": ["the/a", "-/the", "the/the", "-/-", "the/-"],
            "answer": "-/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "Spring is ___ best season of ___ year.",
            "options": ["the/a", "I/the", "a/a", "the/the", "a/-"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "___ long walk in ___ country is very interesting.",
            "options": ["a/the", "the/a", "the/the", "a/a", "-/the"],
            "answer": "a/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "___ Smiths enjoyed their rest at the coast of ___ Black Sea last summer.",
            "options": ["-/the", "the/the", "the/", "the/a", "a/a"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "\"___ Queen Mary\" is one of ___ biggest ships in the world.",
            "options": ["-/a", "-/the", "the/the", "-/-", "the/a"],
            "answer": "the/the"
          },
          {
            "id": 98,
            "question": "They stayed only ___ day at the hotel.",
            "options": ["a", "the", "an", "-", "some"],
            "answer": "a"
          },
          {
            "id": 99,
            "question": "It is ___ holiday of all European people. ___ people have ___ two days’ holiday.",
            "options": [
              "-/-/-",
              "a/-/the",
              "the/-/the",
              "the/the/a",
              "a/the/a"
            ],
            "answer": "the/the/a"
          },
          {
            "id": 100,
            "question": "This is ___ lion that I saw in the circus yesterday.",
            "options": ["a", "-", "the", "an", "any"],
            "answer": "the"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Prepositions",
    "link": "prepositions",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": []
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Pronouns",
    "link": "pronouns",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "Have you heard that a friend of ___ went to Vietnam",
            "options": ["my", "mine", "her", "their", "its"],
            "answer": "mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "That is the girl ___ brother came to see ___",
            "options": [
              "that / we",
              "whose / us",
              "which / they",
              "whom / its",
              "what / us"
            ],
            "answer": "whose / us"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "If ___ has ___ questions, I’ll be pleased to answer them.",
            "options": [
              "someone/any",
              "anyone/any",
              "none/any",
              "anyone/none",
              "someone/none"
            ],
            "answer": "anyone/any"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "I haven’t read ___ of these books but George has read ___ of them.",
            "options": [
              "none/some",
              "no/some",
              "any/some",
              "any/any",
              "any/no"
            ],
            "answer": "any/some"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "That pen isn’t ___ . ___ is a green one.",
            "options": ["my/my", "his/he", "mine/mine", "I/me", "her/its"],
            "answer": "mine/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "She always thinks of ___ happiness.",
            "options": ["another", "others", "other", "another’s", "others’"],
            "answer": "others’"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "___ was not a marriage that could last.",
            "options": ["my", "her", "them", "theirs", "our"],
            "answer": "theirs"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "If this hat is ___, where have you put ___?",
            "options": [
              "your/mine",
              "his/hers",
              "mine/her",
              "ours/their",
              "hers/my"
            ],
            "answer": "his/hers"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "___ read the book and ___ took it to the library.",
            "options": ["He/me", "I/he", "You/her", "She/her", "we/them"],
            "answer": "I/he"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "The work done by ___ is very important.",
            "options": ["he", "she", "we", "they", "you"],
            "answer": "you"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "Why is ___ sitting in the dark?",
            "options": ["we", "she", "you", "I", "her"],
            "answer": "she"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "- What has Ann?\n- ___ has a very nice cat",
            "options": ["we", "it", "she", "he", "them"],
            "answer": "she"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "Will ___ please give me your pen?",
            "options": ["he", "she", "you", "him", "them"],
            "answer": "you"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "MR. WATSON said that THE MYSTERY was over.",
            "options": ["he/it", "he/she", "she/she", "they/it", "he/them"],
            "answer": "he/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "Bad NEWS has wings.",
            "options": ["it", "he", "they", "she", "them"],
            "answer": "it"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "I have a cat. ___ is very nice.",
            "options": ["you", "they", "it", "its", "who"],
            "answer": "it"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "How many children have THE TAYLORS?",
            "options": ["them", "they", "it", "their", "its"],
            "answer": "they"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "___ didn’t take our children to the park as ___ were at school.",
            "options": [
              "her / our",
              "we / they",
              "us / they",
              "we / them",
              "his / her"
            ],
            "answer": "we / they"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "What makes THE SATELLITE rush round the earth at such a great speed?",
            "options": ["she", "its", "her", "it", "him"],
            "answer": "it"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "___ house is almost the same as ___ neighbors’ house. The only difference in appearance is that ___is grey and ___ is white.",
            "options": [
              "our/ours/ours/theirs",
              "ours/ours/our/their",
              "my/hers/my/her",
              "our/our/ours/theirs",
              "my/ours/ours/theirs"
            ],
            "answer": "our/our/ours/theirs"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "___ roommate and ___ have to share a bookshelf: ___ keeps ___ books on the top two shelves, and I keep ___ on the bottom two shelves.",
            "options": [
              "my/me/she/her/mine",
              "his/me/her/hers/my",
              "my/I/she/her/mine",
              "her/hers/she/her/my",
              "my/her/she/hers/mine"
            ],
            "answer": "my/I/she/her/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "Later DICKENS described HIS CHILDHOOD in some of his famous novels.",
            "options": ["she/them", "they/it", "he/us", "him/them", "he/it"],
            "answer": "he/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "Of course I ___ used to be very wealthy.",
            "options": ["my", "mine", "myself", "ourselves", "himself"],
            "answer": "myself"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "I enjoyed the music, but I didn’t like the play ___ .",
            "options": ["yourself", "herself", "myself", "itself", "himself"],
            "answer": "itself"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "I always enjoy ___ when I go to concerts of classical music.",
            "options": [
              "himself",
              "myself",
              "themselves",
              "herself",
              "ourselves"
            ],
            "answer": "myself"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "You know, Mary bought ___ a new dress yesterday.",
            "options": ["myself", "itself", "himself", "oneself", "herself"],
            "answer": "herself"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "Let the boys clean the room ___ .",
            "options": ["them", "himself", "their", "theirs", "themselves"],
            "answer": "themselves"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "We should help everyone as much as possible because we often need help ___ .",
            "options": [
              "themselves",
              "ourselves",
              "yourselves",
              "himself",
              "myself"
            ],
            "answer": "ourselves"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "Did you all do the grammar exercises ___?",
            "options": [
              "yourselves",
              "yourself",
              "herself",
              "themselves",
              "ourselves"
            ],
            "answer": "yourselves"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "He will sit in the room to keep ___ warm.",
            "options": [
              "himself",
              "herself",
              "themselves",
              "yourself",
              "myself"
            ],
            "answer": "himself"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "I looked at ___ in the mirror.",
            "options": ["me", "its", "myself", "my", "mine"],
            "answer": "myself"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "Dorothy was happy when she found ___ in a magic country.",
            "options": ["her", "she", "hers", "herself", "himself"],
            "answer": "herself"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "They always went to places ___ they saw historical monuments.",
            "options": ["which", "what", "that", "where", "who"],
            "answer": "where"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "\"___ else is here?\" she asked.",
            "options": ["my", "whom", "which", "why", "who"],
            "answer": "who"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "I wonder ___ her sister’s boy looks like.",
            "options": ["that", "what", "which", "who", "whose"],
            "answer": "what"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "I like the book ___ I’ve read recently.",
            "options": ["who", "what", "which", "whose", "whatever"],
            "answer": "which"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "The man ___ works at this table is my friend.",
            "options": ["how", "what", "who", "which", "as"],
            "answer": "who"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "___ chapter did you like best?",
            "options": ["what", "whose", "which", "that", "this"],
            "answer": "which"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "Cook was an English explorer ___ made three voyages round the world.",
            "options": ["what", "who", "which", "where", "when"],
            "answer": "who"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "You shouldn’t live with a man ___ doesn’t love you.",
            "options": ["that", "which", "who", "what", "whom"],
            "answer": "who"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "You must find somebody ___ can help you.",
            "options": ["whose", "whom", "who", "what", "which"],
            "answer": "who"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "Who could tell ___ his son’s circumstances really was.",
            "options": ["which", "that", "why", "what", "whose"],
            "answer": "what"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "Here are the books, ___ is yours?",
            "options": ["what", "which", "whose", "wherever", "whether"],
            "answer": "which"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "When they saw a POLICEMAN they stopped in the middle of the STREET.",
            "options": ["his/him", "him/it", "her/its", "he/it", "him/ours"],
            "answer": "him/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "He didn’t take many clothes with ___",
            "options": ["them", "him", "his", "your", "ours"],
            "answer": "him"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "- On what days do you have English lessons?\n\n    - We have ___ on Tuesday, Wednesday and Friday.",
            "options": ["them", "it", "her", "him", "they"],
            "answer": "them"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "Nick knows English well. Ask ___ to help you.",
            "options": ["her", "hers", "me", "him", "us"],
            "answer": "him"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "He wanted ___ to ring ___ up.",
            "options": [
              "they/them",
              "her/your",
              "you/him",
              "them/their",
              "us/his"
            ],
            "answer": "you/him"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "I can’t find all the books you asked me for. I put ___ I found on your desk.",
            "options": ["the", "this", "that", "those", "its"],
            "answer": "those"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "Leave THE CHILDREN alone.",
            "options": ["they", "us", "them", "its", "our"],
            "answer": "them"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "I have a father, a mother, a grandfather, three brothers and two sisters. ___ my family.",
            "options": [
              "Its",
              "These were",
              "Those were",
              "That was",
              "This is"
            ],
            "answer": "This is"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "___ your skis?",
            "options": [
              "Is this",
              "Are that",
              "Is that",
              "Are these",
              "Those are"
            ],
            "answer": "Are these"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "She would like ___ to go in for sport.",
            "options": ["us", "we", "our", "ours", "she"],
            "answer": "us"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "Father watched ___ crossing the street.",
            "options": ["he", "we", "him", "yourself", "himself"],
            "answer": "him"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "They all ran out of the hotel except ___ .",
            "options": ["mine", "his", "hers", "one", "nobody"],
            "answer": "one"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "Do you see ___ bushes on the ___ side of the river?",
            "options": [
              "this/other",
              "that/another",
              "them/other",
              "those/other",
              "some/other"
            ],
            "answer": "those/other"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "___ are pencils and ___ are pens.",
            "options": [
              "this/that",
              "that/these",
              "these/those",
              "that/this",
              "those/those"
            ],
            "answer": "these/those"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "Take it from ___ and give it to ___ .",
            "options": ["he/I", "him/me", "you/you", "his/my", "they/us"],
            "answer": "him/me"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "He put the map before ___ .",
            "options": ["him", "they", "he", "my", "she"],
            "answer": "him"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "- I need a TV-set.\n\n    - Why don’t you buy ___ .",
            "options": ["them", "one", "ones", "him", "its"],
            "answer": "one"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "It was clear they loved ___ .",
            "options": [
              "one another",
              "each other",
              "their",
              "who ever",
              "what ever"
            ],
            "answer": "each other"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "But now we are both happy and we love ___ .",
            "options": ["us", "each one", "everyone", "each other", "another"],
            "answer": "each other"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "Michel can only guess ___ ___ think.",
            "options": ["whom/he", "that/me", "who/our", "what/I", "what/he"],
            "answer": "what/I"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "- ___ is your daughter?\n\n    - ___ is an English teacher.",
            "options": [
              "that / she",
              "what / she",
              "she / who",
              "who / her",
              "which / that"
            ],
            "answer": "what / she"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "He was very angry because he couldn’t find the report ___ .",
            "options": [
              "everywhere",
              "something",
              "anywhere",
              "somewhere",
              "nowhere"
            ],
            "answer": "anywhere"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "___ of you can play the piano?",
            "options": ["where", "what", "whose", "which", "whom"],
            "answer": "which"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "There is the man ___ ___ saw in the park the other day.",
            "options": [
              "whom / we",
              "which / our",
              "what / ours",
              "what / we",
              "whose / we"
            ],
            "answer": "whom / we"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "Come at ___ time ___ is convenient to ___ .",
            "options": [
              "any / what / when",
              "some / that / us",
              "any / that / you",
              "some / which / her",
              "some / what / you"
            ],
            "answer": "any / that / you"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "At last we’ve found our book, but where is ___?",
            "options": ["her", "your", "you", "yours", "mine"],
            "answer": "yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "___ met ___ in the street and ___ told ___ all about it.",
            "options": [
              "they/him/he/me",
              "he/him/them/they",
              "they/him/he/them",
              "he/them/she/him",
              "she/her/he/them"
            ],
            "answer": "they/him/he/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "I’ve brought ___ books for you.",
            "options": ["any", "anyone", "some", "someone", "which"],
            "answer": "some"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "___ want ___ matches. Have ___ got ___?",
            "options": [
              "She / any / any / they",
              "I / some / you / any",
              "They / any / we / some",
              "I / some / you / some",
              "He / some / you / any"
            ],
            "answer": "I / some / you / any"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "The word “Germans” was ___ to be frightened at.",
            "options": ["somebody", "something", "anything", "any", "someone"],
            "answer": "something"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "Why didn’t you ask ___ to help ___?",
            "options": [
              "somebody / your",
              "anybody / you",
              "anyone / yourself",
              "somebody / yourselves",
              "anybody / somebody"
            ],
            "answer": "anybody / you"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "They broke into little groups. ___ had his own wonderful story to tell.",
            "options": ["some", "all", "every", "each", "other"],
            "answer": "each"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "Those seats are not ___, they are ___ .",
            "options": [
              "theirs/ours",
              "her/mine",
              "your/our",
              "themselves/ours",
              "his/it"
            ],
            "answer": "theirs/ours"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "Kate is a very nice girl and I like ___ for ___ kindness.",
            "options": ["him/her", "her/she", "she/her", "her/her", "she/his"],
            "answer": "her/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "- Here are ___ shoes.\n\n    - These aren’t ___ . They are ___ .",
            "options": [
              "my/mine/my",
              "her/her/mine",
              "your/mine/yours",
              "their/yours/ours",
              "our/yours/their"
            ],
            "answer": "your/mine/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "___ do you like best - your mother or your father?",
            "options": ["what", "who", "which one", "whose", "why"],
            "answer": "who"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "___ thought ___ could read the story ___ .",
            "options": [
              "You / she/herself",
              "You/herself/her",
              "She/she/herself",
              "He/him/his",
              "You/yourself/your"
            ],
            "answer": "She/she/herself"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "___ are ___ maps and ___ are ___ .",
            "options": [
              "these/yours/those/her",
              "these/your/those/ours",
              "this/you/that/our",
              "these/him/those/me",
              "those/hers/these/you"
            ],
            "answer": "these/your/those/ours"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "Some of the WOMEN watched THE CHILDREN playing with THEIR TOYS.",
            "options": [
              "she/they/them",
              "them/them/them",
              "they/they/them",
              "us/you/it",
              "them/they/they"
            ],
            "answer": "them/them/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "Summer in ___ place is much cooler than in ___ .",
            "options": [
              "my/her",
              "our/their",
              "their/ours",
              "mine/yours",
              "his/my"
            ],
            "answer": "our/their"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "Is there ___ interesting in the newspaper today?",
            "options": ["anything", "any", "something", "some", "no"],
            "answer": "anything"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "She asked ___ to visit ___ sick child.",
            "options": [
              "our/their",
              "us/him",
              "them/hers",
              "us/her",
              "his/her"
            ],
            "answer": "us/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "___ the results of your work.",
            "options": [
              "this is",
              "that was",
              "this was",
              "those are",
              "that is"
            ],
            "answer": "those are"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "___ shoes are black, ___ are brown.",
            "options": ["me/his", "our/him", "my/hers", "he/my", "their/we"],
            "answer": "my/hers"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "- Where is the hen?\n\n    - ___ is sitting on ___ nest.",
            "options": [
              "she/hers",
              "he’s/his",
              "she’s/hers",
              "it/its",
              "it’s/his"
            ],
            "answer": "it/its"
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "-” I didn’t see ___ puppies, Dad”.\n\n    -”___ are with ___ mother”, said Alice’s father.",
            "options": [
              "yours/it is/its",
              "our/they/ours",
              "my/they/your",
              "my/them/their",
              "their/it’s/its"
            ],
            "answer": "my/they/your"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "-Yesterday I found a watch. I don’t know whose watch was ___ .\n\n    -___ was ___ if you found it in the garden.",
            "options": [
              "this/that/our",
              "they/this/his",
              "that/that/mine",
              "these/those/hers",
              "that/this/your"
            ],
            "answer": "that/that/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "Ted and Nick looked for ___ dog for a long time.\n\nThey found a little one but it wasn’t ___ .",
            "options": [
              "his/its",
              "our/their",
              "his/mine",
              "their/theirs",
              "their/ours"
            ],
            "answer": "their/theirs"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "Next year famous Mr. Toscanini came to the town to see Mr. Smith again. But ___ couldn’t find ___ .",
            "options": ["she/him", "they/her", "he/her", "she/her", "he/him"],
            "answer": "he/him"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "I want ___ to answer ___ question.",
            "options": [
              "her/them",
              "their/our",
              "her/him",
              "you/his",
              "you/hers"
            ],
            "answer": "you/his"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "Will ___ give ___ your pen? I’ve left ___ at home.",
            "options": [
              "you/me/my",
              "you/him/your",
              "they/her/his",
              "they/you/their",
              "you/me/mine"
            ],
            "answer": "you/me/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "There was ___ in my suitcase so I could carry it without ___ effort.",
            "options": [
              "something/no",
              "nothing/any",
              "anything/some",
              "nothing/some",
              "some/any"
            ],
            "answer": "nothing/any"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "You are ___ now, and don’t let ___ forget it.",
            "options": [
              "anybody/anyone",
              "somebody/anybody",
              "something/anything",
              "something/something",
              "anything/anyone"
            ],
            "answer": "somebody/anybody"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "It’s not easy to the old man to do shopping. My parents have to do ___ shopping for ___ to help.",
            "options": ["him/him", "his/his", "him/his", "his/him", "her/him"],
            "answer": "his/him"
          },
          {
            "id": 98,
            "question": "___ doesn’t like to be reminded ___ ___ mother lives in a farmhouse.",
            "options": [
              "he/what/her",
              "I/ /my",
              "she/that/her",
              "we/what/their",
              "her/which/her"
            ],
            "answer": "she/that/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 99,
            "question": "How much time does ___ spend on ___ homework?",
            "options": ["we/our", "he/his", "me/her", "them/their", "her/she"],
            "answer": "he/his"
          },
          {
            "id": 100,
            "question": "___ presidents elected in years ending in zero died in ___ office.",
            "options": [
              "his/her",
              "everybody/their",
              "our/her",
              "all/their",
              "their/all"
            ],
            "answer": "all/their"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "name": "Exercise 6",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 101,
            "question": "___ of them must take an exam.",
            "options": ["some", "nobody", "every", "everybody", "any"],
            "answer": "some"
          },
          {
            "id": 102,
            "question": "___ mother never regarded ___ with much favor and there was an antipathy between ___ .",
            "options": [
              "my/her/them",
              "its/her/us",
              "his/they/us",
              "your/it/you",
              "she/we/you"
            ],
            "answer": "my/her/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 103,
            "question": "We’ve got a language lab in our college, and ___ is quite up to date. Have you got ___ in yours?",
            "options": [
              "it / one",
              "one / some",
              "it / some",
              "one / any",
              "it / it"
            ],
            "answer": "it / one"
          },
          {
            "id": 104,
            "question": "We always want ___ to do the most difficult part of the work.",
            "options": ["someone’s", "someone", "pupils", "they", "ones"],
            "answer": "someone"
          },
          {
            "id": 105,
            "question": "He might have concealed from ___ but not from ___ .",
            "options": [
              "other/herself",
              "others/himself",
              "each other/him",
              "themselves/us",
              "on another/it"
            ],
            "answer": "others/himself"
          },
          {
            "id": 106,
            "question": "She put out ___ hand and took ___ .",
            "options": [
              "hers/my",
              "her/mine",
              "she/he",
              "them/his",
              "its/ours"
            ],
            "answer": "her/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 107,
            "question": "If ___ can’t talk to Mark ___ don’t want to talk to ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she/she/somebody",
              "he/he/anybody",
              "I/I/any one",
              "they/they/it",
              "you/you/they"
            ],
            "answer": "I/I/any one"
          },
          {
            "id": 108,
            "question": "___ told ___ a strange “Good bye” and looked at ___ .",
            "options": [
              "He/my/one another",
              "Which/them/it",
              "We/me/us",
              "They/their/them",
              "They/me/each other"
            ],
            "answer": "They/me/each other"
          },
          {
            "id": 109,
            "question": "The teacher asked ___ if he did the work ___ .",
            "options": [
              "her/his",
              "its/ours",
              "him/themselves",
              "him/himself",
              "us/them"
            ],
            "answer": "him/himself"
          },
          {
            "id": 110,
            "question": "If ___ comes home early, tell ___ to wait for ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she/him/hers",
              "he/her/him",
              "he/him/me",
              "we/us/them",
              "it/me/her"
            ],
            "answer": "he/him/me"
          },
          {
            "id": 111,
            "question": "I don’t think this pen is ___, it’s ___ .",
            "options": [
              "my/yours",
              "mine/your",
              "his/my",
              "yours/mine",
              "their/hers"
            ],
            "answer": "yours/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 112,
            "question": "I felt ___ becoming irritated by ___ .",
            "options": [
              "itself/them",
              "myself/her",
              "one another/that",
              "them/theirs",
              "who/which"
            ],
            "answer": "myself/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 113,
            "question": "Did you meet ___ friends at the party?\n\nNo, I met ___ .",
            "options": [
              "some of yours / no",
              "any of your / none",
              "any of your / no",
              "some of your / no",
              "any of you / none"
            ],
            "answer": "any of your / none"
          },
          {
            "id": 114,
            "question": "Have ___ finished ___ work?\n\nYes, we have. We’ve done ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she/her/it",
              "they/there/it",
              "you/your/it",
              "you/their/this",
              "he/your/"
            ],
            "answer": "you/your/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 115,
            "question": "We asked ___ to join ___ if ___ liked.",
            "options": [
              "you/their/we",
              "me/them/theirs",
              "you/her/you",
              "him/she/he",
              "them/we/he"
            ],
            "answer": "you/her/you"
          },
          {
            "id": 116,
            "question": "Have ___ seen ___? Is this book ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "she/her/his",
              "they/hers/my",
              "you/her/hers",
              "him/me/mine",
              "you/me/your"
            ],
            "answer": "you/her/hers"
          },
          {
            "id": 117,
            "question": "___ invited ___ to stay with ___ in the hotel.",
            "options": [
              "I/me/them",
              "she/he/they",
              "we/us/me",
              "they/us/them",
              "you/us/she"
            ],
            "answer": "they/us/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 118,
            "question": "There is ___ you must believe in.",
            "options": ["his", "anything", "anybody", "something", "some"],
            "answer": "something"
          },
          {
            "id": 119,
            "question": "I’ll go to ___ place, ___ time you wish.",
            "options": ["some/some", "any/any", "no/any", "any/no", "/"],
            "answer": "any/any"
          },
          {
            "id": 120,
            "question": "You’ve got an excellent secretary in your office. We’ve got ___ too, but ___ doesn’t speak ___ foreign language.",
            "options": [
              "one / he / any",
              "him / he / some",
              "some / one / any",
              "one / one / any",
              "one / he / no"
            ],
            "answer": "one / he / any"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "name": "Exercise 7",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 121,
            "question": "Then she saw ___ father. He had laid ___ fishing rod and was taking something from ___ pocket.",
            "options": [
              "his/her/its",
              "her/his/his",
              "them/his/his",
              "its/his/its",
              "they/his/his"
            ],
            "answer": "her/his/his"
          },
          {
            "id": 122,
            "question": "“Please, stay a little while”\n\n“Of course, mum, ___ was going to suggest ___ ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he/it/myself",
              "we/us/ourselves",
              "it/it/itself",
              "I/it/myself",
              "she/us/myself"
            ],
            "answer": "I/it/myself"
          },
          {
            "id": 123,
            "question": "I wanted to ask ___ both what you thought of my latest films if ___ saw them.",
            "options": ["you/you", "their/we", "his/him", "me/I", "hers/you"],
            "answer": "you/you"
          },
          {
            "id": 124,
            "question": "I was late. I found ___ in the house.",
            "options": ["each", "nobody", "one", "some", "any"],
            "answer": "nobody"
          },
          {
            "id": 125,
            "question": "This book is ___, there is ___ name on ___ .",
            "options": [
              "your/your/it",
              "his/me/it",
              "mine/my/me",
              "his/it/his",
              "mine/my/it"
            ],
            "answer": "mine/my/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 126,
            "question": "John left the house without saying ___ to ___ .",
            "options": [
              "nothing / somebody",
              "nothing / nobody",
              "anything / anybody",
              "anything / nobody",
              "something / nobody"
            ],
            "answer": "anything / anybody"
          },
          {
            "id": 127,
            "question": "We asked her to tell us ___ interesting, but she refused to tell us ___ .",
            "options": [
              "anything / anything",
              "anything / nothing",
              "anything / none",
              "something / nothing",
              "something / anything"
            ],
            "answer": "something / anything"
          },
          {
            "id": 128,
            "question": "MOTHER will send MARY to buy THE TICKETS.",
            "options": [
              "she/herself/it",
              "she/her/them",
              "she/it/their",
              "she/them/hers",
              "she/your/theirs"
            ],
            "answer": "she/her/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 129,
            "question": "Isn’t that ___ friend over there?\n\nOh! No, she isn’t ___ friend, she is ___ .",
            "options": [
              "your / my / yours",
              "your / his / my",
              "my / yours / mine",
              "mine / my / yours",
              "ours / your / mine"
            ],
            "answer": "your / my / yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 130,
            "question": "“I’m going out with my friend”, she said.\n\nShe said that ___ was going out with ___ friend.",
            "options": ["I/my", "she/her", "they/their", "you/your", "we/our"],
            "answer": "she/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 131,
            "question": "He always looks unhappy. ___ in the world can make him smile.",
            "options": [
              "anybody",
              "something",
              "nothing",
              "anything",
              "someone"
            ],
            "answer": "nothing"
          },
          {
            "id": 132,
            "question": "Have you packed ___?",
            "options": [
              "anybody",
              "someone",
              "everybody",
              "everything",
              "nobody"
            ],
            "answer": "everything"
          },
          {
            "id": 133,
            "question": "I don’t like the hat of ___ at all. ___ doesn’t suit ___ .",
            "options": [
              "hers/it/you",
              "her/it/you",
              "mine/it/his",
              "theirs/he/them",
              "yours/it/you"
            ],
            "answer": "yours/it/you"
          },
          {
            "id": 134,
            "question": "Dick has lost ___ screwdriver. Leave ___ ___ .",
            "options": [
              "yours/her/my",
              "his/her/mine",
              "his/him/yours",
              "our/him/its",
              "my/me/their"
            ],
            "answer": "his/him/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 135,
            "question": "This isn’t ___ book. It must be ___ .",
            "options": ["my/yours", "your/she", "his/her", "her/me", "our/its"],
            "answer": "my/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 136,
            "question": "A friend of ___ told ___ about it.",
            "options": [
              "his/my",
              "mine/me",
              "your/me",
              "mine/she",
              "their/them"
            ],
            "answer": "mine/me"
          },
          {
            "id": 137,
            "question": "I’ve never heard ___ speak to ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she / he",
              "them / they",
              "her / him",
              "they / him",
              "you / they"
            ],
            "answer": "her / him"
          },
          {
            "id": 138,
            "question": "Do you know ___ Cindy gave a present to her boss?",
            "options": ["who", "why", "that", "how much", "what"],
            "answer": "why"
          },
          {
            "id": 139,
            "question": "___ eyes were as bright as ___ .",
            "options": [
              "mine / you",
              "his/hers",
              "its/she",
              "hers/his",
              "ours/our"
            ],
            "answer": "hers/his"
          },
          {
            "id": 140,
            "question": "I can’t find my watch ___ . I’ve looked for it ___ .",
            "options": [
              "nothing/anything",
              "something/everywhere",
              "everywhere/nowhere",
              "anywhere/everywhere",
              "anybody/nobody"
            ],
            "answer": "anywhere/everywhere"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "name": "Exercise 8",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 141,
            "question": "We got home late. We were very tired and ___ went to bed at once.",
            "options": [
              "anybody",
              "nobody",
              "somebody",
              "anything",
              "everybody"
            ],
            "answer": "nobody"
          },
          {
            "id": 142,
            "question": "I have found ___ lost pen. I don’t need ___ .",
            "options": ["his/me", "we/they", "her/its", "your/it", "your/them"],
            "answer": "your/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 143,
            "question": "___ say that he is leaving ___ native town tomorrow.",
            "options": ["he/his", "we/us", "they/his", "she/his", "I/him"],
            "answer": "they/his"
          },
          {
            "id": 144,
            "question": "Could you give ___ book to ___ please. She has forgotten to take ___ .",
            "options": [
              "her/your/hers",
              "your/her/hers",
              "my/my/mine",
              "him/his/theirs",
              "it/him/its"
            ],
            "answer": "your/her/hers"
          },
          {
            "id": 145,
            "question": "Here is ___ notebook, but I can’t find ___ .",
            "options": [
              "my/your",
              "you/mine",
              "your/their",
              "his/her",
              "your/mine"
            ],
            "answer": "your/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 146,
            "question": "Do you know ___ this word means?\n\nYes, it means “continue”.",
            "options": ["who", "when", "that", "why", "what"],
            "answer": "what"
          },
          {
            "id": 147,
            "question": "Which of ___ is ___ brother? ___ are so alike.",
            "options": [
              "him/my/they",
              "them/your/they",
              "us/his/you",
              "you/her/we",
              "them/his/you"
            ],
            "answer": "them/your/they"
          },
          {
            "id": 148,
            "question": "The CHILD was looking for HIS CAP while HIS FATHER called him.",
            "options": [
              "he/it/he",
              "he/it/him",
              "he/it/his",
              "she/it/her",
              "she/it/it"
            ],
            "answer": "he/it/he"
          },
          {
            "id": 149,
            "question": "When a child, ISAAC lived with HIS MOTHER, UNCLE, AND GRANDMOTHER.",
            "options": ["he/them", "she/him", "they/him", "it/her", "they/us"],
            "answer": "he/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 150,
            "question": "On ___ way home Peter decided to buy new skates for ___.",
            "options": [
              "he/him",
              "his/his",
              "his/herself",
              "his/himself",
              "her/him"
            ],
            "answer": "his/himself"
          },
          {
            "id": 151,
            "question": "THE HIGH PRICES affected THE POOR.",
            "options": [
              "they/them",
              "they/it",
              "you/them",
              "they/her",
              "be/him"
            ],
            "answer": "they/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 152,
            "question": "A BLIND MAN was groping for the DOOR HANDLE.",
            "options": ["he/it", "she/it", "it/them", "they/me", "she/them"],
            "answer": "he/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 153,
            "question": "He asked her name and ___ told ___ ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she/him/her",
              "he/her/her",
              "she/her/his",
              "she/him/hers",
              "he/he/his"
            ],
            "answer": "she/him/hers"
          },
          {
            "id": 154,
            "question": "“But I can’t do ___ for him,” the girl told ___ friend.",
            "options": [
              "somebody/their",
              "anything/her",
              "something/any",
              "theirs/nothing",
              "anybody/no"
            ],
            "answer": "anything/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 155,
            "question": "THE EIGHTH OF MARCH is WOMEN’S Day.",
            "options": ["It/their", "It/her", "It/his", "It/our", "She/her"],
            "answer": "It/their"
          },
          {
            "id": 156,
            "question": "___ own hand shook as ___ accepted a rose or two from ___ and thanked ___ .",
            "options": [
              "his/he/hers/her",
              "my/they/theirs/her",
              "her/we/ours/us",
              "their/us/we/they",
              "our/he/his/himself"
            ],
            "answer": "his/he/hers/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 157,
            "question": "Can you give me ___ to eat? I’m very hungry.",
            "options": ["anything", "nothing", "what", "someone", "anybody"],
            "answer": "anything"
          },
          {
            "id": 158,
            "question": "There was ___ snakelike in the boy’s black eyes.",
            "options": ["something", "someone", "some", "anything", "none"],
            "answer": "something"
          },
          {
            "id": 159,
            "question": "___ is devoted to ___ family.",
            "options": ["I/my", "he/him", "he/his", "she/mine", "it/them"],
            "answer": "he/his"
          },
          {
            "id": 160,
            "question": "___ was evident that ___ wanted ___ to drop the subject, ___ I did accordingly.",
            "options": [
              "she/she/I/who",
              "I/she/me/that",
              "it/she/me/which",
              "they/theirs/I/me",
              "that/us/him/"
            ],
            "answer": "it/she/me/which"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "name": "Exercise 9",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 161,
            "question": "I didn’t want to think about ___ else but English.",
            "options": [
              "nothing",
              "anything",
              "someone",
              "everywhere",
              "nobody"
            ],
            "answer": "anything"
          },
          {
            "id": 162,
            "question": "I never have ___ for breakfast but a cup of hot milk.",
            "options": [
              "someone",
              "nothing",
              "anything",
              "everything",
              "anyone"
            ],
            "answer": "anything"
          },
          {
            "id": 163,
            "question": "MY FRIEND AND I walked in SCOTLAND last year and climbed the MOUNTAINS there.",
            "options": [
              "they/it/them",
              "you/he/they",
              "we/it/them",
              "you/she/they",
              "he/he/them"
            ],
            "answer": "we/it/them"
          },
          {
            "id": 164,
            "question": "Here is ___ exercise book. Where’s ___?",
            "options": [
              "my/her",
              "my/yours",
              "his/your",
              "her/their",
              "me/its"
            ],
            "answer": "my/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 165,
            "question": "___ are going to give Kate and Bob a washing machine for ___ wedding.",
            "options": [
              "they/his",
              "I / her",
              "we/their",
              "you/your",
              "some/any"
            ],
            "answer": "we/their"
          },
          {
            "id": 166,
            "question": "Ann took ___ bicycle. Will you give ___ ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "her/my/theirs",
              "our/me/him",
              "my/you/ours",
              "my/me/yours",
              "he/its/hers"
            ],
            "answer": "my/me/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 167,
            "question": "Father said: “You may go ___ you like.”",
            "options": [
              "anywhere",
              "nowhere",
              "something",
              "anyone",
              "somewhere"
            ],
            "answer": "anywhere"
          },
          {
            "id": 168,
            "question": "Where is your niece? ___ is somewhere here. Don’t you hear ___ singing ?",
            "options": ["he/his", "it/its", "he/their", "she/its", "she/her"],
            "answer": "she/her"
          },
          {
            "id": 169,
            "question": "My flat is large. What about ___?",
            "options": ["mine", "her", "their", "your", "yours"],
            "answer": "yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 170,
            "question": "Has ___ read the text?",
            "options": ["any", "anybody", "someone", "some", "we"],
            "answer": "anybody"
          },
          {
            "id": 171,
            "question": "Did ___ want ___ to help ___?",
            "options": [
              "you / he / her",
              "you / me / them",
              "they / her / he",
              "them / her / he",
              "he / his / him"
            ],
            "answer": "you / me / them"
          },
          {
            "id": 172,
            "question": "That test with a bad mark was ___, those were ___",
            "options": [
              "my/her",
              "his/her",
              "yours/their",
              "me/ours",
              "mine/theirs"
            ],
            "answer": "yours/their"
          },
          {
            "id": 173,
            "question": "Our goods are not beautiful.\n\nDo you think ___ are better?",
            "options": ["your", "their", "her", "its", "theirs"],
            "answer": "theirs"
          },
          {
            "id": 174,
            "question": "___ name is Samuel, but ___ may call ___ Sam.",
            "options": [
              "her/he/him",
              "his/you/me",
              "my/she/him",
              "your/you/me",
              "my/you/me"
            ],
            "answer": "my/you/me"
          },
          {
            "id": 175,
            "question": "POETESS was not in the HALL.",
            "options": ["she/it", "he/it", "it/it", "they/it", "you/it"],
            "answer": "she/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 176,
            "question": "In the town there were ___ new hospitals.",
            "options": ["anybody", "some", "any", "something", "oneselves"],
            "answer": "some"
          },
          {
            "id": 177,
            "question": "It was ___ he didn’t want to remember.",
            "options": ["anything", "nobody", "anybody", "anyone", "something"],
            "answer": "something"
          },
          {
            "id": 178,
            "question": "___ put on ___ coats and left the room.",
            "options": ["we/his", "you/her", "they/their", "he/his", "she/her"],
            "answer": "they/their"
          },
          {
            "id": 179,
            "question": "When Peter told ___ about ___ I didn’t believe ___ .",
            "options": [
              "her/her/her",
              "they/me/them",
              "him/it/her",
              "me/it/him",
              "us/you/her"
            ],
            "answer": "me/it/him"
          },
          {
            "id": 180,
            "question": "Let ___ take ___ book, please.",
            "options": ["his/her", "him/", "him/your", "me/him", "I/my"],
            "answer": "him/your"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "name": "Exercise 10",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 180,
            "question": "Let ___ take ___ book, please.",
            "options": ["his/her", "him/", "him/your", "me/him", "I/my"],
            "answer": "him/your"
          },
          {
            "id": 181,
            "question": "___ is ___ watch and ___ is ___ .",
            "options": [
              "that/her/this/you",
              "this/him/that/her",
              "this/my/that/yours",
              "this/you/that/your",
              "this/her/that/her"
            ],
            "answer": "this/my/that/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 182,
            "question": "As ___ is clear to ___, I’m not going to say ___ else.",
            "options": [
              "everything/somebody/anything",
              "everybody/somebody/anybody",
              "everything/everybody/anything",
              "somebody/nobody/something",
              "nothing/nobody/anything"
            ],
            "answer": "everything/everybody/anything"
          },
          {
            "id": 183,
            "question": "Is there ___ in the room? Please, open the door!",
            "options": [
              "somewhere",
              "something",
              "anything",
              "some day",
              "anybody"
            ],
            "answer": "anybody"
          },
          {
            "id": 184,
            "question": "This is ___ watch and that is ___ .",
            "options": [
              "yours/mine",
              "my/yours",
              "your I yours",
              "my/you",
              "mine I your"
            ],
            "answer": "my/yours"
          },
          {
            "id": 185,
            "question": "It’s very quiet in the office today. There’s ___ here. ___ is on holiday.",
            "options": [
              "anybody / everybody",
              "anything / nothing",
              "nobody / all of them",
              "somebody / nothing",
              "nobody / everybody"
            ],
            "answer": "nobody / everybody"
          },
          {
            "id": 186,
            "question": "I’ll be very glad if you invite ___ else to join us.",
            "options": ["somebody", "one more", "friend", "aunt", "something"],
            "answer": "somebody"
          },
          {
            "id": 187,
            "question": "Don’t worry. I’ll do ___ best to help ___ .",
            "options": ["my/you", "your/you", "his/him", "her/her", "/to you"],
            "answer": "my/you"
          },
          {
            "id": 188,
            "question": "___ friend is going to make a report today. ___ say ___ will be very interesting.",
            "options": [
              "my/he/it",
              "her/we/its",
              "his/they/it",
              "our/she/he",
              "your/it/it"
            ],
            "answer": "his/they/it"
          },
          {
            "id": 189,
            "question": "Can I use ___ pen today? I’ve left ___ at home.",
            "options": ["his/her", "your/mine", "her/his", "me/them", "my/it"],
            "answer": "your/mine"
          },
          {
            "id": 190,
            "question": "Here is ___ text book. Where is ___?",
            "options": [
              "her / my",
              "his / their",
              "my / them",
              "my / yours",
              "it / it"
            ],
            "answer": "my / yours"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Present Tenses",
    "link": "present-tenses",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "I’m taking my sister out as she ___ any sun for a long time.",
            "options": [
              "hasn’t had",
              "haven’t had",
              "hadn’t been",
              "will have",
              "shall have"
            ],
            "answer": "hasn’t had"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "He ___ ill for three months already.",
            "options": ["was", "has been", "is", "have been", "were"],
            "answer": "has been"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "Who goes sightseeing?",
            "options": [
              "Nina does.",
              "We shall.",
              "We did.",
              "I did.",
              "She has."
            ],
            "answer": "Nina does."
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "I usually ___ a blouse and jeans at home, but today I ___ on a new dress.",
            "options": [
              "wear/have put",
              "have worn/have put",
              "wore/has put",
              "wears/has put",
              "will wear/put"
            ],
            "answer": "wear/have put"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "What ___ the president ___? -He ___ a contract.",
            "options": [
              "does/do/has signed",
              "is/doing/is signing",
              "will/do/was signing",
              "is/going to do/would sign",
              "shall/do/has been signing"
            ],
            "answer": "is/doing/is signing"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "Look! The cat ___ your cutlet.",
            "options": [
              "is eating",
              "was eating",
              "eats",
              "has been eating",
              "had eaten"
            ],
            "answer": "is eating"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "You look pale. You ___ too hard these days.",
            "options": [
              "have been working",
              "worked",
              "are working",
              "work",
              "were working"
            ],
            "answer": "have been working"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ since I saw you last?",
            "options": [
              "do/do",
              "are/doing",
              "have/been doing",
              "did/do",
              "will/do"
            ],
            "answer": "have/been doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "It is 8.30. Ben and Ann ___ breakfast.",
            "options": [
              "have",
              "are having",
              "is having",
              "was having",
              "were having"
            ],
            "answer": "are having"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "She ___ a journalist nowadays.",
            "options": ["are", "was", "is", "were", "am"],
            "answer": "is"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "You ___ always ___ your things. Put them into their bag.",
            "options": [
              "are/losing",
              "-/lost",
              "have/lost",
              "shall/have been losing",
              "had/lust"
            ],
            "answer": "are/losing"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "What place ___ the youth of our country occupy in all branches now?",
            "options": ["did", "shall", "is", "does", "will"],
            "answer": "does"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "I ___ home for lunch on Mondays. I have lunch in the canteen.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t go",
              "was going",
              "don’t go",
              "doesn’t go",
              "will not go"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t go"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "Westminster Abbey is the ancient old church in which the coronation ceremonies of almost all English kings and queens ___ place.",
            "options": [
              "will take",
              "was taken",
              "was taking",
              "is taking",
              "have taken"
            ],
            "answer": "have taken"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "This is the most interesting film I ___ ever ___.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t/see",
              "was/seen",
              "have /saw",
              "have/seen",
              "had/seen"
            ],
            "answer": "have/seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "“Nobody ___ in that country,” said Pinocchio to his friend.",
            "options": [
              "don’t learn",
              "are learning",
              "learns",
              "doesn’t learn",
              "learn"
            ],
            "answer": "learns"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Paul ___ a student of Cambridge University.",
            "options": ["were", "are", "am", "be", "is"],
            "answer": "is"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "“Little boy”, said a man, “why do you carry that umbrella over your head? It ___ and the sun ___”",
            "options": [
              "rains/isn’t shining",
              "doesn’t rain/shines",
              "isn’t raining/isn’t shining",
              "is raining/is shining",
              "isn’t raining/don’t shine"
            ],
            "answer": "isn’t raining/isn’t shining"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "Who often has dinner at the canteen?",
            "options": ["I did", "we do", "he had", "they have", "she will"],
            "answer": "we do"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "I ___ never ___ him before.",
            "options": ["- /met", "- /meet", "have/met", "has/met", "-/meets"],
            "answer": "have/met"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "The weather is awful, it ___ all day.",
            "options": [
              "rains",
              "is raining",
              "rained",
              "has rained",
              "has been raining"
            ],
            "answer": "has been raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "It is 2 o’clock. I ___ afraid I ___ late.",
            "options": [
              "was/am",
              "shall be/am",
              "am/am",
              "was/was",
              "am/wasn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "am/am"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "Who usually answers these letters in your office?",
            "options": [
              "My friend can.",
              "That man will.",
              "I do, of course.",
              "Mary is.",
              "Those engineers did."
            ],
            "answer": "I do, of course."
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "The milk is hot I ___ on it to make it cold.",
            "options": [
              "am blowing",
              "blow",
              "is blowing",
              "blew",
              "had blown"
            ],
            "answer": "am blowing"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "- You don’t like horror films, do you?\n\n- ___ . They are so terrifying.",
            "options": [
              "Yes, I can.",
              "No, I can’t.",
              "No, I don’t.",
              "Yes, I do.",
              "No, we didn’t."
            ],
            "answer": "No, I don’t."
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "___ this engineer work at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.",
            "options": ["do", "does", "has", "had", "shall"],
            "answer": "does"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "He ___ never ___ him sing.",
            "options": [
              "had___ heard",
              "has___heard",
              "have___ heard",
              "was___ hearing",
              "is___ hearing"
            ],
            "answer": "has___heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "I think ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if he is about fifty",
              "he is about fifty",
              "her about fifty",
              "him about fifty",
              "be about fifty"
            ],
            "answer": "he is about fifty"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "I miss her very much, almost every minute of the day I think of her, or I think I ___ her.",
            "options": [
              "am hearing",
              "hear",
              "heard",
              "have heard",
              "will hear"
            ],
            "answer": "hear"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "Look! There ___ a man sitting at the first table near the door. He ___ at us.",
            "options": [
              "was/looks",
              "had been/looked",
              "were/had looked",
              "is/is looking",
              "is/was looking"
            ],
            "answer": "is/is looking"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "These engineers always ___ in the office and ___.",
            "options": [
              "stayed/learn",
              "stay/learn",
              "stays/learns",
              "have stayed/learned",
              "stay/learned"
            ],
            "answer": "stay/learn"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "It’s the happiest evening I ever ___.",
            "options": ["had", "have had", "has", "has had", "had had"],
            "answer": "have had"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "Let me show the picture that I ___ this week.",
            "options": [
              "am drawing",
              "shall be drawing",
              "have drawn",
              "drew",
              "will be drawing"
            ],
            "answer": "have drawn"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "This is the 7th year Ann and Mary ___ this school.",
            "options": [
              "has attended",
              "have been attending",
              "had been attending",
              "are attending",
              "were attending"
            ],
            "answer": "have been attending"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "He ___ his English in the morning, he ___ it in the evening.",
            "options": [
              "doesn’t have/is having",
              "don’t have/had",
              "doesn’t have/has",
              "didn’t have/have",
              "hadn’t/will have"
            ],
            "answer": "doesn’t have/has"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "The sun ___ in the East and ___ in the West.",
            "options": [
              "sets/rises",
              "sets/goes",
              "rises/sets",
              "goes/rises",
              "set/rise"
            ],
            "answer": "rises/sets"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "While ___ to school we always ___ a bus.",
            "options": [
              "going/take",
              "went/take",
              "shall go/will take",
              "had gone/took",
              "goes/takes"
            ],
            "answer": "going/take"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "We don’t like him because he always ___ lies.",
            "options": [
              "tell",
              "was telling",
              "tells",
              "are telling",
              "has told"
            ],
            "answer": "tells"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "I ___ all my work. I am free now.",
            "options": ["do", "am doing", "shall do", "have done", "had done"],
            "answer": "have done"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "She ___ at school since 1984.",
            "options": [
              "teach",
              "has been teaching",
              "taught",
              "was teaching",
              "have taught"
            ],
            "answer": "has been teaching"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "- ___ your father ___ at the Medical College?\n\n  - Yes, he does.",
            "options": [
              "do/work",
              "did/work",
              "has/worked",
              "does/work",
              "shall/work"
            ],
            "answer": "does/work"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "He ___ to school at 7:30 and ___ at 2 o’clock.",
            "options": [
              "goes/comes back",
              "went/is coming back",
              "go/come back",
              "was going/has come back",
              "is going/came back"
            ],
            "answer": "goes/comes back"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "-You ___ not ___ your soup.\n\n  -I’m sorry. I’m not hungry.",
            "options": [
              "are/eat",
              "has/eaten",
              "are/eating",
              "did/ate",
              "will/eat"
            ],
            "answer": "are/eating"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "-Who ___ French in your family?\n\n  -I ___ .",
            "options": [
              "speaks/do",
              "speak/does",
              "spoke/do",
              "speaking/did",
              "are speaking/did"
            ],
            "answer": "speaks/do"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "Although Mary has been cooking for many years, she still ___ how to prepare Chinese food.",
            "options": [
              "did not know",
              "know",
              "don’t know",
              "doesn’t know",
              "hadn’t known"
            ],
            "answer": "doesn’t know"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "The aims of the course ___ me willing to begin.",
            "options": ["makes", "is making", "were made", "make", "making"],
            "answer": "make"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "Listen! Somebody ___ at the door.",
            "options": [
              "sing",
              "sings",
              "are singing",
              "is singing",
              "is sung"
            ],
            "answer": "is singing"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "-___ life ___ on Mars?\n\n  -No, it ___ .",
            "options": [
              "Does/exist/doesn’t",
              "Did/existed/didn’t",
              "Has/existed/had",
              "Had/existed/had",
              "Will/exist/will"
            ],
            "answer": "Does/exist/doesn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "I ___ this man at all.",
            "options": [
              "don’t know",
              "know",
              "knew",
              "have known",
              "doesn’t know"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t know"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "The boys ___ four English books this year.",
            "options": ["read", "had read", "reads", "have read", "read"],
            "answer": "have read"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "I know he reads every book I ___ ever ___ of.",
            "options": [
              "-/hear",
              "-/heard",
              "have/heard",
              "has/heard",
              "had/heard"
            ],
            "answer": "have/heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "Nothing will make him ___ back to her.",
            "options": ["to come", "come", "came", "coming", "would come"],
            "answer": "come"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "Listen! Someone ___ at the door.",
            "options": [
              "knocks",
              "to knock",
              "has knocked",
              "is knocking",
              "has been knocking"
            ],
            "answer": "is knocking"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "“This thief ___ usually promise to steal again,” said Sherlock Holmes.",
            "options": ["won’t", "didn’t", "isn’t", "doesn’t", "don’t"],
            "answer": "doesn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "Samuel says he’s 25 years old, but nobody ___ him.",
            "options": [
              "is believing",
              "believes",
              "had believed",
              "don’t believe",
              "doesn’t believe"
            ],
            "answer": "believes"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "The sea ___ to those who ___ to listen to it.",
            "options": [
              "speaks/likes",
              "speak/like",
              "speaks/like",
              "speak/likes",
              "speak/will like"
            ],
            "answer": "speaks/like"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "Take your umbrella. It ___ .",
            "options": [
              "was raining",
              "rained",
              "rains",
              "is raining",
              "would be raining"
            ],
            "answer": "is raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "We can’t disturb him now. He ___ .",
            "options": [
              "operate",
              "will operate",
              "has operated",
              "is operating",
              "operates"
            ],
            "answer": "is operating"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "The children of the man who works with me ___ the window this morning.",
            "options": [
              "were broken",
              "break",
              "broke",
              "have broken",
              "had broken"
            ],
            "answer": "have broken"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "“Who ___ this picture?” the teacher asks.",
            "options": [
              "is drawn",
              "drawn",
              "have drawn",
              "draws",
              "has drawn"
            ],
            "answer": "has drawn"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "-Where is Comrade A?\n\n  -He ___ tennis.",
            "options": [
              "plays",
              "is playing",
              "played",
              "has been playing",
              "will play"
            ],
            "answer": "is playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "I ___ never ___ such beautiful flowers before.",
            "options": [
              "shall / see",
              "had / seen",
              "have / seen",
              "has / seen",
              "will / see"
            ],
            "answer": "have / seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "I’ve got to get him to the station. His train ___ at the moment.",
            "options": [
              "leave",
              "has left",
              "had left",
              "is leaving",
              "are leaving"
            ],
            "answer": "is leaving"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "-What ___ you ___?\n\n  -I ___ now.",
            "options": [
              "are/doing/am washing up",
              "have/done/am washing up",
              "have/been done/am washed up",
              "were/done/have washed up",
              "is/doing/did not wash up"
            ],
            "answer": "are/doing/am washing up"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "We can go out now. It ___ .",
            "options": [
              "don’t rain",
              "rains",
              "didn’t rain",
              "has rained",
              "isn’t raining"
            ],
            "answer": "isn’t raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "You’ll see what I ___ about you recently.",
            "options": [
              "shall write",
              "have written",
              "had written",
              "is written",
              "was written"
            ],
            "answer": "have written"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "She ___ since last week.",
            "options": [
              "is ill",
              "was ill",
              "had been ill",
              "has been ill",
              "will be ill"
            ],
            "answer": "has been ill"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "Listen! Somebody ___ at the door.",
            "options": [
              "knocked",
              "has knocked",
              "is knocking",
              "was knocking",
              "knocks"
            ],
            "answer": "is knocking"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "This year we ___ a good harvest of cotton.",
            "options": [
              "has grown",
              "have grown",
              "grown",
              "were growing",
              "are grown"
            ],
            "answer": "have grown"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "Look at the little boys! They ___ with stones.",
            "options": [
              "play",
              "will play",
              "are playing",
              "is playing",
              "played"
            ],
            "answer": "are playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "It ___ him 20 minutes to get to the work usually.",
            "options": [
              "take",
              "is taking",
              "have taken",
              "is not taking",
              "takes"
            ],
            "answer": "takes"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "Usually my working day ___ at 8.30 sharp.",
            "options": [
              "start",
              "starts",
              "would be",
              "won’t start",
              "has started"
            ],
            "answer": "starts"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "Stop a minute, think what you ___ .",
            "options": ["are saying", "say", "says", "is saying", "has said"],
            "answer": "are saying"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "The population of the world ___ very fast.",
            "options": ["rise", "rises", "is rising", "rose", "is risen"],
            "answer": "is rising"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "Tourists ___ a lot of different information when they travel.",
            "options": ["get", "gets", "has got", "would get", "were getting"],
            "answer": "get"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "The English seaside ___ very popular lately.",
            "options": [
              "becomes",
              "has become",
              "became",
              "will become",
              "is becoming"
            ],
            "answer": "has become"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "___ he already___ the rules in the race ?",
            "options": [
              "did/break",
              "does/break",
              "is/breaking",
              "has/broken",
              "had/broken"
            ],
            "answer": "has/broken"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "Peter ___ his lessons. When he finishes them he’ll watch TV.",
            "options": ["does", "do", "did", "is doing", "has done"],
            "answer": "is doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "I ___ never ___ the book.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t/read",
              "haven’t/read",
              "have/read",
              "don’t/read",
              "was/reading"
            ],
            "answer": "have/read"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "Look! The girls ___ in the park.",
            "options": [
              "skate",
              "skated",
              "are skating",
              "will skate",
              "has skated"
            ],
            "answer": "are skating"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "She is sorry, she ___ so rude.",
            "options": ["were", "will be", "are", "has been", "had been"],
            "answer": "has been"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "Why ___ nothing ___?",
            "options": [
              "has / been done still",
              "hasn’t / been done yet",
              "has / been done yet",
              "was / done yet",
              "have / been done yet"
            ],
            "answer": "has / been done yet"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "Shh! The teacher ___ on the blackboard.",
            "options": [
              "wrote",
              "was writing",
              "writes",
              "will write",
              "is writing"
            ],
            "answer": "is writing"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "I ___ here since 1972.",
            "options": [
              "was living",
              "had lived",
              "lives",
              "am living",
              "have lived"
            ],
            "answer": "have lived"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "___ you ___ to England?",
            "options": [
              "were/being",
              "are/being",
              "have/been",
              "were/being",
              "had/been"
            ],
            "answer": "have/been"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "Hello! Who ___?",
            "options": [
              "spoke",
              "speaks",
              "has been speaking",
              "is speaking",
              "was spoken"
            ],
            "answer": "is speaking"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "Max ___ to be good at interpreting, ___ he?",
            "options": [
              "doesn’t seem/does",
              "seems/does",
              "seemed/did",
              "seems/does",
              "didn’t seem/doesn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "doesn’t seem/does"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "___ you ever ___ Herr Boschen sing his great German comic songs?",
            "options": [
              "had/heard",
              "did/hear",
              "do/hear",
              "are/hearing",
              "have/heard"
            ],
            "answer": "have/heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "Who ___ writing the text yet?",
            "options": [
              "haven’t finished",
              "didn’t finish",
              "doesn’t finish",
              "won’t finish",
              "hasn’t finished"
            ],
            "answer": "hasn’t finished"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "- What ___ you ___?\n- I ___ a letter.",
            "options": [
              "are doing/am writing",
              "have done/am writing",
              "did/write",
              "have done/am writing",
              "has done/wrote"
            ],
            "answer": "are doing/am writing"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "We ___ already twenty words.",
            "options": [
              "learned",
              "have learned",
              "learn",
              "will learn",
              "are learning"
            ],
            "answer": "have learned"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "“I can’t marry Mr. Fire. I ___ already ___ my word to another man”, said the chief’s daughter.",
            "options": [
              "don’t/give",
              "had/given",
              "shall/give",
              "didn’t/give",
              "have/given"
            ],
            "answer": "have/given"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "Be quick! A dog ___ after your child.",
            "options": ["runs", "ran", "was running", "will run", "is running"],
            "answer": "is running"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "I ___ never ___ to the USA.",
            "options": [
              "is/ been",
              "has/been",
              "have/been",
              "having/been",
              "was/being"
            ],
            "answer": "have/been"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "Oh, not really, I ___ a minute since I came in.",
            "options": [
              "haven’t had",
              "haven’t",
              "were not",
              "will have",
              "hadn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "haven’t had"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "Take away the crib; the teacher ___ at you.",
            "options": ["look", "is looking", "looks", "looked", "had looked"],
            "answer": "is looking"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "I ___ them for 10 months.",
            "options": [
              "know",
              "knows",
              "have known",
              "will know",
              "shall know"
            ],
            "answer": "have known"
          },
          {
            "id": 98,
            "question": "Why ___ you ___ the coat? It’s not cold.",
            "options": [
              "do/put on",
              "has/put on",
              "have/put on",
              "would/put on",
              "had/put on"
            ],
            "answer": "have/put on"
          },
          {
            "id": 99,
            "question": "Don’t enter the classroom. The students ___ an exam.",
            "options": [
              "write",
              "were writing",
              "have written",
              "are writing",
              "had been written"
            ],
            "answer": "are writing"
          },
          {
            "id": 100,
            "question": "Look! They ___ in our direction.",
            "options": [
              "come",
              "came",
              "will come",
              "was coming",
              "are coming"
            ],
            "answer": "are coming"
          },
          {
            "id": 101,
            "question": "I ___ Paul since Christmas.",
            "options": [
              "don’t see",
              "haven’t seen",
              "hadn’t seen",
              "wasn’t seen",
              "won’t see"
            ],
            "answer": "haven’t seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 102,
            "question": "“Fortune” ___ the magazine of business success for over 50 years.",
            "options": ["is", "was", "will be", "has been", "were"],
            "answer": "has been"
          },
          {
            "id": 103,
            "question": "She ___ false impressions on those who ___ you.",
            "options": [
              "will produce / hadn’t known",
              "produces / don’t know",
              "produces / doesn’t know",
              "has produced / will not know",
              "would produce / have not known"
            ],
            "answer": "produces / don’t know"
          },
          {
            "id": 104,
            "question": "Food prices ___ rapidly in the past few months.",
            "options": [
              "had risen",
              "has risen",
              "have risen",
              "was rising",
              "rises"
            ],
            "answer": "have risen"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Future Tenses",
    "link": "future-tenses",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "I ___ to start a new life tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "to be going",
              "am going",
              "shall go",
              "is going",
              "were going"
            ],
            "answer": "am going"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "Mark ___ into the army next year.",
            "options": [
              "was going",
              "goes",
              "will go",
              "would go",
              "will be go"
            ],
            "answer": "will go"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "They ___ dinner at this time tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "have",
              "are having",
              "will have",
              "having had",
              "will be having"
            ],
            "answer": "will have"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "What’s happened to your hair? Your mother ___",
            "options": [
              "didn’t like",
              "liked",
              "likes",
              "would like",
              "won’t like"
            ],
            "answer": "won’t like"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "I ___ if you come too late tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "shall be sleeping",
              "will sleep",
              "sleep",
              "am sleeping",
              "was sleeping"
            ],
            "answer": "shall be sleeping"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "Be quick or we ___ for school.",
            "options": [
              "are late",
              "is late",
              "have been late",
              "shall be late",
              "will not be late"
            ],
            "answer": "shall be late"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ next Sunday?",
            "options": [
              "were doing",
              "have done",
              "are doing",
              "are done",
              "were done"
            ],
            "answer": "are doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "I think I ___ a cassette recorder and use it in class.",
            "options": ["buy", "am buying", "shall buy", "would buy", "bought"],
            "answer": "shall buy"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "We ___ for Niagara tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "are leaving",
              "have left",
              "left",
              "had to leave",
              "shall be left"
            ],
            "answer": "are leaving"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "I’ll ask him what he ___ for lunch.",
            "options": [
              "was having",
              "are having",
              "would have",
              "should have",
              "will have"
            ],
            "answer": "will have"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "Who ___ for a walk tomorrow?",
            "options": ["go", "will go", "didn’t go", "doesn’t go", "went"],
            "answer": "will go"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "They ___ their English exam at this time tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "will take",
              "will be taking",
              "would take",
              "is taking",
              "take"
            ],
            "answer": "will be taking"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "My boss ___ some V.I.P’s tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "will be received",
              "is receiving",
              "will have received",
              "receive",
              "has received"
            ],
            "answer": "is receiving"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "Ask him when the engineers ___ finish the talks.",
            "options": ["will", "would", "had", "have", "do"],
            "answer": "will"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "He ___ to learn French next year.",
            "options": [
              "was going",
              "is going",
              "are going",
              "will be going",
              "shall be going"
            ],
            "answer": "is going"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "All the children ___ on an excursion next week.",
            "options": ["go", "went", "have gone", "will go", "has gone"],
            "answer": "will go"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "___ you ___ at 6 tomorrow?",
            "options": [
              "will/sleep",
              "were/sleeping",
              "will/be sleeping",
              "do/sleep",
              "are/sleeping"
            ],
            "answer": "will/be sleeping"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "I shall be back by 6 and I hope you ___ a good sleep by that time.",
            "options": [
              "will have had",
              "will have",
              "would have",
              "have had",
              "had had"
            ],
            "answer": "will have had"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "This time tomorrow we ___ probably ___ fishing.",
            "options": ["are/will", "-/shall", "shall/be", "shall/-", "do/are"],
            "answer": "shall/be"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ at 6 tomorrow?",
            "options": [
              "will/do",
              "was/doing",
              "will/be doing",
              "is/doing",
              "will/have done"
            ],
            "answer": "will/be doing"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "By the end of the first term we ___ many English books.",
            "options": [
              "shall be read",
              "read",
              "shall have read",
              "have read",
              "shall read"
            ],
            "answer": "shall have read"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ at 6 tomorrow?",
            "options": [
              "did/do",
              "will/be doing",
              "do/do",
              "do/did",
              "have/done"
            ],
            "answer": "will/be doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "He ___ for you at 7 in the evening next Sunday.",
            "options": [
              "was waiting",
              "were waiting",
              "will be waiting",
              "have waited",
              "had been waited"
            ],
            "answer": "will be waiting"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Prepositions",
    "link": "prepositions",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "She never ___ to eat soup.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t like",
              "like",
              "had liked",
              "would not like",
              "liked"
            ],
            "answer": "liked"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "“I’ll drink tea from this tin mug.”\n\n“Where ___ you ___ it?”",
            "options": [
              "did/find",
              "do/find",
              "did/found",
              "were/found",
              "are/found"
            ],
            "answer": "did/find"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "It was dark and cold. At one moment he thought that he ___ his way.",
            "options": ["lost", "will lose", "had lost", "was lost", "loses"],
            "answer": "had lost"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "I didn’t know anyone in the city where I ___ to get.",
            "options": [
              "did try",
              "was trying",
              "would try",
              "have tried",
              "shall try"
            ],
            "answer": "was trying"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "Why ___ you go to the plant?\n\nI ___ no time.",
            "options": [
              "do/had",
              "will/have",
              "did/hadn’t",
              "didn’t/hadn’t",
              "didn’t/had"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t/had"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "A policeman ___ me crossing the street yesterday.",
            "options": ["seen", "saw", "has seen", "will see", "had seen"],
            "answer": "saw"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "Arthur ___ all his exams by 5 o’clock yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "passed",
              "passes",
              "has passed",
              "has been passed",
              "had passed"
            ],
            "answer": "had passed"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "He evidently ___ his shoes for a very long time. They were worn out.",
            "options": [
              "were wearing",
              "are wearing",
              "had been wearing",
              "was wearing",
              "had been worn"
            ],
            "answer": "had been wearing"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "So, the invisible man ___ into the shop and ___ down.",
            "options": [
              "comes/walked",
              "didn’t come/walk",
              "came/walked",
              "will come/walked",
              "comes/would walk"
            ],
            "answer": "came/walked"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "We were at the theatre 2 days ago. The performance was excellent.\n\nWho ___ the leading part?",
            "options": [
              "did play",
              "play",
              "played",
              "would play",
              "has played"
            ],
            "answer": "played"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "One day the boys found a man in the forest. He ___",
            "options": [
              "will die",
              "had been dying",
              "had died",
              "was dying",
              "die"
            ],
            "answer": "had died"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "His father ___ a doctor and he ___ to make his son a doctor, too.",
            "options": [
              "was/wants",
              "were/wanted",
              "will be/would want",
              "was/wanted",
              "were/wanted"
            ],
            "answer": "was/wanted"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "During his school years Cronin ___ great interest in literature.",
            "options": ["take", "took", "has taken", "had taken", "would take"],
            "answer": "took"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "He ___ the box yesterday, because he had to do it.",
            "options": [
              "would open",
              "had opening",
              "have opened",
              "opens",
              "opened"
            ],
            "answer": "opened"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "While the gentlemen ___ the recent events, the ladies ___ about the weather.",
            "options": [
              "discuss/talk",
              "are discussing/was talking",
              "being discussed/being talked",
              "were discussing/were talking",
              "have discussed/have talked"
            ],
            "answer": "were discussing/were talking"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "She ___ you a letter three weeks ago.",
            "options": ["had sent", "has sent", "sent", "send", "was sending"],
            "answer": "sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "When he ___ home I ___ him the book.",
            "options": [
              "came /shall show",
              "comes/showed",
              "has come/has shown",
              "came/showed",
              "was coming/shall show"
            ],
            "answer": "came/showed"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "They ___ breakfast at 7 and ___ home at eight.",
            "options": [
              "have/left",
              "had/left",
              "had/leave",
              "have/leaves",
              "had/had left"
            ],
            "answer": "had/left"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "Long ago people ___ little about those minerals.",
            "options": [
              "had known",
              "knowed",
              "will know",
              "knew",
              "have known"
            ],
            "answer": "knew"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "The dentist ___ two of his teeth. One of them ___ quite good.",
            "options": [
              "pulls out/are",
              "pull out/was",
              "pulled out/was",
              "pull out/was",
              "pulled out/were"
            ],
            "answer": "pulled out/was"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "I couldn’t imagine what ___ to her.",
            "options": [
              "had happened",
              "has been happened",
              "will happen",
              "has been happening",
              "happens"
            ],
            "answer": "had happened"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "He felt that he ___ it wrong.",
            "options": [
              "has made",
              "made",
              "will make",
              "was made",
              "had made"
            ],
            "answer": "had made"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "I ___ my homework when my mother came.",
            "options": [
              "already did",
              "have already done",
              "had already done",
              "has already done",
              "already do"
            ],
            "answer": "had already done"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "Turning I found my father sitting beside me on the sofa. I said\n\n“How ___ you ___ here?”",
            "options": [
              "do/get",
              "did/get",
              "does/get",
              "was/getting",
              "has/been getting"
            ],
            "answer": "did/get"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "Last summer we ___ a trip to Houston.",
            "options": [
              "made",
              "has made",
              "are making",
              "shall make",
              "will be making"
            ],
            "answer": "made"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "He ___ barely ___ of him until that evening.",
            "options": [
              "had/heard",
              "has/heard",
              "was/heard",
              "did/hear",
              "didn’t/hear"
            ],
            "answer": "had/heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "She ___ in Tashkent five years ago.",
            "options": [
              "had lived",
              "lived",
              "has lived",
              "live",
              "have lived"
            ],
            "answer": "lived"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "We ___ English, so I know it a little.",
            "options": [
              "were learning",
              "learned",
              "learns",
              "should learn",
              "were learning"
            ],
            "answer": "learned"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "Yesterday at this time it ___ .",
            "options": [
              "had snowed",
              "snows",
              "snowed",
              "was snowing",
              "had been snowing"
            ],
            "answer": "was snowing"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "We ___ he ___ ill.",
            "options": [
              "did not know/was",
              "knew/am ill",
              "knew/will be",
              "had known/is",
              "were known/be"
            ],
            "answer": "did not know/was"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "The plane ___ at 4 and it ___ us 20 minutes to get there.",
            "options": [
              "was landing/was taking",
              "was landing/took",
              "landed/took",
              "lands/was taken",
              "has landed/is taking"
            ],
            "answer": "landed/took"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "We ___ the station by 5 o’clock yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "shall reach",
              "were reaching",
              "had reached",
              "reached",
              "would reach"
            ],
            "answer": "had reached"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "The Browns ___ out of town last Sunday and ___ a good time there.",
            "options": [
              "were going/had",
              "went/are having",
              "went/had",
              "are going/were having",
              "goes/has"
            ],
            "answer": "went/had"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "Before answering the telephone he ___ down the table.",
            "options": ["laid", "was lying", "had laid", "lay", "has laid"],
            "answer": "laid"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "Who ___ at the meeting yesterday?",
            "options": ["speak", "speaks", "spoke", "had spoken", "will speak"],
            "answer": "spoke"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "He met me with the bird in his hand. It ___ curiously at me.",
            "options": [
              "looks",
              "was looking",
              "has been looking",
              "would look",
              "should look"
            ],
            "answer": "was looking"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "Nick ___ yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "will not come",
              "hadn’t come",
              "didn’t come",
              "hasn’t come",
              "came not"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t come"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "I knew that he ___ the same paper each morning.",
            "options": [
              "was bought",
              "buys",
              "is buying",
              "bought",
              "had bought"
            ],
            "answer": "bought"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "He asked the children who ___ the book.",
            "options": ["tore", "tear", "tears", "had torn", "will tear"],
            "answer": "had torn"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "Who ___ on a hike yesterday?",
            "options": ["did go", "will go", "has gone", "went", "had went"],
            "answer": "went"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "I ___ to do it but I ___ no time. I was very busy.",
            "options": [
              "wanted/has",
              "want/had have",
              "wanted/had",
              "would want/have",
              "have wanted/shall have"
            ],
            "answer": "wanted/had"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "What a luck. I haven’t seen you for ages.\n\nWhen ___ we ___ last time?",
            "options": [
              "did / meet",
              "have / met",
              "had / met",
              "did / met",
              "will / meet"
            ],
            "answer": "did / meet"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "In the summer of 1868, Melville Bell ___ on a lecture tour in the\n\nUSA and Canada.",
            "options": ["goes", "had gone", "went", "have gone", "has gone"],
            "answer": "went"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "He ___ his work before you came.",
            "options": [
              "finished",
              "finishes",
              "has finished",
              "had finished",
              "finish"
            ],
            "answer": "had finished"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "Why ___ he go to Great Britain last month?",
            "options": ["did", "was", "will", "had", "has"],
            "answer": "did"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "Did you ___ or ___ the potatoes?",
            "options": [
              "mince/peeled",
              "minced/peeled",
              "minced/peeling",
              "peels/minced",
              "mince/peel"
            ],
            "answer": "minced/peeled"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "When she ___ they ___ and he left the house.",
            "options": [
              "had come/quarreled",
              "came/quarreled",
              "has come/quarreled",
              "comes/would quarrel",
              "came/had quarreled"
            ],
            "answer": "came/quarreled"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "Who had left the room by the time I came yesterday?",
            "options": ["Tom did", "Tom does", "Tom had", "Tom has", "Tom was"],
            "answer": "Tom had"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "Neither your parents nor I ___ very glad of the fact that you failed\n\nyour Math exam.",
            "options": ["has been", "have been", "were", "was", "are"],
            "answer": "were"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ at 5 p.m. yesterday?",
            "options": [
              "did/do",
              "have/been doing",
              "would/do",
              "were/doing",
              "will/do"
            ],
            "answer": "were/doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "Who ___ to see me last week?",
            "options": ["comes", "will come", "came", "has come", "have come"],
            "answer": "came"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "They didn’t believe him and ___ to laugh.",
            "options": ["begin", "begins", "began", "had begun", "have begun"],
            "answer": "began"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "Children didn’t ___ to school because it ___ Sunday.",
            "options": [
              "went/was",
              "go/were",
              "have gone/was",
              "gone/was",
              "go/was"
            ],
            "answer": "go/was"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "The train ___ at 8.30 p.m. today, but as a rule it ___ at 8.00 p.m.\n\nsharp.",
            "options": [
              "has left / starts",
              "left / started",
              "left / has started",
              "has left / has started",
              "have left / starts"
            ],
            "answer": "left / started"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "The moon ___ and it ___ surprisingly light at night yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "is rising / is",
              "rose / was",
              "had risen / was",
              "was rising / were",
              "rose / had been"
            ],
            "answer": "rose / was"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "Who ___ him yesterday?",
            "options": ["has seen", "did see", "saw", "have seen", "sees"],
            "answer": "saw"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "He ___ nobody about his secret that day.",
            "options": [
              "don’t tell",
              "tell",
              "didn’t tell",
              "told",
              "doesn’t tell"
            ],
            "answer": "told"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Mixed Tenses",
    "link": "mixed-yenses",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "Ann ___ that she ___ the visitor before.",
            "options": [
              "thought / saw",
              "thinks / sees",
              "is thinking / sees",
              "thought / had seen",
              "have thought / had seen"
            ],
            "answer": "thought / had seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "As it ___ dark we ___ to go home.",
            "options": [
              "gets / decided",
              "would get / shall decide",
              "had got / have decided",
              "was getting / decided",
              "will be getting / had decided"
            ],
            "answer": "was getting / decided"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "He ___ looking at her, wondering where he ___ her.",
            "options": [
              "keep / see",
              "kept / had seen",
              "keeps / saw",
              "had kept / had seen",
              "being kept / would see"
            ],
            "answer": "kept / had seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "They ___ to get married last month although they ___ each other for only six weeks.",
            "options": [
              "decide / know",
              "decided / know",
              "decided / had known",
              "decided / knew",
              "decided / has known"
            ],
            "answer": "decided / had known"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "___ the weather good when you ___ tennis?",
            "options": [
              "is / played",
              "was / were playing",
              "will be / played",
              "is / will be playing",
              "has been / will play"
            ],
            "answer": "was / were playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "When he ___ to the station the train already ___.",
            "options": [
              "comes / left",
              "came / leaves",
              "came / had left",
              "had come / left",
              "has come / leaves"
            ],
            "answer": "came / had left"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "Last Monday when I ___ the house it ___ heavily.",
            "options": [
              "leave / rain",
              "left / was raining",
              "left / had rained",
              "was leaving / rained",
              "leave / rains"
            ],
            "answer": "left / was raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "Yesterday when Tom ___ the lesson___.",
            "options": [
              "comes / already begins",
              "came / had already begun",
              "came / already began",
              "will come / already begins",
              "came / already begins"
            ],
            "answer": "came / had already begun"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "I ___ the call because I ___ a shower.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t answer / was taking",
              "don’t answer / take",
              "doesn’t answer / am taking",
              "will not answer / take",
              "am answering / am taking"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t answer / was taking"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "After Mary ___ the room, she ___ the floor.",
            "options": [
              "tidied up / washes",
              "tidies up / has washed",
              "has tidied up / washed",
              "had tidied up / washed",
              "is tidying up / washes"
            ],
            "answer": "had tidied up / washed"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "Yesterday at this time when his hat ___ he ___ across the bridge.",
            "options": [
              "blows off / is walking",
              "blew off / had walked",
              "has blown off / is walking",
              "blew off / was walking",
              "had blown off / walks"
            ],
            "answer": "blew off / had walked"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "He wanted me to go to the skating rink together. As he ___ I ___ my skates he ___ me his brother’s.",
            "options": [
              "knows / broke / offer",
              "knew / broke / offers",
              "knew / had broken / offered",
              "know / had broken / will offer",
              "knew / has broken / offered"
            ],
            "answer": "knew / had broken / offered"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "Tom looked at his hands. He ___ that those hands ___ young and strong before.",
            "options": [
              "knew / was",
              "know / are",
              "had known / were",
              "knew / be",
              "knew / had been"
            ],
            "answer": "had known / were"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "He ___ us the firm ___ wool since 1935.",
            "options": [
              "told / had been exporting",
              "tells / would export",
              "said / is exporting",
              "will be told / exports",
              "told / has been exporting"
            ],
            "answer": "told / had been exporting"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "He didn’t ___ well though he ___ a hard day before.",
            "options": [
              "slept / spent",
              "sleep / spend",
              "sleeping / had spent",
              "sleep / had spent",
              "slept / had spent"
            ],
            "answer": "sleep / had spent"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "He ___ at the blackboard and ___ that the English teacher ___ the word “apple” there.",
            "options": [
              "was looking / sees/wrote",
              "looks / sees / had written",
              "looked / saw / was writing",
              "is looking / saw / writes",
              "has looked / has seen / is writing"
            ],
            "answer": "looked / saw / was writing"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Mr. Brown ___ to me 2 hours ago to return the book which he ___ .",
            "options": [
              "comes / borrows",
              "came / had borrowed",
              "will come / borrowed",
              "came / borrowed",
              "was coming / borrowed"
            ],
            "answer": "came / had borrowed"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "No sooner he ___ than he ___ ill.",
            "options": [
              "had arrived / falls",
              "had arrived / fell",
              "arrives / has fallen",
              "arrived / will fall",
              "is arriving / is falling"
            ],
            "answer": "had arrived / fell"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "I ___ my homework by 6 o’clock yesterday and when my mother came home I ___ supper.",
            "options": [
              "did / have",
              "have done / had",
              "had done / was having",
              "was doing / had",
              "do / have"
            ],
            "answer": "had done / was having"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "He said that he ___ school and he ___ to enter the academy.",
            "options": [
              "finished / was going",
              "has finished / is going",
              "had finished / was going",
              "finishes / are going",
              "finish / was going"
            ],
            "answer": "had finished / was going"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "It ___ dark and it ___ .",
            "options": [
              "is / are raining",
              "was / was raining",
              "are / was",
              "were / were",
              "were / was"
            ],
            "answer": "was / was raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "The pupils ___ the sentences yet, the teacher ___ the blackboard.",
            "options": [
              "has not written / will clean",
              "had not written / cleaned",
              "did not write / cleans",
              "are not writing / clean",
              "had not written / had cleaned"
            ],
            "answer": "had not written / cleaned"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "Henry ___ Puerto Rico before he ___ to St. Thomas.",
            "options": [
              "visited / had gone",
              "had visited / went",
              "was visiting / went",
              "would visit / goes",
              "visited / went"
            ],
            "answer": "had visited / went"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "The company ___ some new equipment before the strike ___ .",
            "options": [
              "have ordered / begin",
              "had ordered / began",
              "ordered / begins",
              "is ordering / began",
              "will order / had begun"
            ],
            "answer": "had ordered / began"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "I ___ he ___ it interesting.",
            "options": [
              "hoped / find",
              "hoped / finds",
              "hopes / would find",
              "hoped / would find",
              "will find / find"
            ],
            "answer": "hoped / would find"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "Mark Twain ___ that they ___ about him.",
            "options": [
              "understand / speaks",
              "understands / speaks",
              "will understand / spoke",
              "understood / are speaking",
              "understood / were speaking"
            ],
            "answer": "understood / were speaking"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "On our way home we ___ the problem if we could ___ the fine celebration of our mother’s birthday.",
            "options": [
              "discussed / organized",
              "were discussing / organize",
              "had discussed / organize",
              "have discussed / were organizing",
              "discuss / organizes"
            ],
            "answer": "were discussing / organize"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "The greater part of London ___ of wood, but after the great fire wider streets and brick houses ___ .",
            "options": [
              "had been / were built",
              "was / were built",
              "is / have been built",
              "are / are built",
              "has been / is built"
            ],
            "answer": "had been / were built"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "After my parents ___ home my life ___ better.",
            "options": [
              "had returned / became",
              "will return / become",
              "return / have become",
              "return / have become",
              "return / would become"
            ],
            "answer": "had returned / became"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "Why ___ you come yesterday? We ___ a good time.",
            "options": [
              "don’t / can have",
              "didn’t / could have had",
              "will / might have",
              "doesn’t / will have",
              "did not / shall have"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t / could have had"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "He___ even before I ___ a finger on him.",
            "options": [
              "screams / was laid",
              "screamed / had laid",
              "would scream / am laying",
              "screams / laid",
              "screamed / would lay"
            ],
            "answer": "screamed / would lay"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "I___ never___ to Cambridge, but I once ___ Oxford.",
            "options": [
              "did / go / visit",
              "have / been / visited",
              "have / been / had visited",
              "was / visiting / had been visiting",
              "will / have gone / don’t visit"
            ],
            "answer": "have / been / visited"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "We ___ to wait because the man ___ .",
            "options": [
              "told / was questioned",
              "were told / questioned",
              "were told / is questioned",
              "told / was being questioned",
              "were told / was being questioned"
            ],
            "answer": "were told / was being questioned"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "They didn’t know that he ___ from the University in 1990 and then ___ abroad.",
            "options": [
              "had graduated / is working",
              "graduated / works",
              "graduated / was working",
              "was graduating / worked",
              "had graduated / worked"
            ],
            "answer": "had graduated / worked"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "We learned that he ___ the office 5 minutes before he ___ .",
            "options": [
              "left / returned",
              "had left / returned",
              "would leave / returned",
              "would have left / came",
              "had left / had returned"
            ],
            "answer": "had left / returned"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "___ you ___ him this week?\n\nYes, I ___ him on Sunday.",
            "options": [
              "did / see / saw",
              "did / see / have seen",
              "have / seen / see",
              "do / see / saw",
              "have / seen / saw"
            ],
            "answer": "have / seen / saw"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "I ___ my interview with the vice president when my daughter ___ me.",
            "options": [
              "had / were calling",
              "was having / had called",
              "have had / called",
              "had / called",
              "was having / called"
            ],
            "answer": "was having / called"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "Ronald Reagan ___ president for 8 years before he ___ .",
            "options": [
              "had been / has retired",
              "had been / had retired",
              "was / had retired",
              "had been / retired",
              "was / retired"
            ],
            "answer": "had been / retired"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "I went out of the house. It ___ . It ___ for two weeks.",
            "options": [
              "rained / was raining",
              "had rained / was raining",
              "was raining / had been raining",
              "had been raining / was raining",
              "was raining / rained"
            ],
            "answer": "had rained / was raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "After long consideration we ___ to the conclusion our behavior ___ .",
            "options": [
              "came / had been justified",
              "came / will be justified",
              "will come / would be justified",
              "are coming / will justify",
              "has come / are being justified"
            ],
            "answer": "came / had been justified"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "The plan ___ for two hours when he ___.",
            "options": [
              "had been discussed / came",
              "is discussed / comes",
              "will be discussed / come",
              "has been discussed / comes",
              "was discussed / would come"
            ],
            "answer": "had been discussed / came"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "Christopher Columbus didn’t know where he ___. When he landed he didn’t know where he ___ when he got back to Spain he didn’t know where he ___.",
            "options": [
              "was sailing / was / had been",
              "had sailed / was / was",
              "is sailing / had been / has been",
              "will be sailing / will be / will have been",
              "would sail / hadn’t been / haven’t been"
            ],
            "answer": "was sailing / was / had been"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "That day after Mr. Brown ___ the letter he ___ me to clarify some details.",
            "options": [
              "has studied / phoned",
              "studied / phoned",
              "had studied / phoned",
              "had studied / had phoned",
              "studied / is phoning"
            ],
            "answer": "had studied / phoned"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "When Christopher Columbus ___ 14 he ___ a sailor.",
            "options": [
              "is / became",
              "was / became",
              "was / becomes",
              "are / become",
              "were / became"
            ],
            "answer": "was / became"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "When Mr. Brown ___ to the party all the guests ___ at the table.",
            "options": [
              "come / sat",
              "came / are sitting",
              "came / were sitting",
              "comes / sit",
              "came / had sat"
            ],
            "answer": "came / were sitting"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "Nick ___ he ___ his homework by 4 o’clock.",
            "options": [
              "say / has done",
              "said / had done",
              "says / do",
              "said / does",
              "said / has done"
            ],
            "answer": "said / had done"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "The American ___ the question slowly so that we ___",
            "options": [
              "repeated / should understand",
              "repeat / understood",
              "repeats / would understand",
              "repeated / understand",
              "repeats / understands"
            ],
            "answer": "repeated / should understand"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "My sister ___ in Florida for one year when we ___ to New York.",
            "options": [
              "has lived / came",
              "have lived / come",
              "lived / come",
              "had lived / came",
              "live / came"
            ],
            "answer": "had lived / came"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "He came to the writing table and ___ through the letters which ___ for him.",
            "options": [
              "look / was waiting",
              "looked / were waiting",
              "looks / has been waiting",
              "looked / waiting",
              "looks / are waiting"
            ],
            "answer": "looked / were waiting"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "Ann ___ her work by 4 o’clock and ___ shopping.",
            "options": [
              "finished / went",
              "finishes / will go",
              "had finished / went",
              "has finished / go",
              "will finish / went"
            ],
            "answer": "had finished / went"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "He ___ he ___ lunch an hour before.",
            "options": [
              "say / had",
              "said / would have",
              "says / shall have",
              "said / had",
              "said / had had"
            ],
            "answer": "said / had had"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "When we ___ the station the train ___ already ___ .",
            "options": [
              "reach / has / left",
              "reached / had / left",
              "reach / was / leaving",
              "shall reach / / left",
              "were reaching / were / leaving"
            ],
            "answer": "reached / had / left"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "I knew that she ___ Miss Betsy, because I remembered how my mother ___ her.",
            "options": [
              "was / had described",
              "is / described",
              "would be / had described",
              "had been / described",
              "has been / describes"
            ],
            "answer": "was / had described"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "She said that Bob ___ as he ___ research work.",
            "options": [
              "was busy / was doing",
              "was busy / had done",
              "was busy / have done",
              "was busy / would be doing",
              "is busy / will be doing"
            ],
            "answer": "was busy / was doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "He says he ___ his friend whom he ___.",
            "options": [
              "meets / didn’t see",
              "met / hadn’t seen",
              "met / haven’t seen",
              "will meet / sees",
              "meet / doesn’t see"
            ],
            "answer": "met / hadn’t seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "That day when we were in the restaurant each one ___ what he ___.",
            "options": [
              "receive / orders",
              "received / had ordered",
              "is receiving / is ordering",
              "will receive / would order",
              "is received / is ordered"
            ],
            "answer": "received / had ordered"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ here? I ___ for my friend. How long ___ you ___ for him? For twenty minutes.",
            "options": [
              "are / doing / am waiting / have / been waiting",
              "do / do / am waiting / do / wait",
              "are / doing / wait / have / been waiting",
              "have / done / am waiting / are / waiting",
              "are / doing / am waiting / are / waiting"
            ],
            "answer": "are / doing / am waiting / have / been waiting"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "Julia has overslept again. She is going ___ late to her work. “I had better ___ a taxi” she thinks.",
            "options": [
              "being / take",
              "to be / take",
              "be / to take",
              "to be / to take",
              "to be / taking"
            ],
            "answer": "to be / take"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "They ___ just ___ and ___ supper now.",
            "options": [
              "have / come / are having",
              "had / come / are having",
              "have / come / is having",
              "had / come / had",
              "have / come / have"
            ],
            "answer": "have / come / are having"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "I usually ___ there by train but this weekend I ___ by bus.",
            "options": [
              "go / am going",
              "went / go",
              "go / go",
              "go / are going",
              "go / was going"
            ],
            "answer": "go / am going"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "You ___ very thoughtful. What ___ you ___ about?",
            "options": [
              "looked / was / thinking",
              "look / are / thinking",
              "look / are / think",
              "looking / are / thinking",
              "have looked / had / thought"
            ],
            "answer": "look / are / thinking"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "His situation ___ since spring. Now he ___ much better.",
            "options": [
              "has improved / feel",
              "improves / felt",
              "improve / is feeling",
              "has improved / feels",
              "improved / has felt"
            ],
            "answer": "has improved / feels"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "It’s evening. People ___ to their house and ___ TV",
            "options": [
              "come / are watching",
              "have come / are watching",
              "come / watch",
              "has come / are watching",
              "are coming / have watched"
            ],
            "answer": "have come / are watching"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "Please, ___ me the newspaper a postman ___ today.",
            "options": [
              "show / bring",
              "shows / brings",
              "showed / brought",
              "show / brought",
              "show / has brought"
            ],
            "answer": "show / has brought"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "Do you ___ that woman in the corner? She ___ her dog walk.",
            "options": [
              "see / is having",
              "saw / was having",
              "to see / is having",
              "see / has",
              "seen / have"
            ],
            "answer": "see / is having"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "My dog ___ a lot but it ___ at the moment.",
            "options": [
              "is barking / doesn’t bark",
              "barked / didn’t bark",
              "barks / isn’t barking",
              "was barking / won’t bark",
              "will bark / doesn’t bark"
            ],
            "answer": "barks / isn't barking"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "I ___ about it at the moment and I think that I ___ how to use it now.",
            "options": [
              "read / knew",
              "was reading / knew",
              "am reading / know",
              "read / know",
              "shall read / have known"
            ],
            "answer": "am reading / know"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "Tom ___ the book since yesterday morning and he ___ it.",
            "options": [
              "has read / just finished",
              "has been reading / has just finished",
              "had been reading / has just finished",
              "will read / just finishes",
              "read / is just finishing"
            ],
            "answer": "has been reading / has just finished"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "I ___ I ___ you there.",
            "options": [
              "thought / meet",
              "thinks / meet",
              "think / have met",
              "thinks / met",
              "think / has met"
            ],
            "answer": "think / have met"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "He ___ a very experienced teacher. He ___ French for 15 years.",
            "options": [
              "to be / taught",
              "am / is teaching",
              "is / has been teaching",
              "will be / was teaching",
              "was / are teaching"
            ],
            "answer": "is / has been teaching"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "I’m ___ to tell you the story I ___ at school today.",
            "options": [
              "go / hear",
              "going / heard",
              "to go / hear",
              "going / have heard",
              "going / had heard"
            ],
            "answer": "going / have heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "Jimmy, Jane and Billy wanted ___ their grandfather who ___ to visit them.",
            "options": [
              "to impress / had come",
              "impressed / came",
              "will impress / comes",
              "had impressed / has come",
              "to impress / to come"
            ],
            "answer": "to impress / had come"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "On ___ the room he ___ left and ___ his way.",
            "options": [
              "entering / turned / went on",
              "having entered / has turned / goes on",
              "entered / turns / went on",
              "enter / turn / goes on",
              "entering / turns / went on"
            ],
            "answer": "entering / turned / went on"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "___ you read the book “The Godfather”? If yes, when ___ you read?",
            "options": [
              "did / have",
              "will / do",
              "have / did",
              "were / done",
              "has / does"
            ],
            "answer": "have / did"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "I ___ Tom since he ___ school.",
            "options": [
              "have seen / leave",
              "saw / has left",
              "hadn’t seen / left",
              "haven’t seen / left",
              "see / leave"
            ],
            "answer": "haven’t seen / left"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "He ___ me his name but I ___ it.",
            "options": [
              "tell / am forgetting",
              "will tell / forgot",
              "told / have forgotten",
              "has told / shall forget",
              "was told / forgot"
            ],
            "answer": "told / have forgotten"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "They ___ you the money before they ___ .",
            "options": [
              "send / leave",
              "sent / left",
              "will send / leave",
              "sent / had left",
              "should sent / had left"
            ],
            "answer": "will send / leave"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "I ___ already ___ the doctor about it, but she couldn’t ___ me.",
            "options": [
              "has / seen / helped",
              "have / seen / help",
              "had / seen / had helped",
              "will / have seen / help",
              "is/having seen / is helping"
            ],
            "answer": "have / seen / help"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "The weather ___ as nice today as it ___ yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "is / was",
              "are / were",
              "is / will be",
              "was / were",
              "were / shall be"
            ],
            "answer": "is / was"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "You ___ six cakes since we ___ .",
            "options": [
              "had / had come",
              "had had / came",
              "have / come",
              "have had / came",
              "have had / have come"
            ],
            "answer": "have had / came"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "The English ___ of sports and ___ themselves as good sportsmen.",
            "options": [
              "are fond / regard",
              "is fond / regards",
              "were fond / regards",
              "was fond / regards",
              "am fond / are regarding"
            ],
            "answer": "are fond / regard"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "The children ___ their hands and they ___ lunch now.",
            "options": [
              "are washing / are having",
              "have washed / are having",
              "wash / have",
              "washed / are having",
              "wash / have had"
            ],
            "answer": "have washed / are having"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "Don’t go out. It ___ . It ___ since morning.",
            "options": [
              "rains / rains",
              "has rained / rains",
              "was raining / was raining",
              "is raining / has been raining",
              "is raining / had rained"
            ],
            "answer": "is raining / has been raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "I ___ you the book after I ___ it.",
            "options": [
              "give / read",
              "shall give / had read",
              "shall give / have read",
              "have given / shall read",
              "am giving / read"
            ],
            "answer": "shall give / have read"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "She ___ all the work and now she ___ in the next room.",
            "options": [
              "did / rest",
              "have done / rests",
              "does / rests",
              "has done / is resting",
              "had done / is resting"
            ],
            "answer": "has done / is resting"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "She ___ this book this week and she ___ discuss it.",
            "options": [
              "read / can",
              "has read / could",
              "had read / can",
              "have read / can",
              "has read / can"
            ],
            "answer": "has read / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "“I hope you ___ well?” “Yes, I ___ ill for two weeks. Now I ___ well.”",
            "options": [
              "felt / was / is",
              "feel / is / am",
              "is feeling / are / is",
              "are feeling / have been / am",
              "was feeling / was / am"
            ],
            "answer": "are feeling / have been / am"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "___ you ___ the man for many years?\nYes, we ___ at Cambridge together.",
            "options": [
              "have / known / were",
              "do / know / is",
              "were / known / were",
              "have / known / was",
              "did / know / was"
            ],
            "answer": "have / known / were"
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "I ___ an exercise now but I ___ it in some minutes.",
            "options": [
              "write / finished",
              "writes / will finish",
              "wrote / is finishing",
              "am writing / shall finish",
              "have written / had finished"
            ],
            "answer": "am writing / shall finish"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "Last year he ___ better than he ___ now.",
            "options": [
              "sings / did",
              "sang / is doing",
              "had sung / does",
              "would sing / did",
              "had been singing / is doing"
            ],
            "answer": "sang / is doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "Students ___ already their tests and now they ___",
            "options": [
              "had written / hand",
              "are writing / handed",
              "have written / are handing",
              "wrote / will hand",
              "write / hands"
            ],
            "answer": "have written / are handing"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "It is going to rain. I ___ glad I ___ my umbrella with me today.",
            "options": [
              "am/takes",
              "am/have taken",
              "is/taken",
              "are/took",
              "is/takes"
            ],
            "answer": "am/have taken"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "Bill ___ his girlfriend now. That’s the third time he ___ her this evening.",
            "options": [
              "phones / phones",
              "has phoned / phones",
              "is phoning / has phoned",
              "will phone / has phoned",
              "is phoning / had phoned"
            ],
            "answer": "is phoning / has phoned"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "Here ___ your keys. The boy ___ you up to your rooms and your luggage ___ up straight away.",
            "options": [
              "is/show/will bring",
              "are/show/will be brought",
              "are/will show/will be brought",
              "were/will show/brings",
              "are/has shown/will bring"
            ],
            "answer": "are/will show/will be brought"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "How long ___ you ___ to stay?\nI ___ we ___ here for a week at least.",
            "options": [
              "are/going/expect/shall be",
              "were/going/expected/shall be",
              "is/going/expect/are",
              "do/go/expected/are",
              "does/go/expect/will be"
            ],
            "answer": "are/going/expect/shall be"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "Is this your first visit to London?\nNo, I ___ here several times before and I ___ quite at home in London.",
            "options": [
              "was/have felt",
              "have been/feel",
              "had been/felt",
              "has been/felt",
              "were/have felt"
            ],
            "answer": "have been/feel"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "I don’t know when she ___ but when she ___ I’ll give her your book.",
            "options": [
              "will come/will come",
              "will come/come",
              "come/will come",
              "will come/comes",
              "comes/will come"
            ],
            "answer": "will come/comes"
          },
          {
            "id": 98,
            "question": "You ___ here until your mother ___ ready to leave.",
            "options": [
              "will stay/is",
              "would stay/is",
              "stayed/will be",
              "are staying/had been",
              "have stayed/would be"
            ],
            "answer": "will stay/is"
          },
          {
            "id": 99,
            "question": "Many changes ___ place since I ___ in my native town 10 years ago.",
            "options": [
              "has taken/was",
              "are taking/had been",
              "took/was",
              "has taken/am",
              "have taken/was"
            ],
            "answer": "have taken/was"
          },
          {
            "id": 100,
            "question": "I ___ to America five years ago. Since then, I ___ American, and ___ nearly all I ___ there.",
            "options": [
              "had gone/haven’t spoken/have",
              "had gone/don’t speak/forget/learned",
              "was going/haven’t spoken/forgot/had learned",
              "went/haven’t spoken/have forgotten/learned",
              "went/hasn’t spoken/forgot/had learned"
            ],
            "answer": "went/haven’t spoken/have forgotten/learned"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "name": "Exercise 6",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 101,
            "question": "It has been long since I ___ him last. I ___ from him all these years.",
            "options": [
              "saw/haven’t heard",
              "had seen/haven’t heard",
              "see/don’t hear",
              "saw/don’t hear",
              "have seen/haven’t heard"
            ],
            "answer": "had seen/haven’t heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 102,
            "question": "He was sure they ___ the station before night ___.",
            "options": [
              "will reach / came",
              "would reach / came",
              "would have reached / came",
              "would reach / would come",
              "reached / came"
            ],
            "answer": "would reach / came"
          },
          {
            "id": 103,
            "question": "“___ you ___ this film yet?”\n“Yes.”\n“When ___ you ___ it?”",
            "options": [
              "have / seen / have / seen",
              "have / seen / did / see",
              "are / going to see / did / see",
              "did / see / have / seen",
              "have / seen / are / going to see"
            ],
            "answer": "have / seen / did / see"
          },
          {
            "id": 104,
            "question": "When ___ you ___ here?\nI ___ just ___.",
            "options": [
              "did/come back/have/come back",
              "have/come back/have/come back",
              "will/come back/have/come",
              "do/come back/have/has come",
              "are/coming back/was/coming back"
            ],
            "answer": "will/come back/have/come"
          },
          {
            "id": 105,
            "question": "Look! There ___ nothing here. Everything ___ away.",
            "options": [
              "are / have been taken",
              "is / has been taken",
              "is / is taken",
              "is / is being taken",
              "is / will be taken"
            ],
            "answer": "is / has been taken"
          },
          {
            "id": 106,
            "question": "Everybody ___ at what ___.",
            "options": [
              "was surprised/has happened",
              "was surprised/had happened",
              "is surprised/happen",
              "surprise/happen",
              "will be surprised/ happened"
            ],
            "answer": "was surprised/had happened"
          },
          {
            "id": 107,
            "question": "The famous writer Tolstoy ___ forever in our memories, in the books he ___ to us.",
            "options": [
              "will live / has left",
              "is living / will be leaving",
              "lived / leaves",
              "would be living / had left",
              "have been living / left"
            ],
            "answer": "will live / has left"
          },
          {
            "id": 108,
            "question": "Ernest Hemingway ___ one of those people who ___ in their beds.",
            "options": [
              "had not been / died",
              "are / died",
              "was not / die",
              "was not / dies",
              "is being / have not died"
            ],
            "answer": "was not / die"
          },
          {
            "id": 109,
            "question": "If you ___ so rude to her she ___ to us earlier.",
            "options": [
              "were not / had come",
              "hadn’t been / would have come",
              "are / would have come",
              "are / will come",
              "are not being / would come"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t been / would have come"
          },
          {
            "id": 110,
            "question": "“Hello, Mr. Roberts” ___ the clerk. “What ___ you ___ home your the wife today?”",
            "options": [
              "greet / do / take",
              "greeting / were / taking",
              "greeted / are / taking",
              "will greet / did / taken",
              "will greet / did / take"
            ],
            "answer": "greeted / are / taking"
          },
          {
            "id": 111,
            "question": "Two years ago she ___ and now she ___ her time visiting friends.",
            "options": [
              "retires / spends",
              "retired / spends",
              "had retired / spends",
              "would retire / is spending",
              "will retire / spent"
            ],
            "answer": "retired / spends"
          },
          {
            "id": 112,
            "question": "He might ___ the accident if he ___ more careful.",
            "options": [
              "avoid / was",
              "have avoided / had been",
              "avoid / had been",
              "had avoided / were",
              "avoids / is"
            ],
            "answer": "have avoided / had been"
          },
          {
            "id": 113,
            "question": "Hello, Ann! I ___ you for ages. Where have you been all this time?\nI ___ to Italy. I ___ back yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t see/was/came",
              "haven’t seen/have been/came",
              "don’t see/have been/have come",
              "saw/was/came back",
              "haven’t seen/had been/had come"
            ],
            "answer": "haven’t seen/have been/came"
          },
          {
            "id": 114,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ at 6 p.m. yesterday?\nI ___ my homework. After I ___ it I played chess with my friend.",
            "options": [
              "did/do/did/have done",
              "was/doing/was doing/had done",
              "were/doing/was doing/had done",
              "were/doing/did/have done",
              "had/done/had done/did"
            ],
            "answer": "were/doing/was doing/had done"
          },
          {
            "id": 115,
            "question": "This book ___ quite different from the one I ___",
            "options": [
              "is/have read",
              "was/am reading",
              "has been/read",
              "have been/reads",
              "is/read"
            ],
            "answer": "is/read"
          },
          {
            "id": 116,
            "question": "___ I ___ after the luggage or ___ you?\nIf you ___ to the luggage and pay the driver I’ll go in and see about rooms.",
            "options": [
              "shall/look/will/see",
              "shall/look/will/will see",
              "will/look/shall/saw",
              "should/look/would/would see",
              "would/looked/will/saw"
            ],
            "answer": "shall/look/will/see"
          },
          {
            "id": 117,
            "question": "Nobody knows what ___ at this meeting but she ___ to him since.",
            "options": [
              "was said / hasn’t spoken",
              "is said / hasn’t spoken",
              "has said / hasn’t spoken",
              "was said / didn’t speak",
              "is being said / doesn’t speak"
            ],
            "answer": "was said / hasn’t spoken"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Modals",
    "link": "modals",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "Why didn’t you help him? You ___ have done it.",
            "options": ["must", "can", "could", "were to", "was able to"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "A: ___ I phone you tonight?\nB: Yes, you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "may / may",
              "must / might",
              "could / can’t",
              "shouldn’t / shouldn’t",
              "have to / had to"
            ],
            "answer": "may / may"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "But I ___ stay in England for six months, and not for a fortnight as I had planned.",
            "options": ["had to", "have to", "am able to", "can", "shall have"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "I ___ draw a circle with a pencil only, and you? Neither can I.",
            "options": ["can’t", "can", "may", "shan’t", "couldn’t"],
            "answer": "can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "Last week I ___ go to town on business trip as the Ministry of Education had asked me to come.",
            "options": ["had to", "might", "should", "could", "was able to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "If one person is careless with a library book, then it ___ be read by others.",
            "options": ["can’t", "couldn’t", "may", "can", "mightn’t"],
            "answer": "can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "After a book is written, it passes through the heads of very many different workers. Each worker works carefully, for there ___ not be any mistakes.",
            "options": ["must", "couldn’t", "could", "might", "has to"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "He tried, but ___ persuade nobody.",
            "options": ["could", "couldn’t", "can", "might", "won’t"],
            "answer": "couldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "People who know a foreign language ___ learn a second one easily.",
            "options": ["may", "should", "mustn’t", "can", "needn’t"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "___ I have a word with you, please?",
            "options": ["may", "had to", "have to", "must", "am able to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "At first I ___ skate well, now I ___ .",
            "options": [
              "couldn’t / can",
              "may / can",
              "mustn’t / can",
              "should / shouldn’t",
              "must / needn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "couldn’t / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "She said they ___ go to the cinema if they liked.",
            "options": ["must", "may", "can", "had to", "could"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "What is your sister doing?\nShe ___ be watching TV.",
            "options": ["may", "can’t", "needn’t", "has to", "could"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "I didn’t want to go there but I ___ .",
            "options": ["must", "might", "shall", "can’t", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "___ I go there now?\nNo, you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "can / hadn’t to",
              "am / aren’t",
              "must / needn’t",
              "might / could",
              "should / will"
            ],
            "answer": "must / needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "Where is he?\nHe ___ be walking in the park.",
            "options": ["can’t", "is able to", "has to", "must", "ought to"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Visitors ___ stay in the hospital after ten pm.",
            "options": [
              "might not",
              "needn’t",
              "couldn’t",
              "must not",
              "didn’t have to"
            ],
            "answer": "must not"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "We had an appointment yesterday afternoon but he ___ see me.",
            "options": [
              "might not",
              "cannot",
              "have to",
              "mustn’t",
              "wasn’t able to"
            ],
            "answer": "wasn’t able to"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "I didn’t ___ ring her up for she did it herself.",
            "options": ["had to", "could", "be to", "have to", "must"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "The rain was so sudden that everybody ___ take a shelter.",
            "options": ["can", "could", "have to", "are to", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "If you ___ fix a radio, you ___ repair a TV too.",
            "options": [
              "can / will be able to",
              "must / may",
              "couldn’t / can",
              "need / has to",
              "may / needn’t to"
            ],
            "answer": "can / will be able to"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "I’ve examined you very carefully. I think all you ___ is a good rest.\nBut I’m still feeling sick. Why don’t you look at my tongue? It ___ a rest too.",
            "options": [
              "must / may",
              "might / can",
              "need / could",
              "should / have to",
              "need / needs"
            ],
            "answer": "need / needs"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "You ___ do this work yourself, if you try.",
            "options": ["can", "had to", "must", "was able to", "were to do"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "Guests of the hotel ___ warn the clerk in advance when they leave.",
            "options": ["can", "may", "must", "is to", "had to"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "My mother ___ neither read nor write after the operation and now I ___ help her.",
            "options": [
              "have to / must",
              "could / have to",
              "couldn’t / had to",
              "were able / can",
              "might / need"
            ],
            "answer": "could / have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "___ I borrow your text book? I’ve left mine at home.",
            "options": ["am able to", "must", "have to", "need", "may"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "People ___ exercise regularly, otherwise they will get out of shape.",
            "options": ["must not", "should", "can", "might", "has to"],
            "answer": "should"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "“Ma,” said a little girl, “Willie wants the biggest piece of cake, and I think I ___ have it, because he was eating cakes two years before I was born.”",
            "options": ["couldn’t", "has to", "is to", "should", "had to"],
            "answer": "should"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "I live near my work. So you ___ go to the office by crowded buses.",
            "options": [
              "have to",
              "are able to",
              "don’t have to",
              "would have to",
              "can’t"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "I ___ go to the cinema yesterday.\nWhy?\nBecause I ___ complete my work.",
            "options": [
              "can’t / must",
              "couldn’t / had to",
              "didn’t have to / may",
              "wasn’t to / need",
              "should / have to"
            ],
            "answer": "couldn’t / had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "The skier broke his leg and ___ compete in the recent Olympic Games.",
            "options": ["couldn’t", "mustn’t", "had to", "can’t", "might"],
            "answer": "couldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "I ___ not translate this text yesterday. ___ you help me to translate it tonight?",
            "options": [
              "could / can",
              "can / can",
              "may / may",
              "had to / could",
              "can / must"
            ],
            "answer": "could / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "Does Larry ___ leave home at 7.30?",
            "options": ["have to", "must", "has to", "need", "should"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "___ any of you speak Italian?\nNo, but we are learning it and I hope we ___ speak it next year.",
            "options": [
              "must / will have to",
              "may / have got to",
              "can / shall be able to",
              "could / could",
              "might / had to"
            ],
            "answer": "can / shall be able to"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "___ I take your pen for a moment?\nCertainly.",
            "options": ["must", "may", "might", "should", "will"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "I ___ speak English last year but I ___ do it now.",
            "options": [
              "must / can",
              "could / can",
              "might / may",
              "couldn’t / can",
              "might / could"
            ],
            "answer": "couldn’t / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "Mother, ___ I go for a walk? I’ve done all my work.",
            "options": ["have to", "am to", "may", "must", "might"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "I was ill and ___ go to school for some days.",
            "options": ["can’t", "must", "could", "couldn’t", "can"],
            "answer": "couldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "___ we do this work now?\n___ . You can do it tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "Can / Yes, you can",
              "Must / No, you needn’t",
              "May / Yes, you may",
              "Could / Yes, you must",
              "Might / No, you might not"
            ],
            "answer": "Must / No, you needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "“___ I do anything for you?”, the secretary asked the stranger.",
            "options": ["can", "had to", "must", "have to", "am"],
            "answer": "can"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "___ we finish our work today?\nNo, you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "Can / couldn’t",
              "May / can",
              "Have to / can",
              "Must / needn’t",
              "Had / needn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "Must / needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "I ___ go to the library for books as I often write compositions at school.",
            "options": ["can", "could", "may", "might", "have to"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "It ___ rain this afternoon.",
            "options": ["had to", "may", "is able to", "could", "might"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "___ the director receive me now?",
            "options": ["Have to", "Is able", "Can", "Is to", "Has to"],
            "answer": "Can"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "Who ___ help him at 2 yesterday?",
            "options": ["have to", "is to", "can", "need", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "I said that after all that had happened I ___ run away to my aunt’s.",
            "options": ["could", "might", "had to", "need", "was able to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "___ I go to the cinema?\nNo, you ___ . The film is for grown ups.",
            "options": [
              "may / mustn’t",
              "can / needn’t",
              "could / can’t",
              "must / may not",
              "shall / haven’t"
            ],
            "answer": "may / mustn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "Teacher: “You ___ ring me up when you ___ my advice.",
            "options": [
              "could / need",
              "may / need",
              "can / will need",
              "must / needed",
              "have to / need"
            ],
            "answer": "may / need"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "“Never put off till tomorrow what you ___ do today.”",
            "options": ["have to", "must", "might", "can", "should"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "I ___ understand the rule; ___ I take the examination another time?\nYes, of course.",
            "options": [
              "can’t / may",
              "couldn’t / had to",
              "didn’t have to / may",
              "wasn’t to / need",
              "should / have to"
            ],
            "answer": "can’t / may"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "Pupils ___ speak only English at their English lessons.",
            "options": ["must not", "must", "cannot", "has to", "had to"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "The lecturer mentioned the name of the town several times, but unfortunately I ___ remember it.",
            "options": ["can", "could", "may", "could not", "may not"],
            "answer": "could not"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "Must I do this exercise too?\nNo, you ___ . It isn’t necessary.",
            "options": [
              "can’t",
              "may not",
              "mustn’t",
              "needn’t",
              "oughtn’t to"
            ],
            "answer": "needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "Mother, look, I ___ skate well.",
            "options": ["can", "may", "must", "have to", "ought to"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "I’m sorry you ___ smoke here.",
            "options": ["had to", "can’t", "could", "must", "have to"],
            "answer": "can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "We ___ protect our nature from pollution.",
            "options": ["need", "had to", "are to", "may", "must"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "He is very helpless, I ___ help him.",
            "options": ["need", "might", "have to", "can", "may"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "Excuse me, ___ you tell me the time?",
            "options": ["may", "must", "might", "can", "are able to"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "My grandfather’s ill and I ___ go to see him today, I ___ go with you.",
            "options": [
              "can / can’t",
              "have to / can’t",
              "may / have to",
              "need / must",
              "be able to / may not"
            ],
            "answer": "have to / can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "The Browns ___ not return on Sunday, as the weather was bad.",
            "options": ["may", "could", "have to", "must", "can’t"],
            "answer": "could"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "I looked through this book about 2 hours, but ___ find anything interesting.",
            "options": ["can’t", "couldn’t", "had to", "can", "hadn’t to"],
            "answer": "couldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "You ___ do this for it’s necessary.",
            "options": ["may", "can", "have to", "has", "could"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "You ___ work hard at your English.",
            "options": ["must", "mustn’t", "can’t", "has to", "may not"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "We ___ read much in the original if we want to learn a foreign language.",
            "options": ["had to", "can", "must", "may", "could"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "We ___ do it by midday if we had the instruments.",
            "options": ["may", "can", "must", "could", "might"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "You ___ get a visa before you go abroad next summer.",
            "options": ["may", "can", "could", "have to", "will have to"],
            "answer": "will have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "If you want to improve your English you ___ work very hard.",
            "options": ["can", "may", "are able to", "had to", "must"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "You’ve been traveling all day. You ___ be very tired.",
            "options": ["must", "can’t", "might", "ought to", "shouldn’t"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "My eyesight isn’t very good. I ___ wear glasses for reading.",
            "options": ["might", "have to", "can", "may", "could"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "He said that I ___ look around.",
            "options": ["might", "may", "can", "has to", "is able to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "He ___ agree with your suggestion.",
            "options": ["may not", "need", "are able to", "are to", "have to"],
            "answer": "may not"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "My son fell ill yesterday, I ___ stay at home.",
            "options": ["must", "can", "may", "need", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "I will not read this book, you ___ do it if you want.",
            "options": ["can", "might", "have to", "can’t", "must"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "___ you show me those black shoes? How much are they?",
            "options": ["may", "must", "can", "have to", "will have to"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "I ___ leave the party early last night, because I wasn’t very well.",
            "options": ["must", "may", "could", "have to", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "She ___ lift me up with one hand.",
            "options": ["may", "need", "can", "to have to", "to be able to"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "You ___ work if you don ‘t want to.",
            "options": ["must not", "can’t", "needn’t", "must", "has to"],
            "answer": "needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "You ___ come and have dinner with us some day.",
            "options": ["was able to", "could", "has to", "is to", "must"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "It was very difficult to hear. I ___ understand what she was saying.",
            "options": [
              "can’t",
              "may not",
              "wasn’t able to",
              "couldn’t",
              "could"
            ],
            "answer": "couldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "The teacher told us that we ___ work harder at our English.",
            "options": ["have", "must", "could", "may", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "A little girl comes up to her mother and asks if she ___ go to the park with her friend.",
            "options": ["couldn’t", "can’t", "must", "may", "has to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "If you are ill and ___ go to school you ___ learn everything what you have missed.",
            "options": [
              "can / must",
              "can’t / must",
              "may / can",
              "has to / may",
              "can’t / might"
            ],
            "answer": "can’t / must"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "The dog had run away and the children ___ find it though they were looking for it the whole day.",
            "options": ["can", "can’t", "could", "may", "could not"],
            "answer": "could not"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "As Mr. John hadn’t got the dictionary at hand, he ___ guess the meaning of the word.",
            "options": ["should", "can", "has to", "must", "had to"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "Mark Twain ___ easily ___ across the Mississippi River.",
            "options": [
              "must / swim",
              "had to / swam",
              "may / swim",
              "would / to swim",
              "could / swim"
            ],
            "answer": "could / swim"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "It was late but the pupils ___ stay at school for an additional lesson.",
            "options": ["could", "must", "had to", "needed", "might"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "The children have done their homework. I think they ___ have a rest now.",
            "options": ["may", "might", "are", "could", "will be able to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "Shall I retell the text?\n___ . You can only translate it.",
            "options": [
              "Yes, you will.",
              "Do, please.",
              "No, you didn’t.",
              "No, you needn’t.",
              "Yes, you may."
            ],
            "answer": "No, you needn’t."
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "Patient: Must I go to the hospital?\nDoctor: No, you ___ . You ___ stay at home.",
            "options": [
              "can’t / had to",
              "mustn’t / had to",
              "needn’t / may",
              "are able to / can",
              "shouldn’t / might"
            ],
            "answer": "needn’t / may"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "It ___ rain today. There are so many clouds in the sky.",
            "options": ["can", "has to", "may", "should", "mustn’t"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "I understood that he ___ never ___ back.",
            "options": [
              "will / come",
              "doesn’t / came",
              "won’t / home",
              "would / come",
              "wouldn’t / come"
            ],
            "answer": "would / come"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "My son is ill so I ___ stay at home.",
            "options": ["mustn’t", "has to", "can", "may", "have to"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "Must I do it? No, you ___ . It isn’t necessary.",
            "options": ["couldn’t", "may not", "needn’t", "can’t", "shouldn’t"],
            "answer": "needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "I feel sick and tired. So I ___ go to school.",
            "options": [
              "can",
              "could",
              "haven’t to",
              "am not able to",
              "am able to"
            ],
            "answer": "am not able to"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "He was very poor and ___ marry a woman eight years older than himself.",
            "options": ["must", "could", "needed", "had to", "might"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "Children ___ go to school at the age of 7.",
            "options": ["can", "must", "may", "has to", "could"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "___ I trouble you for a moment?\nYes, certainly. What ___ I do for you?",
            "options": [
              "can / might",
              "may / can",
              "must / may",
              "could / may",
              "can / must"
            ],
            "answer": "may / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 98,
            "question": "He ___ know her address. Ask him.",
            "options": ["need", "must", "could", "might", "have to"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 99,
            "question": "You knew he was ill. You ___ have visited him.",
            "options": ["can", "might", "need", "have to", "may"],
            "answer": "might"
          },
          {
            "id": 100,
            "question": "May I take this pen? No, you ___ .",
            "options": ["can", "may", "mustn’t", "need", "haven’t to"],
            "answer": "mustn’t"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "name": "Exercise 6",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 101,
            "question": "”What’s happened to the dog? It isn’t here.”\n”Dan ___ have taken it with him.”",
            "options": ["had to", "was to", "might", "may", "could"],
            "answer": "might"
          },
          {
            "id": 102,
            "question": "You ___ give it back to me before you go.",
            "options": ["might", "couldn’t", "must", "need", "had to"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 103,
            "question": "That’s a question nobody ___ answer.",
            "options": ["must not", "were to", "cannot", "might", "can"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 104,
            "question": "___ God be with you.",
            "options": ["can", "must", "may", "had to", "is to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 105,
            "question": "A fool man ___ ask more questions than a wise man ___ answer.",
            "options": [
              "may / can",
              "can / must",
              "may / might",
              "can / might",
              "must / could"
            ],
            "answer": "may / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 106,
            "question": "“Does Jack shave?”\n“No, he’s got a beard so he ___ shave.”",
            "options": [
              "hasn’t to",
              "hasn’t got to",
              "don’t have to",
              "can’t",
              "will be able to"
            ],
            "answer": "hasn’t got to"
          },
          {
            "id": 107,
            "question": "Don’t worry. You ___ do it just now. You ___ do it tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "must / can",
              "should / may",
              "can / could",
              "had to / must",
              "needn’t / can"
            ],
            "answer": "needn’t / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 108,
            "question": "I ___ speak English well now but I hope I ___ speak next year.",
            "options": [
              "could / can",
              "can’t / shall be able to",
              "must / shall have to",
              "may / may",
              "am able to / shall have to"
            ],
            "answer": "can’t / shall be able to"
          },
          {
            "id": 109,
            "question": "The driver ___ have taken a side road.",
            "options": ["shall", "need", "may", "have to", "is to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 110,
            "question": "He ___ have replaced the tire, it was still quite good.",
            "options": ["could", "can", "needn’t", "had to", "should"],
            "answer": "needn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 111,
            "question": "How ___ I tell her that her life will be ruined from this day on? I think, I can’t.",
            "options": ["must", "need", "may", "shall", "can"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 112,
            "question": "It was so warm that we ___ wear our coats. It was very pleasant.",
            "options": [
              "couldn’t",
              "didn’t have to",
              "shouldn’t",
              "mightn’t",
              "mustn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 113,
            "question": "They will get hungry on the train; I think, you ___ give them some sandwiches.",
            "options": ["should", "could", "might", "had to", "needn’t"],
            "answer": "should"
          },
          {
            "id": 114,
            "question": "You ___ a raincoat. You are wet through.",
            "options": [
              "must have worn",
              "may wear",
              "should have worn",
              "could wear",
              "needn’t have worn"
            ],
            "answer": "should have worn"
          },
          {
            "id": 115,
            "question": "“You ___ choose any present you like, take it, please”, said mother.",
            "options": ["might", "could", "may", "have to", "are able to"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 116,
            "question": "Have you looked through these newspapers?\nNo, I haven’t. I ___ write an article.",
            "options": ["has to", "had to", "mustn’t", "can", "might"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 117,
            "question": "We didn’t go out last night. We ___ to the cinema but we decided to stay at home.",
            "options": [
              "could have gone",
              "must have gone",
              "should go",
              "are to go",
              "needn’t go"
            ],
            "answer": "could have gone"
          },
          {
            "id": 118,
            "question": "I was at home yesterday. You ___ have called and taken the dictionary.",
            "options": ["must", "may", "could", "might", "have to"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 119,
            "question": "When I was a child I ___ draw well.\nAnd now? ___ you do it now?",
            "options": [
              "must / may",
              "could / can",
              "should / need",
              "may / could",
              "ought to / can’t"
            ],
            "answer": "could / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 120,
            "question": "That day as I ___ to be there at 5 sharp, I ___ to take a taxi.",
            "options": [
              "am / had to",
              "is / may",
              "was / had to",
              "were / can",
              "were / had to"
            ],
            "answer": "was / had to"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "name": "Exercise 7",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 121,
            "question": "You ___ read this book: you are grown up.",
            "options": ["may", "might", "has to", "can’t", "may not"],
            "answer": "may"
          },
          {
            "id": 122,
            "question": "I ___ come to see you tonight as I ___ answer many questions.",
            "options": [
              "can / may",
              "can’t / have to",
              "can’t / can not",
              "must / had to",
              "may / may not"
            ],
            "answer": "can’t / have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 123,
            "question": "Last night the plane ___ land because of the sudden change of the wind.",
            "options": ["must", "may", "has to", "had to", "can"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 124,
            "question": "___ he speak French as English last year?",
            "options": ["can", "may", "had to", "can’t", "could"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 125,
            "question": "She said that he ___ take her dictionary.",
            "options": ["may", "can", "is allowed", "is able", "might"],
            "answer": "might"
          },
          {
            "id": 126,
            "question": "As my sister was taking an examination I ___ look after her baby yesterday.",
            "options": ["could", "had to", "must", "was able to", "should"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 127,
            "question": "“He ___ in the house now,” thinks the girl.",
            "options": ["could", "may be", "might be", "had to be", "will be"],
            "answer": "might be"
          },
          {
            "id": 128,
            "question": "Your brother is ill, so he ___ go out for a walk.",
            "options": ["can", "could", "may", "might", "must not"],
            "answer": "must not"
          },
          {
            "id": 129,
            "question": "It ___ rain today, we ___ see clouds in the sky.",
            "options": [
              "has to / can",
              "must / have to",
              "could / can’t",
              "may / can",
              "might / must"
            ],
            "answer": "may / can"
          },
          {
            "id": 130,
            "question": "Charles Dickens ___ go to school at an early age, as he ___ help his family.",
            "options": [
              "should / would",
              "couldn’t / had to",
              "must / couldn’t",
              "might / should",
              "had not to / would"
            ],
            "answer": "couldn’t / had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 131,
            "question": "They ___ tell the truth, but they ___ .",
            "options": [
              "had to / can’t",
              "have to / couldn’t",
              "must / can’t",
              "are to / couldn’t",
              "may / had to"
            ],
            "answer": "must / can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 132,
            "question": "I have very little time and I ___ take a taxi.",
            "options": ["may", "could", "should", "have to", "have"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 133,
            "question": "You ___ this. Why didn’t you use a chance?",
            "options": [
              "can do",
              "could have done",
              "must do",
              "may do",
              "need do"
            ],
            "answer": "could have done"
          },
          {
            "id": 134,
            "question": "I ___ send him a letter yesterday.",
            "options": ["am", "can", "may", "had to", "should"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 135,
            "question": "She told him he ___ go home.",
            "options": ["may", "can", "ought", "might", "have to"],
            "answer": "might"
          },
          {
            "id": 136,
            "question": "No matter how she ___ try the door ___ open.",
            "options": [
              "can / should",
              "could / must",
              "should / will",
              "might / wouldn’t",
              "must / ought to"
            ],
            "answer": "might / wouldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 137,
            "question": "___ I take your book ? I ___ write many exercises tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "must / must",
              "should / have to",
              "may / shall have to",
              "might / had to",
              "can / would"
            ],
            "answer": "may / shall have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 138,
            "question": "She ___ get up and she ___ stay in bed as she is seriously ill.",
            "options": [
              "must / has to",
              "can’t / has to",
              "should / is to",
              "may / must",
              "is able / shall"
            ],
            "answer": "can’t / has to"
          },
          {
            "id": 139,
            "question": "My cousin ___ read and write when he was five.",
            "options": ["could", "may", "have to", "must", "can"],
            "answer": "could"
          },
          {
            "id": 140,
            "question": "We ___ to meet at the theatre entrance at a quarter to eight yesterday.",
            "options": ["are", "must", "have", "were", "couldn’t"],
            "answer": "were"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "name": "Exercise 8",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 141,
            "question": "They ___ do this the day after tomorrow. Now they are very busy.",
            "options": [
              "may",
              "can",
              "must",
              "will be able to",
              "were able to"
            ],
            "answer": "will be able to"
          },
          {
            "id": 142,
            "question": "I ___ write to Ann. I haven’t written to her for ages.",
            "options": ["can", "must", "had to", "could", "may"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 143,
            "question": "This work ___ be done at once.",
            "options": ["can", "must", "ought", "should", "may"],
            "answer": "must"
          },
          {
            "id": 144,
            "question": "The teacher said they ___ all go home.",
            "options": ["may", "have to", "might", "can", "be able to"],
            "answer": "have to"
          },
          {
            "id": 145,
            "question": "How ___ I get to the nearest bus stop?\nYou ___ go straight and then turn to the left.",
            "options": [
              "must / can",
              "can / must",
              "should / may",
              "may / have to",
              "could / might"
            ],
            "answer": "can / must"
          },
          {
            "id": 146,
            "question": "Oh, you are seriously ill. I think you ___ consult a doctor and if he tells you to keep to bed you ___ do.",
            "options": [
              "may / might",
              "must / can’t",
              "should / must",
              "have to / couldn’t",
              "has to / may"
            ],
            "answer": "should / must"
          },
          {
            "id": 147,
            "question": "Tom ___ pass his exam in Literature and now he is working hard as he ___ take it again.",
            "options": [
              "can’t / was able",
              "must / had to",
              "may / could",
              "couldn’t / has to",
              "can’t / had to"
            ],
            "answer": "couldn’t / has to"
          },
          {
            "id": 148,
            "question": "___ I come in? No, you ___ I am very busy now. I ___ write a report.",
            "options": [
              "may / can’t / must",
              "must / may not / had to",
              "may / can’t / must",
              "may / may not / can",
              "must / mustn’t / may"
            ],
            "answer": "may / can’t / must"
          },
          {
            "id": 149,
            "question": "___ I smoke here?\nNo, you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "can / may",
              "may / mustn’t",
              "can / should",
              "can / can’t",
              "may / need"
            ],
            "answer": "can / can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 150,
            "question": "You ___ break the body but you ___ break the spirit.",
            "options": [
              "may / can’t",
              "could / can’t",
              "must / must",
              "can / might not",
              "may / may"
            ],
            "answer": "may / can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 151,
            "question": "He ___ tell you how glad he is.",
            "options": ["was able to", "couldn’t", "can’t", "had to", "have"],
            "answer": "can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 152,
            "question": "He said that I ___ telephone him any time I liked.",
            "options": ["can", "will", "might", "have to", "will have to"],
            "answer": "might"
          },
          {
            "id": 153,
            "question": "I have a terrible headache. I ___ do anything.",
            "options": ["could", "can", "should", "can’t", "might"],
            "answer": "can’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 154,
            "question": "___ your son speak English?\nNo, but he ___ when he was a schoolboy.",
            "options": [
              "has to / must",
              "could / may",
              "might / can",
              "can / could",
              "may / must"
            ],
            "answer": "can / could"
          },
          {
            "id": 155,
            "question": "Find the synonym of the modal verb “must”.",
            "options": [
              "I might be wrong.",
              "We may go there.",
              "He needs a dictionary.",
              "You can say anything.",
              "He was to go to the south."
            ],
            "answer": "He was to go to the south."
          },
          {
            "id": 156,
            "question": "You ___ easily find the newspaper now where his article was printed.",
            "options": ["might", "need", "couldn’t", "had to", "can"],
            "answer": "can"
          },
          {
            "id": 157,
            "question": "He said that his father was ill and they ___ go to see the doctor yesterday.",
            "options": ["can", "had to", "are able", "can’t", "may"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 158,
            "question": "Sorry, I ___ go with you. I ___ finish my work.",
            "options": [
              "may not / must",
              "couldn’t / have to",
              "mustn’t / can",
              "can’t / must",
              "am / could"
            ],
            "answer": "can’t / must"
          },
          {
            "id": 159,
            "question": "Last year in April I ___ use my umbrella more often than in May.",
            "options": ["must", "can", "were able", "had to", "may"],
            "answer": "had to"
          },
          {
            "id": 160,
            "question": "“___ I have another cup of tea?”",
            "options": ["must", "might", "may", "would", "need"],
            "answer": "may"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Conditionals",
    "link": "conditionals",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "If I ___ my entrance exams I ___ the happiest man in the world.",
            "options": [
              "shall pass / would be",
              "passed / am",
              "passed / would have been",
              "will pass / be",
              "pass / shall be"
            ],
            "answer": "pass / shall be"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "We ___ to see you next Sunday, if I ___ well.",
            "options": [
              "shall come / shall get",
              "come / get",
              "comes / will get",
              "will come / get",
              "will come / will get"
            ],
            "answer": "will come / get"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ if the train ___ in time?",
            "options": [
              "will be / doing / come",
              "did / will not come",
              "do / didn’t / come",
              "have / done / came",
              "will / do / doesn’t come"
            ],
            "answer": "will / do / doesn’t come"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "If I ___ time I ___ you.",
            "options": [
              "have / help",
              "shall have / shall help",
              "shall have / help",
              "have / shall help",
              "has / help"
            ],
            "answer": "have / shall help"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "If you ___ tickets we ___ Paris.",
            "options": [
              "will buy / shall visit",
              "bought / visit",
              "buys / visited",
              "were buying / should visit",
              "buy / shall visit"
            ],
            "answer": "buy / shall visit"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "Tomorrow if the weather ___ fine we ___ out of the town for hours.",
            "options": [
              "is / shall get",
              "will be / shall get",
              "be / will get",
              "were / get",
              "was / get"
            ],
            "answer": "is / shall get"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "If you are free, watch the film they ___ on TV.",
            "options": [
              "shows",
              "showed",
              "are showing",
              "had showed",
              "have showed"
            ],
            "answer": "are showing"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "If the weather ___ fine we ___ to the park.",
            "options": [
              "is / shall go",
              "was / go",
              "are / go",
              "was / shall go",
              "would / should go"
            ],
            "answer": "is / shall go"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "If my friend ___ to our town next year I ___ him the sights of the city.",
            "options": [
              "shall come / show",
              "comes / shall show",
              "has come / is showing",
              "is coming / will show",
              "come / shows"
            ],
            "answer": "comes / shall show"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "They ___ not object to your plan if you ___ it up perfectly.",
            "options": [
              "do / will make",
              "did / won’t make",
              "will / make",
              "would / don’t make",
              "don’t / shall make"
            ],
            "answer": "will / make"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "If ___ rings me up, tell him that I’ll be in at 5.",
            "options": [
              "anything",
              "nobody",
              "everything",
              "something",
              "somebody"
            ],
            "answer": "somebody"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "Hark will play tennis if he ___ his work in time.",
            "options": [
              "finish",
              "finished",
              "finishing",
              "finishes",
              "will finish"
            ],
            "answer": "finishes"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "If you ___ after two hares you ___ none.",
            "options": [
              "run / catch",
              "run / will catch",
              "will run / will catch",
              "will run / catch",
              "ran / catch"
            ],
            "answer": "run / will catch"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "If we ___ English four times a week we’ll learn it.",
            "options": ["are having", "had", "have", "will have", "shall have"],
            "answer": "have"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "If you ___ in a hurry, leave that to me.",
            "options": ["will be", "were", "are", "was", "are being"],
            "answer": "were"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "If you ___ to please an English person, be very polite about his garden.",
            "options": ["want", "wanted", "are wanting", "will want", "wants"],
            "answer": "wanted"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "You ___ miss the train if you ___ a taxi.",
            "options": [
              "will / don’t take",
              " / don’t take",
              "will / won’t take",
              "don’t / take",
              "will / would not take"
            ],
            "answer": "will / don’t take"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "We ___ if they ___ .",
            "options": [
              "shall not know / come",
              "don’t know / will come",
              "didn’t know / will come",
              "haven’t known / come",
              "knew / will come"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t know / will come"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "If you want to be healthy you should ___ .",
            "options": [
              "sleep much",
              "attend all your classes",
              "go in for sports",
              "give up sport",
              "take up art"
            ],
            "answer": "go in for sports"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "If you ___ Oxford you ___ some interesting old buildings.",
            "options": [
              "will visit / will see",
              "visit / see",
              "visited / will see",
              "visits / see",
              "visit / will see"
            ],
            "answer": "visit / will see"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "He ___ the picture if it ___ him.",
            "options": [
              "will buy / impressed",
              "would buy / impresses",
              "will buy / impresses",
              "will buy / will impress",
              "has bought / impress"
            ],
            "answer": "will buy / impresses"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "If you ___ Ann tomorrow, can you tell her to phone?",
            "options": ["saw", "see", "will see", "had seen", "shall see"],
            "answer": "see"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "They are expecting us. They will be disappointed if we ___ .",
            "options": [
              "won’t come",
              "didn’t come",
              "haven’t come",
              "don’t come",
              "came"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t come"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "I wonder whether he ___ if nothing unexpected ___",
            "options": [
              "comes / detains",
              "will come / detain",
              "comes / will detain",
              "will come / will detain",
              "will come / detains"
            ],
            "answer": "will come / detains"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "I ___ my work in time if you ___ me.",
            "options": [
              "shall do / help",
              "should do / helps",
              "do / will help",
              "have done / help",
              "had done / would help"
            ],
            "answer": "shall do / help"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "The British people think, if you ___ tea ___ you.",
            "options": [
              "were depressed / cheers",
              "are depressed / will cheer",
              "shall be depressed / will cheer",
              "have been depressed / cheered",
              "had been depressed / was cheered"
            ],
            "answer": "are depressed / will cheer"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "If you ___ wisely you ___ cheerfully.",
            "options": [
              "command / will be obeyed",
              "commanded / would have been obeyed",
              "had commanded / would be obeyed",
              "command / will obey",
              "will command / are obeyed"
            ],
            "answer": "command / will be obeyed"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "If it ___ this winter, we ___ skiing.",
            "options": [
              "snow / go",
              "snows / shall go",
              "snowed / went",
              "snowed / had gone",
              "had snowed / had gone"
            ],
            "answer": "snows / shall go"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "I ___ them some money if they ___ me for.",
            "options": [
              "send / ask",
              "sent / asked",
              "will send / will ask",
              "would send / ask",
              "shall send / ask"
            ],
            "answer": "shall send / ask"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "If I ___ shopping I ___ some food tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "went / shall buy",
              "go / buy",
              "am going / would buy",
              "go / shall buy",
              "had gone / would buy"
            ],
            "answer": "go / shall buy"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "We ___ for a walk if the weather___ fine.",
            "options": [
              "shall go / will be",
              "go / is",
              "shall go / is",
              "go / will be",
              "goes / will be"
            ],
            "answer": "shall go / is"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "If the weather ___ fine we ___ for a walk.",
            "options": [
              "was / shall go",
              "is / shall go",
              "will be / shall go",
              "is / go",
              "was / went"
            ],
            "answer": "is / shall go"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "Mike ___ certainly if he ___ not busy.",
            "options": [
              "comes / is",
              "will come / will be",
              "will come / is",
              "comes / will be",
              "come / will be"
            ],
            "answer": "will come / is"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "I ___ next week if I can ___ a train ticket.",
            "options": [
              "go / get",
              "shall go / got",
              "went / got",
              "shall go / get",
              "was going / get"
            ],
            "answer": "shall go / get"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "I ___ happy if I ___ the university.",
            "options": [
              "shall be / shall enter",
              "am / shall enter",
              "am / enter",
              "shall be / enter",
              "was / enter"
            ],
            "answer": "shall be / enter"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "Our fate is in her hands now. If she ___ tickets we ___ away.",
            "options": [
              "has bought / would fly",
              "buys / shall fly",
              "buy / fly",
              "bought / fly",
              "bought / would have flown"
            ],
            "answer": "buys / shall fly"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "If you ___ in their talk they ___ .",
            "options": [
              "don’t interfere / will quarrel",
              "didn’t interfere / have quarreled",
              "doesn’t interfere / will quarrel",
              "interfere / should have quarreled",
              "interfere / are quarrelling"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t interfere / will quarrel"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "If he ___ in Tokyo he ___ us.",
            "options": [
              "was / will visit",
              "were / would visit",
              "will be / will visit",
              "is / would visit",
              "are / will visit"
            ],
            "answer": "were / would visit"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "If he ___ ill, he would stay at home.",
            "options": ["is", "be", "were", "am", "are"],
            "answer": "were"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "What would you do if a millionaire ___ you a lot of money.",
            "options": ["gave", "give", "will give", "giving", "gives"],
            "answer": "gave"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "If it ___ not so late I should go with you.",
            "options": ["was", "were", "is", "be", "are"],
            "answer": "were"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "If I ___ the car myself I ___ you use it.",
            "options": [
              "needed / would let",
              "don’t need / would let",
              "didn’t need / wouldn’t let",
              "didn’t need / would let",
              "doesn’t need / would let"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t need / would let"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "This house ___ better if they ___ it, ___ the grass and ___ flowers.",
            "options": [
              "will look / painted / cut / plant",
              "would look / paint / cut / planted",
              "looks / painted / cut / planted",
              "looked / painted / cut / planted",
              "would look / painted / cut / planted"
            ],
            "answer": "would look / painted / cut / planted"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "If I ___ you I ___ never her.",
            "options": [
              "am / shall forgive",
              "was / don’t forgive",
              "were / would forgive",
              "had been / forgave",
              "shall be / would have forgiven"
            ],
            "answer": "were / would forgive"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "I am sure Mike will lend you some money. I ___ if he refused.",
            "options": [
              "will be surprised",
              "am surprised",
              "would have been surprised",
              "would be surprised",
              "were surprised"
            ],
            "answer": "would be surprised"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "Many people would be out of work if that factory ___ down.",
            "options": [
              "had been closed",
              "were closed",
              "was closing",
              "is closed",
              "will be closed"
            ],
            "answer": "were closed"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "I ___ living in England if the weather ___ better.",
            "options": [
              "don’t mind / was",
              "didn’t mind / is",
              "wouldn’t mind / is",
              "wouldn’t mind / were",
              "wouldn’t mind / will be"
            ],
            "answer": "wouldn’t mind / were"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "She promised that nothing ___ till he ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "would be done / came",
              "is done / came",
              "will be done / comes",
              "has been done / came",
              "have been done / comes"
            ],
            "answer": "would be done / came"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "If he ___ generous, he ___ the poor.",
            "options": [
              "were/would have helped",
              "is/would have helped",
              "was/would help",
              "was/will help",
              "were/would help"
            ],
            "answer": "were/would help"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "If I ___ you I ___ French next year.",
            "options": [
              "am / learn",
              "was / shall learn",
              "am / should learn",
              "were / should learn",
              "were / learned"
            ],
            "answer": "were / should learn"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "I ___ so upset, if I ___ you.",
            "options": [
              "am / am",
              "wouldn’t be / were",
              "was / were",
              "won’t be / are",
              "shall be / would be"
            ],
            "answer": "wouldn’t be / were"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "If you ___ the Prime Minister what ___ you ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "are / would / have done",
              "were / would / do",
              "will be/will / do",
              "have been / are / doing",
              "will have been / would / be doing"
            ],
            "answer": "were / would / do"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "If he ___ here he ___ help you.",
            "options": [
              "is / would help",
              "were / would help",
              "would be / helped",
              "was / helps",
              "are / helping"
            ],
            "answer": "were / would help"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "I hoped if I ___ by the 10 o’clock train I ___ change for a bus.",
            "options": [
              "went / shan’t",
              "should go / hadn’t",
              "go / shan’t",
              "went / shouldn’t",
              "go / shouldn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "went / shouldn’t"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "Mr. Bond said if Mr. Blake ___ at 10 o’clock he ___ to see him later.",
            "options": [
              "is busy / will come",
              "will be busy / will come",
              "was busy / came",
              "was busy / would come",
              "is busy / comes"
            ],
            "answer": "was busy / would come"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "___ your mother wouldn’t be angry with you.",
            "options": [
              "If you didn’t get bad marks.",
              "If you got bad marks.",
              "If you haven’t got bad marks.",
              "If you get bad marks.",
              "If you don’t get bad marks."
            ],
            "answer": "If you didn’t get bad marks."
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "If I were you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "I shall wait",
              "I wait",
              "I would wait",
              "I waited",
              "I’m waiting"
            ],
            "answer": "I would wait"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "If all the seas ___ one sea, what a great sea it ___ .",
            "options": [
              "were/would be",
              "is/will be",
              "would be/were will",
              "be/will be",
              "were / will be"
            ],
            "answer": "were/would be"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "___ you really ___ me if I ___ away?",
            "options": [
              "would / follow / go",
              "will / follow / am going",
              "would / follow / went",
              "will / follow / would have gone",
              "will / follow / goes"
            ],
            "answer": "would / follow / went"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "If I ___ you I ___ him.",
            "options": [
              "am / will help",
              "to be / would help",
              "were / would help",
              "is / would have helped",
              "are / will help"
            ],
            "answer": "were / would help"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "If my brothers ___ time now they ___ help me.",
            "options": [
              "has / helps",
              "have had / have helped",
              "have / help",
              "is having / helped",
              "had / would help"
            ],
            "answer": "had / would help"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "If I ___ the power I ___ people smoking at school and public places.",
            "options": [
              "had / stop",
              "could have / would stop",
              "had / stopped",
              "had / would stop",
              "have / would stop"
            ],
            "answer": "had / would stop"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "If Helen ___ anywhere in the world she ___ in India.",
            "options": [
              "lived / live",
              "live / would live",
              "could live / would live",
              "didn’t live / would live",
              "lives / would live"
            ],
            "answer": "could live / would live"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "If I ___ you I ___ harder.",
            "options": [
              "am / will work",
              "will be / work",
              "be / shall work",
              "were / would work",
              "am / would have worked"
            ],
            "answer": "were / would work"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "If I ___ you I ___ it.",
            "options": [
              "am / regretted",
              "am / regrets",
              "were / wouldn’t regret",
              "is / didn’t regret",
              "was/regret"
            ],
            "answer": "were / wouldn’t regret"
          },
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "The boy ___ at home an hour before, if he ___ his school at one o’clock last Monday.",
            "options": [
              "would be / had left",
              "was / would leave",
              "had been / had left",
              "has been / left",
              "would have been / had left"
            ],
            "answer": "would have been / had left"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "___ he would have signed his name in the corner.",
            "options": [
              "If he would have painted the picture",
              "If he paints the picture",
              "If he painted the picture",
              "If he shall paint the picture",
              "If he had painted the picture"
            ],
            "answer": "If he had painted the picture"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "If you ___ him yesterday he ___ you everything.",
            "options": [
              "asked / told",
              "has asked / will tell",
              "asked / would tell",
              "had asked / would have told",
              "would ask / would have told"
            ],
            "answer": "had asked / would have told"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "If you had worked more, you ___ to translate this article yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "are able",
              "was able",
              "were able",
              "would have been able",
              "has been able"
            ],
            "answer": "would have been able"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "If you ___ to me yesterday, we ___ this article.",
            "options": [
              "came / shall translate",
              "would come / should translate",
              "had come / should have translated",
              "come / having translated",
              "were coming / should be translating"
            ],
            "answer": "had come / should have translated"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "If you ___ in time yesterday we ___ this work.",
            "options": [
              "had come / would have done",
              "came / would have done",
              "come / shall go",
              "will come / shall go",
              "come / would go"
            ],
            "answer": "had come / would have done"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "She ___ if she ___ that she was ill.",
            "options": [
              "won’t go out / knows",
              "didn’t go out / knew",
              "hasn’t gone out / has known",
              "wouldn’t have gone out / had known",
              "doesn’t go out / knows"
            ],
            "answer": "wouldn’t have gone out / had known"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "He failed his exam and he has to take it again in summer. If he ___ so many lessons he ___ it. But he didn’t follow the teacher’s advice.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t miss / would pass",
              "hadn’t missed / would have passed",
              "doesn’t miss / won’t pass",
              "has missed / will pass",
              "will miss / doesn’t pass"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t missed / would have passed"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "“I ___ my work if you___ me then. Thank you.”",
            "options": [
              "shan’t finish / don’t help.",
              "haven’t finished / don’t help.",
              "shouldn’t have finished / hadn’t helped.",
              "don’t finish / won’t help.",
              "didn’t finish / helped."
            ],
            "answer": "shouldn’t have finished / hadn’t helped."
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "Why didn’t you do the task? If he ___ everything from the start we ___ it earlier.",
            "options": [
              "hadn’t spoilt / would have done",
              "didn’t spoil / would have done",
              "doesn’t spoil / will do",
              "wouldn’t spoil / did",
              "spoils / shall have done"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t spoilt / would have done"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "The children ___ in the open air if the weather ___ better last Sunday.",
            "options": [
              "had played / was",
              "played / was",
              "would have played / had been",
              "will play / is",
              "would play / were"
            ],
            "answer": "would have played / had been"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "If we ___ a letter at 8 o’clock yesterday, we ___ on the same day.",
            "options": [
              "got / started",
              "had got / had started",
              "would get / had started",
              "had got / should have started",
              "should have got / had started"
            ],
            "answer": "had got / should have started"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "If you ___ so many lessons you ___ all the exams.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t miss / passed",
              "hadn’t missed / would have passed",
              "haven’t missed / would pass",
              "missed / will pass",
              "had missed / would have passed"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t missed / would have passed"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "I would have sent you a postcard while I was on holiday if I ___ your address.",
            "options": [
              "had",
              "was having",
              "had had",
              "will have",
              "would have"
            ],
            "answer": "had had"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "If the driver ___ the accident wouldn’t have happened.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t",
              "doesn’t stop",
              "won’t stop",
              "hadn’t stopped",
              "hasn’t stopped"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t stopped"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "If he ___ all right, he ___ with us yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "was / was",
              "had been / would have been",
              "were / would be",
              "had been / would be",
              "would be / would have been"
            ],
            "answer": "had been / would have been"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "If she ___ a new dress, I ___ her then.",
            "options": [
              "hadn’t been wearing / might have recognized",
              "didn’t wear / might recognize",
              "wasn’t wearing / might recognize",
              "wouldn’t wear / would recognize",
              "hadn’t been wearing / might recognize"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t been wearing / might have recognized"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "They ___ for the examination better if they ___ about it earlier.",
            "options": [
              "would prepare / knew",
              "prepare / know",
              "prepared / knew",
              "would have prepared / had known",
              "will prepare / know"
            ],
            "answer": "would have prepared / had known"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "If you ___ the dictionary yesterday I ___ to translate the article today.",
            "options": [
              "had given / would be able",
              "give / am able",
              "gave / will be able",
              "will give / am able",
              "have given / was able"
            ],
            "answer": "had given / would be able"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "If the help ___ in time, the experiment ___ tomorrow afternoon.",
            "options": [
              "had offered / would he completed",
              "was offered / will be completed",
              "had been offered / would be completed",
              "is offered / would be completed",
              "are offered / will be completed"
            ],
            "answer": "had been offered / would be completed"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "If you ___ these pills yesterday you ___ well now.",
            "options": [
              "had taken / would be",
              "took / would be",
              "had taken / had been",
              "took / will be",
              "would take / would be"
            ],
            "answer": "had taken / would be"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "If I had gone to the party last night, I ___ tired now.",
            "options": ["will be", "am", "would be", "would have been", "was"],
            "answer": "would be"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "She didn’t know if the letter ___ by the time she ___",
            "options": [
              "would be delivered / will come",
              "would deliver / comes",
              "will be delivered / came",
              "would have been delivered / came",
              "was delivered / came"
            ],
            "answer": "would have been delivered / came"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "If he ___ English well, he ___ the article without difficulty yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "knew / would have translated",
              "know / had been translated",
              "has known / will have translate",
              "would know / will translate",
              "would have known / would have translated"
            ],
            "answer": "knew / would have translated"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "If you ___ harder last year you ___ English well now.",
            "options": [
              "worked / had known",
              "work / will know",
              "had worked / would know",
              "will work / know",
              "would work / would have known"
            ],
            "answer": "had worked / would know"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "If you ___ harder you ___ more money and now you ___ to buy a car.",
            "options": [
              "have worked / would earn / could",
              "had worked / would have earned / would be able",
              "had worked / would earn / will be able",
              "has worked / would have earned / could",
              "worked / would earn / might"
            ],
            "answer": "had worked / would have earned / would be able"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "If you ___ your swimming suit you would be able to go for a swim now.",
            "options": [
              "don’t leave",
              "weren’t leaving",
              "will not leave",
              "haven’t left",
              "hadn’t left"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t left"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Comparatives - Superlatives",
    "link": "comparatives-superlatives",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "It was ___ music I have ever heard.",
            "options": [
              "more beautiful",
              "less beautiful",
              "the most beautiful",
              "beautiful",
              "most beautiful"
            ],
            "answer": "the most beautiful"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "It’s ___ powder I have ever used.",
            "options": ["good", "-", "the best", "best", "better"],
            "answer": "the best"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "John is ___ of all to act.",
            "options": ["quickest", "quick", "-", "quicker", "the quickest"],
            "answer": "the quickest"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "He is ___ strong ___ his brother.",
            "options": [
              "as / like",
              "similar / as",
              "as / as",
              "strong / than",
              "so / as"
            ],
            "answer": "as / as"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "English grammar is ___ than Russian one.",
            "options": [
              "easy",
              "easier",
              "the easiest",
              "as easy as",
              "not so easy"
            ],
            "answer": "easier"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "I have ___ time than he does.",
            "options": ["bigger", "larger", "most", "less", "least"],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "This girl is ___ intelligent than the rest of the class.",
            "options": ["most", "the most", "more", "the more", "much"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "Two heads are ___ than one.",
            "options": ["good", "bad", "worse", "worst", "better"],
            "answer": "better"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "Alice came late, Philip came later, and Tony ___",
            "options": ["latest", "last", "the latest", "later", "the last"],
            "answer": "the latest"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "Mark Twain, one of ___ and ___ American writers, lived in a small town in his childhood.",
            "options": [
              "greater / most popular",
              "great / more popular",
              "the greatest / most popular",
              "more great / the most popular",
              "most great / the popular"
            ],
            "answer": "the greatest / most popular"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "-Why didn’t you discuss this question yesterday?\n-It was ___ important than the others.",
            "options": ["little", "least", "the least", "-", "less"],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "Your English is much ___ now. You’ve made___ mistakes this time.",
            "options": [
              "best / least",
              "better / less",
              "the best / less",
              "good / less",
              "best / the least"
            ],
            "answer": "better / less"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "The Thames is ___ river in Great Britain.",
            "options": ["the longest", "long", "longest", "-", "longer"],
            "answer": "the longest"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "Do you have ___ or ___ rain this autumn than the last one.",
            "options": [
              "many / little",
              "more / less",
              "more / fewer",
              "much / less",
              "more / few"
            ],
            "answer": "more / less"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "Please, tell me something ___ than this old joke.",
            "options": [
              "interesting",
              "less interesting",
              "more interesting",
              "the most interesting",
              "the least interesting"
            ],
            "answer": "more interesting"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "This question is ___ than the first one, let’s discuss it tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "important",
              "less important",
              "the most important",
              "the least important",
              "-"
            ],
            "answer": "less important"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Do you have ___ or ___ sunny days this summer?",
            "options": [
              "more / few",
              "many / less",
              "much / little",
              "more / less",
              "many / few"
            ],
            "answer": "more / less"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "We have ___ money than they have.",
            "options": ["little", "much", "less", "few", "many"],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "Please, give me this bouquet of flowers. I think it is___ than the rest ones.",
            "options": [
              "beautiful / expensive",
              "more beautiful / more expensive",
              "the most beautiful / most expensive",
              "beautiful / most expensive",
              "most beautiful / most expensive"
            ],
            "answer": "more beautiful / more expensive"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "Of the four girls Marcia is ___ .",
            "options": [
              "prettiest",
              "prettier",
              "-",
              "the prettiest",
              "prettier"
            ],
            "answer": "the prettiest"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "It’s ___ to go by car than by train.",
            "options": ["cheap", "cheaper", "-", "cheapest", "the cheapest"],
            "answer": "cheaper"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "It is much ___ to speak English than to understand",
            "options": [
              "-",
              "the most difficult",
              "more difficult",
              "difficult",
              "most difficult"
            ],
            "answer": "more difficult"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "He’s ___ intelligent than my brother.",
            "options": ["most", "good", "better", "more", "last"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "He is ___ among his classmates.",
            "options": ["old", "taller", "the youngest", "short", "higher"],
            "answer": "the youngest"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "This is ___ place I’ve ever seen.",
            "options": ["dirty", "the dirtiest", "more dirty", "dirtier", "-"],
            "answer": "the dirtiest"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "What is ___ crime than loss of time.",
            "options": ["greater", "greatest", "great", "-", "most great"],
            "answer": "greater"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "He came home in the ___ mood.",
            "options": [
              "sun",
              "sunniest",
              "more sunny",
              "much sunny",
              "sunnier"
            ],
            "answer": "sunniest"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "False friend is ___ than open enemies.",
            "options": ["worst", "worse", "the worst", "-", "bad"],
            "answer": "worse"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "“Why do you always buy five loaves, no ___ and ___?”",
            "options": [
              "many / little",
              "less / fewer",
              "more / much",
              "more / less",
              "most / less"
            ],
            "answer": "more / less"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "It’s ___ in here than it is in the street.",
            "options": ["hot", "the hottest", "-", "hotter", "hottest"],
            "answer": "hotter"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "Are the streets of London ___ or ___ than the streets of Belfast?",
            "options": [
              "the narrowest / wider",
              "narrow / wide",
              "narrower / wider",
              "more narrow / wide",
              "most narrow / most wide"
            ],
            "answer": "narrower / wider"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "I make ___ mistakes now than last year.",
            "options": ["few", "fewer", "-", "the fewest", "fewest"],
            "answer": "fewer"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "The weather is much ___ pleasant than it usually is at this time.",
            "options": ["most", "more", "the most", "little", "-"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "To spend summer at the seaside is ___ pleasant than in the town.",
            "options": ["-", "less", "the most", "more", "the least"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "It is ___ and ___ to live here than there.",
            "options": [
              "warm / most pleasant",
              "warmer / pleasant",
              "warmest / pleasanter",
              "warmer / more pleasant",
              "warm / more pleasant"
            ],
            "answer": "warmer / more pleasant"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "Are the streets ___ and ___ than they were some years ago ?",
            "options": [
              "wide / cleaner",
              "wider / cleanest",
              "widest / cleaner",
              "widest / cleanest",
              "wider / cleaner"
            ],
            "answer": "wider / cleaner"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "Lake Baikal is ___ lake in the world.",
            "options": ["deeper", "the deepest", "deep", "deepest", "-"],
            "answer": "the deepest"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "Many people think Scotland is ___ than England.",
            "options": [
              "most beautiful",
              "the least beautiful",
              "least beautiful",
              "more beautiful",
              "beautiful"
            ],
            "answer": "more beautiful"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "My luggage was ___ than my friend’s.",
            "options": ["good", "the best", "many", "less", "the worst"],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "Her love must be ___ than mine.",
            "options": [
              "the deepest",
              "most deep",
              "deepest",
              "deeper",
              "deep"
            ],
            "answer": "deeper"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "His plan is ___ practical of all.",
            "options": ["-", "more", "much", "the most", "most"],
            "answer": "the most"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "I think it is ___ beautiful landscape I’ve ever seen.",
            "options": ["more", "more", "the most", "the best", "worst"],
            "answer": "the most"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "Our garden is ___ than that of the neighbor’s.",
            "options": [
              "little",
              "the least",
              "most difficult",
              "the best",
              "less"
            ],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "Which are ___ comfortable, sandals or tennis shoes?",
            "options": ["most", "little", "more", "much", "any"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "In the second half, the team played ___ and the game ended in a draw.",
            "options": [
              "earliest",
              "the worst",
              "interesting",
              "the most interesting",
              "worse"
            ],
            "answer": "worse"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "Area of Brazil is ___ than that of England.",
            "options": ["less", "most", "much", "larger", "many"],
            "answer": "larger"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "He was ___ angry than I had expected.",
            "options": ["most", "more", "much", "better", "good"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "Which question do you think is ___ difficult one?",
            "options": ["-", "much", "more", "the most", "most"],
            "answer": "the most"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "There is ___ milk in this jug than in that one.",
            "options": ["most", "the most", "the least", "little", "less"],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "The weather today is ___ than yesterday.",
            "options": ["good", "bad", "fine", "worse", "the worst"],
            "answer": "worse"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "Her version is ___ original than yours.",
            "options": ["much", "the most", "more", "many", "the least"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "Mr. Smith liked his ___ son than others.",
            "options": ["older", "elder", "the oldest", "all", "the eldest"],
            "answer": "elder"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "Yesterday Camilla was ___ girl there.",
            "options": ["happy", "happiest", "the happiest", "-", "happier"],
            "answer": "the happiest"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "Traveling is ___ in summer than in winter.",
            "options": [
              "interesting",
              "more interesting",
              "the most interesting",
              "farther",
              "largest"
            ],
            "answer": "more interesting"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "Which bird flies ___, the swallow or the gull?",
            "options": ["-", "fast", "faster", "the fastest", "fastest"],
            "answer": "faster"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "My clothes have never been ___ than this.",
            "options": ["cleaner", "cleanest", "clean", "-", "the cleanest"],
            "answer": "cleaner"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "My dress is ___ than yours, isn’t it?",
            "options": ["long", "-", "the longest", "longest", "longer"],
            "answer": "longer"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "Which is ___ country in the UK?",
            "options": [
              "industrial",
              "the most industrial",
              "more industrial",
              "most industrial",
              "industrial"
            ],
            "answer": "the most industrial"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "Do you speak English ___ than Spanish?",
            "options": [
              "most fluently",
              "fluent",
              "rather fluent",
              "fluently",
              "more fluently"
            ],
            "answer": "more fluently"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "Margaret types ___ than Mary does.",
            "options": ["fast", "-", "faster", "the fastest", "fastest"],
            "answer": "faster"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "This chair is ___ comfortable than that one.",
            "options": ["-", "little", "less", "the least", "least"],
            "answer": "less"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "Both of them are skiing very badly, but she is skiing even ___ than he is.",
            "options": ["bad", "-", "worse", "the worst", "worst"],
            "answer": "worse"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "The ___ you start, the ___ you’ll finish.",
            "options": [
              "soon / more quickly",
              "sooner / more quickly",
              "sooner / quickly",
              "soon / quickly",
              "more sooner / more quickly"
            ],
            "answer": "sooner / more quickly"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "The play I saw yesterday was ___ than this one.",
            "options": ["bad", "worse", "worst", "the worst", "-"],
            "answer": "worse"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "Mary is much ___ than Ann, though they are both alike.",
            "options": ["tall", "taller", "the tallest", "-", "tallest"],
            "answer": "taller"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "My arm felt hot but that ache was ___ than the pain that burned in my breast.",
            "options": [
              "stronger",
              "the strongest",
              "strongest",
              "strong",
              "-"
            ],
            "answer": "stronger"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "Your dictation is ___ of all.",
            "options": ["bad", "worse", "good", "well", "the worst"],
            "answer": "the worst"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "My room is ___ than yours.",
            "options": ["large", "-", "larger", "the largest", "largest"],
            "answer": "larger"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "“Family album” is ___ than “Follow me”.",
            "options": [
              "interesting",
              "most interesting",
              "more interesting",
              "the most interesting",
              "as interesting"
            ],
            "answer": "more interesting"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "This exercise is ___ than the last one.",
            "options": ["-", "good", "best", "better", "the best"],
            "answer": "better"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "The longer the way the ___ tired we are.",
            "options": ["most", "more", "the most", "-", "much"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "Today ___ and ___ people come to understand that learning English is ___ .",
            "options": [
              "many / much / most useful",
              "many / more / more useful",
              "little / less / useful",
              "most / less / less useful",
              "more / more / useful"
            ],
            "answer": "more / more / useful"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "___ goods you sell, ___ profit you’ll make.",
            "options": [
              "more / more",
              "the more / more",
              "more / the more",
              "the more / the more",
              "the most / the most"
            ],
            "answer": "the more / the more"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "Yesterday was ___ day we’ve had this summer.",
            "options": [
              "hotter",
              "hot",
              "the hottest",
              "hottest",
              "much hotter"
            ],
            "answer": "the hottest"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "Girls are much ___ than boys.",
            "options": [
              "quiet",
              "the quietest",
              "so quiet",
              "quieter",
              "too quiet"
            ],
            "answer": "quieter"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "Do you need any ___ help?",
            "options": ["much", "more", "many", "most", "the most"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "Actions speak ___ than words.",
            "options": [
              "loudest",
              "less louder",
              "most loudest",
              "louder",
              "loudly"
            ],
            "answer": "louder"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "It is ___ work I’ve ever done.",
            "options": ["bad", "worse", "better", "the worst", "best"],
            "answer": "the worst"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "Uncle Nick was the ___ son of the family.",
            "options": ["old", "young", "big", "elder", "next"],
            "answer": "elder"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "This room is ___ than that one.",
            "options": [
              "large",
              "little",
              "the smallest",
              "the least",
              "smaller"
            ],
            "answer": "smaller"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "The twenty-second of December is ___ day of the year.",
            "options": [
              "short",
              "much shorter",
              "shorter",
              "the shortest",
              "less short"
            ],
            "answer": "the shortest"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "Who is ___ important person in the history of your country?",
            "options": ["more", "less", "high", "popular", "the most"],
            "answer": "the most"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "I think, today the British television program “The Weakest Link” is ___ popular of all the TV programs.",
            "options": ["more", "much", "the most", "-", "most"],
            "answer": "the most"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "John is ___ but ___ boy in the family.",
            "options": [
              "taller / the youngest",
              "the tallest / the youngest",
              "taller / younger",
              "more tall / the most young",
              "the tallest / more young"
            ],
            "answer": "the tallest / the youngest"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "This is ___ rule in this book.",
            "options": [
              "difficult",
              "more difficult",
              "most difficult",
              "the most difficult",
              "much difficult"
            ],
            "answer": "the most difficult"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "Antalya in my opinion is ___ place for rest.",
            "options": ["good", "less", "the least", "the best", "better"],
            "answer": "the best"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "The story I have read is ___ in this book.",
            "options": [
              "the most interesting",
              "more interesting",
              "less interesting",
              "much interesting",
              "few interesting"
            ],
            "answer": "the most interesting"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "They showed me their best suits but, if these are their ___ suits, what are their ___ ones like.",
            "options": [
              "best / worst",
              "better / worst",
              "best / worse",
              "worse / better",
              "good / worst"
            ],
            "answer": "best / worst"
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "He works the ___ but earns the ___ .",
            "options": [
              "harder / less",
              "more / most",
              "less / harder",
              "hardest / least",
              "least / harder"
            ],
            "answer": "hardest / least"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "Monte Carlo is one of ___ beautiful cities in the world.",
            "options": ["much", "the most", "much more", "the least", "less"],
            "answer": "the most"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "Let me know if you hear any ___ news.",
            "options": ["many", "more", "most", "the most", "much"],
            "answer": "more"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "It’s ___ weather anyone can remember.",
            "options": ["better", "the worst", "bad", "worse", "least"],
            "answer": "the worst"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "I think the cotton of Turkmenistan is one of ___ in the world.",
            "options": ["better", "good", "the best", "longer", "richer"],
            "answer": "the best"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "I have done ___ part of my homework.",
            "options": [
              "difficult",
              "more difficult",
              "most difficult",
              "the most difficult",
              "-"
            ],
            "answer": "the most difficult"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "Can’t you type ___?",
            "options": [
              "shortly",
              "more carefully",
              "hardly",
              "nearly",
              "completely"
            ],
            "answer": "more carefully"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "The teacher said that the results of our tests were not good. She added that ___ of all was mine.",
            "options": ["bad", "better", "worse", "good", "the worst"],
            "answer": "the worst"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "Which season is ___ in Thailand?",
            "options": [
              "rainy",
              "the rainiest",
              "most rainy",
              "more rainy",
              "raining"
            ],
            "answer": "the rainiest"
          },
          {
            "id": 98,
            "question": "___ I can stay is three hours.",
            "options": [
              "long",
              "longer",
              "more longer",
              "the longest",
              "much longer"
            ],
            "answer": "the longest"
          },
          {
            "id": 99,
            "question": "Unfortunately her disease was ___ than we thought at first.",
            "options": [
              "more serious",
              "serious",
              "the most serious",
              "most serious",
              "the more serious"
            ],
            "answer": "more serious"
          },
          {
            "id": 100,
            "question": "This is ___ clown I’ve ever seen.",
            "options": ["good", "better", "the best", "well", "bad"],
            "answer": "the best"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Infinitive - Gerund",
    "link": "infinitive-gerund",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "He admitted ___ the car but denied ___ it by himself.",
            "options": [
              "stealing / doing",
              "to steal / doing",
              "stealing / to do",
              "to steal / to do",
              "stealing / to be done"
            ],
            "answer": "stealing / doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "How do you feel if someone laughs at you? I hate people ___ at me.",
            "options": [
              "laughed",
              "laughing",
              "being laughed",
              "to be laughed",
              "to be laughing"
            ],
            "answer": "laughing"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "We often hear her ___ at concerts.",
            "options": ["sings", "singing", "sang", "to sing", "have sung"],
            "answer": "singing"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "Mother wants him ___ to the country during the summer.",
            "options": ["goes", "go", "to go", "will go", "went"],
            "answer": "to go"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "___ many books on history helps school children to get knowledge about the past of different nations.",
            "options": ["read", "reads", "has read", "will read", "reading"],
            "answer": "reading"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "As well as ___ I like ___ .",
            "options": [
              "running/walking",
              "run/walk",
              "run/walked",
              "running/walked",
              "run/to walk"
            ],
            "answer": "running/walking"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "The man ___ the newspaper is my brother.",
            "options": ["read", "reads", "has read", "reading", "will read"],
            "answer": "reading"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "It is very pleasant ___ in the river on hot days in the summers.",
            "options": [
              "bathe",
              "bathing",
              "bathed",
              "to bathe",
              "having bathed"
            ],
            "answer": "to bathe"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "He warmed himself by ___ hot tea.",
            "options": [
              "drinking",
              "drank",
              "drunk",
              "to drink",
              "is drinking"
            ],
            "answer": "drinking"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "It’s very pleasant ___ on the beach in summer.",
            "options": ["lie", "to lie", "lay", "lain", "lying"],
            "answer": "to lie"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "I hope my dream will come true this year.\nAnd what do you dream of?\nOh, I dream of ___ a law school and ___ a lawyer.",
            "options": [
              "to enter / to become",
              "enter / become",
              "entering / becoming",
              "entered / become",
              "to enter / becoming"
            ],
            "answer": "entering / becoming"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "He sat in the arm chair ___ a newspaper.",
            "options": ["read", "reads", "reading", "had read", "is read"],
            "answer": "reading"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "___ English is the best way of ___ it.",
            "options": [
              "speak / learn",
              "speaking / learning",
              "to speak / to learn",
              "spoke / learning",
              "speak / learning"
            ],
            "answer": "speaking / learning"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "She dreams of her son’s ___ a director of the company.",
            "options": [
              "becoming",
              "is becoming",
              "become",
              "became",
              "was becoming"
            ],
            "answer": "becoming"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "Why didn’t you try ___ yourself a job?",
            "options": [
              "found",
              "have found",
              "finding",
              "to find",
              "to be found"
            ],
            "answer": "finding"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "We watched the coastline ___ slowly.",
            "options": [
              "recede",
              "to recede",
              "recedes",
              "have receded",
              "receded"
            ],
            "answer": "recede"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Nobody heard her ___ English.",
            "options": [
              "spoke",
              "speaks",
              "speak",
              "was speaking",
              "had spoken"
            ],
            "answer": "speak"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "We stopped at the motorway services ___ something to eat.",
            "options": ["to get", "to have got", "was getting", "get", "got"],
            "answer": "to get"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "I’m not really interested in ___ to the University.",
            "options": ["go", "went", "going", "being gone", "have gone"],
            "answer": "going"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "This article is worth ___ .",
            "options": ["reading", "read", "to read", "has read", "will read"],
            "answer": "reading"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "They have got enough money ___ to the cinema.",
            "options": ["go", "having gone", "to have gone", "to go", "going"],
            "answer": "to go"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "I saw him ___ a newspaper.",
            "options": [
              "to read",
              "to have read",
              "reading",
              "to be reading",
              "having read"
            ],
            "answer": "reading"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "Watch me ___ the fence.",
            "options": [
              "jumping",
              "jumped",
              "to jump",
              "had jumped",
              "did jump"
            ],
            "answer": "jumping"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "She decided ___ to Spain for her holidays.",
            "options": ["to go", "go", "goes", "to be going", "to have gone"],
            "answer": "to go"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "In winter he spends much time in the mountains, he is fond of ___ .",
            "options": [
              "to skate",
              "skated",
              "skating",
              "to be skated",
              "having skated"
            ],
            "answer": "skating"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "The street was full of people ___ and ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "laughed / gone",
              "laughing / going",
              "having laughed / go",
              "to laugh / to go",
              "to be laughed / going"
            ],
            "answer": "laughing / going"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "___ a foreign language you can ___ great opportunities in your life.",
            "options": [
              "know / have",
              "knowing / to have",
              "knowing / have",
              "knows / having",
              "knowing / having"
            ],
            "answer": "knowing / have"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "On ___ the classroom the teacher asked to the pupil on duty, \"Who is absent?\"",
            "options": [
              "entering",
              "entered",
              "to enter",
              "be entering",
              "being entered"
            ],
            "answer": "entering"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "Working in the garden it is pleasant ___ to music.",
            "options": [
              "listening",
              "listened",
              "to listen",
              "after listening",
              "having listened"
            ],
            "answer": "to listen"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "You are lucky you have not got a child ___ .",
            "options": [
              "to look after",
              "should look after",
              "looking after",
              "having looked after",
              "is looking after"
            ],
            "answer": "to look after"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "She saw the girl ___ in the yard.",
            "options": [
              "playing",
              "on playing",
              "played",
              "to play",
              "was playing"
            ],
            "answer": "playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "He usually left us without ___ a word.",
            "options": ["to say", "saying", "said", "say", "having been said"],
            "answer": "saying"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "I’m fond of ___ in the river.",
            "options": ["have swum", "swam", "swim", "swimming", "having swum"],
            "answer": "swimming"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "The aim of the exhibition is ___ experience.",
            "options": [
              "to be exchanged",
              "exchanged",
              "to have exchanged",
              "to exchange",
              "being exchanged"
            ],
            "answer": "to exchange"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "The horse ___ the race ___ the winner of the same event two years ago.",
            "options": [
              "led / was",
              "leading / is",
              "leading / was",
              "to lead / was",
              "leads / being"
            ],
            "answer": "leading / was"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "His mother was against his ___ football.",
            "options": ["play", "was playing", "played", "to play", "playing"],
            "answer": "playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "Miss Benson was looking forward to ___ the title role in the new play.",
            "options": [
              "play",
              "playing",
              "to be played",
              "played",
              "being played"
            ],
            "answer": "playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "Pete likes ___ . His dream is to visit Japan.",
            "options": [
              "painting",
              "reading",
              "writing",
              "traveling",
              "swimming"
            ],
            "answer": "traveling"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "My friends need ___ English.",
            "options": [
              "learns",
              "to learn",
              "to have learned",
              "to be learned",
              "having learned"
            ],
            "answer": "to learn"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "When I came into the room she stopped ___ T.V.",
            "options": [
              "watching",
              "watch",
              "watched",
              "on watching",
              "watches"
            ],
            "answer": "watching"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "Which of the boys ___ in the yard is Ted?",
            "options": ["play", "played", "plays", "is playing", "playing"],
            "answer": "playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "We saw them ___ the street.",
            "options": [
              "crossed",
              "crossing",
              "will cross",
              "had crossed",
              "will be crossing"
            ],
            "answer": "crossing"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "It’s never too late ___ .",
            "options": [
              "being learned",
              "not to learn",
              "learned",
              "learning",
              "to learn"
            ],
            "answer": "to learn"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "The girls ___ in the garden are my sisters.",
            "options": [
              "played",
              "to play",
              "playing",
              "on playing",
              "are playing"
            ],
            "answer": "playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "I like ___ the people happy.",
            "options": [
              "to have made",
              "made",
              "making",
              "having made",
              "being made"
            ],
            "answer": "making"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "Besides ___ I like ___ swimming competitions.",
            "options": [
              "swimming / to watch",
              "to swim / to watch",
              "swimming / watched",
              "to swim / watching",
              "swimming / watch"
            ],
            "answer": "swimming / to watch"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "Tom wants to read a book but Susan makes him ___ something in the paper. It’s an advertisement for a better job. She wants him ___ for this job.",
            "options": [
              "to read / to apply",
              "to read / apply",
              "read / to apply",
              "reading / apply",
              "to read / applying"
            ],
            "answer": "to read / apply"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "She left the room without ___ good bye.",
            "options": ["say", "saying", "to say", "said", "on saying"],
            "answer": "saying"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "The friends spoke of their ___ together.",
            "options": ["to go", "going", "gone", "is going", "on going"],
            "answer": "going"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "If your plane has crashed high in the mountains, it’s best ___ close to the plane. Rescuers have got a better chance of ___ the plane than one person alone.",
            "options": [
              "to keep / finding",
              "keeping / found",
              "kept / to have found",
              "kept / not to find",
              "keeping / being found"
            ],
            "answer": "to keep / finding"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "Robert saw the doctor ___ the patient.",
            "options": [
              "to examine",
              "to have examined",
              "having examined",
              "being examined",
              "examine"
            ],
            "answer": "examine"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "The girl ___ in the yard asked me the time.",
            "options": ["play", "to play", "played", "playing", "was playing"],
            "answer": "playing"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "The emperor thought of ___ his state powerful.",
            "options": [
              "becoming",
              "become",
              "became",
              "having become",
              "had become"
            ],
            "answer": "becoming"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "Mother was anxious ___ her family.",
            "options": [
              "to see",
              "seeing",
              "to be seen",
              "having seen",
              "being seen"
            ],
            "answer": "to see"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "I can’t help ___ you about it.",
            "options": [
              "to tell",
              "telling",
              "having told",
              "having been told",
              "being told"
            ],
            "answer": "telling"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "Many builders and engineers from other republics began ___ to build new houses in Moscow in 1995.",
            "options": [
              "helping",
              "would help",
              "helped",
              "shall help",
              "having helped"
            ],
            "answer": "helping"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "I have never heard him ___ French.",
            "options": [
              "to speak",
              "speaking",
              "spoken",
              "being spoken",
              "to have spoken"
            ],
            "answer": "speaking"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "Nobody expected him ___ Lola.",
            "options": [
              "marry",
              "married",
              "to marry",
              "will marry",
              "would marry"
            ],
            "answer": "to marry"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "This holiday is worth ___ .",
            "options": [
              "celebrates",
              "celebrated",
              "celebrating",
              "have celebrated",
              "to celebrate"
            ],
            "answer": "celebrating"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "Frank is in hospital. He feels bad. He has to give up ___ and ___ beer. But he can’t. He says to his wife, ‘’Would you mind ___ some cigarettes next time?”",
            "options": [
              "smoking / to drink / bringing",
              "to smoke / drinking / bringing",
              "smoking / drank / bringing",
              "smoking / drinking / bringing",
              "to smoke / to drink / to bring"
            ],
            "answer": "smoking / drinking / bringing"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "Ernest Hemingway was fond of ___ books.",
            "options": ["read", "to read", "reading", "be read", "to be read"],
            "answer": "reading"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "Turn on the radio. I want ___ to the news.",
            "options": [
              "listen",
              "listening",
              "to listen",
              "listened",
              "have been listened"
            ],
            "answer": "to listen"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "How do you feel if someone interrupts you? I hate people ___ me.",
            "options": [
              "interrupted",
              "to be interrupted",
              "not to interrupt",
              "having interrupted",
              "interrupting"
            ],
            "answer": "interrupting"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "After ___ my work I’ll join you.",
            "options": [
              "finish",
              "to finish",
              "have finished",
              "finishing",
              "finished"
            ],
            "answer": "finishing"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "Please, try ___ quiet, everyone is sleeping.",
            "options": ["be", "to be", "being", "having been", "been"],
            "answer": "being"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "He enjoyed ___ .",
            "options": ["singing", "sing", "was singing", "to sing", "sung"],
            "answer": "singing"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "The man ___ in the garden is listening to music.",
            "options": ["work", "is working", "working", "to work", "worked"],
            "answer": "working"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "___ the article we began ___ it.",
            "options": [
              "reading / discuss",
              "having read / discussing",
              "to read / to discuss",
              "read / discussing",
              "reading / discussed"
            ],
            "answer": "having read / discussing"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "The man ___ a cigarette is Tom’s cousin.",
            "options": [
              "smoked",
              "to smoke",
              "smoking",
              "have smoked",
              "had smoked"
            ],
            "answer": "smoking"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "I study English again, because ___ a foreign language is very important.",
            "options": [
              "speak",
              "spoken",
              "having spoken",
              "speaking",
              "spoke"
            ],
            "answer": "speaking"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "I like your ___ English.",
            "options": [
              "speak",
              "speaking",
              "was spoken",
              "have spoken",
              "having spoken"
            ],
            "answer": "speaking"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "Instead of ___ for Olga at home I decided ___ her in the street.",
            "options": [
              "to wait / to meet",
              "waiting / to meet",
              "waiting / meeting",
              "to wait / to meet",
              "wait / meeting"
            ],
            "answer": "waiting / to meet"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "They looked at the ___ plane.",
            "options": [
              "flying",
              "flown",
              "flew",
              "being flown",
              "having been flown"
            ],
            "answer": "flying"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "___ the language he couldn’t understand the question.",
            "options": ["know", "knows", "not to know", "known", "not knowing"],
            "answer": "not knowing"
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "Which of these four young men ___ by the fire is your son?",
            "options": ["sitting", "sit", "will sit", "sits", "sat"],
            "answer": "sitting"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "We expect him ___ tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "arrived",
              "to arrive",
              "to have arrived",
              "to be arrived",
              "having arrived"
            ],
            "answer": "to arrive"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "They sat up all night ___ .",
            "options": [
              "talk",
              "talked",
              "talking",
              "to be talked",
              "to have talked"
            ],
            "answer": "talking"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "The young man didn’t stop ___ although I asked him twice.",
            "options": [
              "is smoking",
              "smoked",
              "smoking",
              "smoked",
              "to smoke"
            ],
            "answer": "smoking"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "He introduced me to an acquaintance ___ that I did not know her.",
            "options": [
              "to believe",
              "believing",
              "to have believed",
              "of believing",
              "not to believe"
            ],
            "answer": "believing"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "I hope ___ you this evening.",
            "options": ["to see", "to be seen", "have seen", "see", "seen"],
            "answer": "to see"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "name": "Exercise 5",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 81,
            "question": "I am thankful for his ___ in time.",
            "options": ["came", "come", "to have come", "coming", "to come"],
            "answer": "coming"
          },
          {
            "id": 82,
            "question": "I remember the day when you took me aboard of your ship to help you in ___ the shark.",
            "options": [
              "hunt",
              "to hunt",
              "hunting",
              "hunted",
              "having hunted"
            ],
            "answer": "hunting"
          },
          {
            "id": 83,
            "question": "But the beaver went on ___ lace.",
            "options": ["to make", "make", "made", "making", "have made"],
            "answer": "making"
          },
          {
            "id": 84,
            "question": "___ with you is real pleasure.",
            "options": [
              "talked",
              "is talking",
              "on talking",
              "talking",
              "talks"
            ],
            "answer": "talking"
          },
          {
            "id": 85,
            "question": "What time do you come to the office?\nUsually at 9, but tomorrow I’ll have to be there a bit earlier ___ through some documents.",
            "options": [
              "looking",
              "looked",
              "to be looking",
              "to look",
              "to be looked"
            ],
            "answer": "to look"
          },
          {
            "id": 86,
            "question": "We knew nothing of his ___ a student.",
            "options": ["being", "be", "been", "to be", "to have been"],
            "answer": "being"
          },
          {
            "id": 87,
            "question": "He remembered he was going to buy a new suit ___ the shop.",
            "options": ["pass", "passes", "to pass", "passing", "will pass"],
            "answer": "passing"
          },
          {
            "id": 88,
            "question": "___ for better future many Asians leave their native countries ___ to Europe.",
            "options": [
              "hope / move",
              "hoping / moves",
              "hoped / moving",
              "hoping / moving",
              "hope / moving"
            ],
            "answer": "hoping / moving"
          },
          {
            "id": 89,
            "question": "She tried to be serious but she couldn’t help ___ .",
            "options": [
              "to laugh",
              "laughing",
              "laughed",
              "laugh",
              "having laughed"
            ],
            "answer": "laughing"
          },
          {
            "id": 90,
            "question": "Would you mind ___ the door, please?",
            "options": [
              "to close",
              "being closed",
              "closing",
              "close",
              "closed"
            ],
            "answer": "closing"
          },
          {
            "id": 91,
            "question": "She has nobody ___ to.",
            "options": ["talked", "to talk", "talk", "talks", "is talking"],
            "answer": "to talk"
          },
          {
            "id": 92,
            "question": "I enjoy ___ in the garden at weekends.",
            "options": [
              "work",
              "to work",
              "to be working",
              "working",
              "worked"
            ],
            "answer": "working"
          },
          {
            "id": 93,
            "question": "He is an artistic person very good at ___ poetry.",
            "options": [
              "to write",
              "to be written",
              "having written",
              "write",
              "writing"
            ],
            "answer": "writing"
          },
          {
            "id": 94,
            "question": "___ in Geneva for many years he knew the city well.",
            "options": [
              "Living",
              "Lived",
              "Being lived",
              "To live",
              "Have lived"
            ],
            "answer": "Living"
          },
          {
            "id": 95,
            "question": "Captain was the last ___ the ship.",
            "options": [
              "leaving",
              "is leaving",
              "on leaving",
              "to leave",
              "left"
            ],
            "answer": "to leave"
          },
          {
            "id": 96,
            "question": "I don’t mind ___ .",
            "options": [
              "to walk",
              "be walking",
              "walking",
              "having been walked",
              "to have walked"
            ],
            "answer": "walking"
          },
          {
            "id": 97,
            "question": "If you are lost in a snow storm it’s best ___ a hole and sit in it until it stops ___ .",
            "options": [
              "digging / snowing",
              "dig / snowed",
              "to dig / snowed",
              "digging / snowed",
              "to dig / snowing"
            ],
            "answer": "to dig / snowing"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Passive voice",
    "link": "passive-voice",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "I hope that the truth ___ very soon.",
            "options": [
              "will find out",
              "will be finding out",
              "is found out",
              "will be found out",
              "shall find out"
            ],
            "answer": "will be found out"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "Everything ___ before you came.",
            "options": [
              "is done",
              "was done",
              "has done",
              "had been done",
              "has been done"
            ],
            "answer": "was done"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "Did the company test the equipment yesterday?\nYes it ____.",
            "options": [
              "has tested",
              "had been tested",
              "had tested",
              "was tested",
              "tested"
            ],
            "answer": "was tested"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "The sports competitions which ___ on Sunday ___ by a lot of people.",
            "options": [
              "are held / will be visited",
              "was held / will visit",
              "will held / will visit",
              "have been held / have visited",
              "will be held / will be visited"
            ],
            "answer": "will be held / will be visited"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "The inspector is not in the town. He ___ to another place some days ago.",
            "options": [
              "was sent",
              "sent",
              "will be sent",
              "will send",
              "sends"
            ],
            "answer": "was sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "This story ___ to everybody as the name of the first space pioneer ___ in the heart of people all over the world.",
            "options": [
              "knows / lives",
              "knew / lived",
              "is known / is lived",
              "is known / lives",
              "knows / is lived"
            ],
            "answer": "is known / lives"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "The business letter ___ just ___ .",
            "options": [
              "is / written",
              "has / been written",
              "was / written",
              "were / written",
              "is / going to write"
            ],
            "answer": "has / been written"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "Business letters ___ usually on special forms.",
            "options": [
              "will be written",
              "are written",
              "are being written",
              "is written",
              "write"
            ],
            "answer": "are written"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "Sometimes a lot of guests ___ to his birthday party.",
            "options": [
              "had invited",
              "was invited",
              "were inviting",
              "are invited",
              "is inviting"
            ],
            "answer": "are invited"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "The business letters ___ tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "are sent",
              "is sent",
              "will be sent",
              "will send",
              "would be sent"
            ],
            "answer": "will be sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "All the business letters ___ yesterday. They ___ to the post office immediately.",
            "options": [
              "answered / take",
              "were answered / took",
              "are answered / were taken",
              "answered / took",
              "were answered / were taken"
            ],
            "answer": "were answered / took"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "The special information ___ in an hour or so, that’s why it ___ in the newspapers yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "brings / didn’t publish",
              "will bring / don’t publish",
              "will be brought / wasn’t published",
              "will be brought / didn’t publish",
              "brought / wasn’t published"
            ],
            "answer": "will be brought / wasn’t published"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "Houses ___ very quickly now.",
            "options": [
              "builds",
              "are building",
              "built",
              "are built",
              "were built"
            ],
            "answer": "are built"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "In 1834 the Houses of Parliament with the exception of Westminster Hall ___ by fire, they ___ later.",
            "options": [
              "destroyed / was rebuilt",
              "was being destroyed / rebuilt",
              "were destroyed /were rebuilt",
              "is destroyed / has been rebuilt",
              "destroys / rebuilds"
            ],
            "answer": "were destroyed /were rebuilt"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "You can’t use this textbook now. It ___ by your friend.",
            "options": [
              "takes",
              "has been taken",
              "took",
              "were taken",
              "had taken"
            ],
            "answer": "has been taken"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "Many modern apartments ___ in Berlin since 1980.",
            "options": [
              "are built",
              "are building",
              "were built",
              "have been built",
              "has been built"
            ],
            "answer": "have been built"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "The new film ___ in all the big theatres of the city.",
            "options": [
              "is demonstrated",
              "was being demonstrated",
              "is being demonstrated",
              "would be demonstrated",
              "had been demonstrated"
            ],
            "answer": "is being demonstrated"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "Nobody likes ___ for at night.",
            "options": ["be sent", "is sent", "was sent", "to be sent", "sent"],
            "answer": "to be sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "I ___ that I ___ at the station at 5.",
            "options": [
              "was told / should be met",
              "told / is being met",
              "tells / am met",
              "am told / was met",
              "will be told / would be met"
            ],
            "answer": "was told / should be met"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "Heroes ___ by people because they served their people and their country.",
            "options": [
              "is remembered",
              "was remembered",
              "are remembered",
              "had been remembered",
              "would be remembered"
            ],
            "answer": "are remembered"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "By the time we came to the bookshop all books ___",
            "options": [
              "are sold",
              "were sold",
              "had been sold",
              "are being sold",
              "is being sold"
            ],
            "answer": "had been sold"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "Don’t touch the door, it ___ just ___ .",
            "options": [
              "is / being painted",
              "has / been painted",
              "is / painted",
              "will / be painted",
              "would / be painted"
            ],
            "answer": "has / been painted"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "Scientific articles ___ often ___ in this paper.",
            "options": [
              "to be / published",
              "are / being published",
              "are / published",
              "have / published",
              "are / publish"
            ],
            "answer": "are / published"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "The fugitive ___ from prison to prison in Germany until he ___ in prison in 1944.",
            "options": [
              "transferred / killed",
              "was transferred / was killed",
              "is transferred / was killed",
              "has been transferred / has been killed",
              "will be transferred / was killed"
            ],
            "answer": "was transferred / was killed"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "I ___ a card to the club and in the afternoon I went there to play bridge.",
            "options": [
              "had been given",
              "were given",
              "was given",
              "have given",
              "was giving"
            ],
            "answer": "was given"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "I hope this book ___ .",
            "options": [
              "will find",
              "will be found",
              "found",
              "were found",
              "had been found"
            ],
            "answer": "will be found"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "___ about this film tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "It is an article",
              "He said",
              "I shall be asked",
              "Bob liked to tell",
              "He couldn’t"
            ],
            "answer": "I shall be asked"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "New schools ___ in our city every year.",
            "options": [
              "is built",
              "are to be built",
              "will build",
              "are built",
              "have built"
            ],
            "answer": "are built"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "A liar ___ when he speaks the truth.",
            "options": [
              "don’t believe",
              "isn’t believed",
              "believed",
              "believe",
              "didn’t believe"
            ],
            "answer": "isn’t believed"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "The doctor ___ just ___ for.",
            "options": [
              "is / sent",
              "was / sent",
              "has / sent",
              "has / been sent",
              "will / be sent"
            ],
            "answer": "has / been sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "This year a very beautiful theatre ___ in our city.",
            "options": [
              "built",
              "was built",
              "has been built",
              "had been built",
              "has built"
            ],
            "answer": "has been built"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "The Great Expectations ___ by Charles Dickens.",
            "options": [
              "were written",
              "is written",
              "wrote",
              "are written",
              "was written"
            ],
            "answer": "was written"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "In 1969 two manned spaceships ___ into space from the first space station.",
            "options": [
              "launch",
              "launched",
              "launches",
              "were launching",
              "were launched"
            ],
            "answer": "were launched"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "We can’t get there in time. By the time we get there the papers ___ .",
            "options": [
              "will be destroyed",
              "would be destroyed",
              "will have been destroyed",
              "are destroyed",
              "have been destroyed"
            ],
            "answer": "will have been destroyed"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "This school ___ next year.",
            "options": [
              "will close",
              "is closed",
              "will be closed",
              "was closed",
              "would be closed"
            ],
            "answer": "will be closed"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "A woman’s work ___ never done.",
            "options": ["are", "is", "will", "would", "were"],
            "answer": "is"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "Last Monday I received a telegram ___ by my sister on the 1st of May.",
            "options": ["sending", "to send", "had sent", "sent", "was sent"],
            "answer": "sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "I ___ about my father’s death before my mother.",
            "options": [
              "is told",
              "shall be told",
              "had been told",
              "were told",
              "have been told"
            ],
            "answer": "had been told"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "Someone wrote this report last week. This report ___ last week.",
            "options": [
              "is written",
              "was written",
              "has been written",
              "had been written",
              "would be written"
            ],
            "answer": "was written"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "Finally he decided to come back and live in the house of his parents which ___ by his aunt.",
            "options": ["kept", "was kept", "are kept", "were kept", "keeps"],
            "answer": "was kept"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "The men ___ after the explosion.",
            "options": [
              "are said to be arrested",
              "said to be arrested",
              "are said to being arrested",
              "are said to have been arrested",
              "are said to arrest"
            ],
            "answer": "are said to have been arrested"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "Mike didn’t have his car yesterday. It ___ at the station.",
            "options": [
              "was serviced",
              "were serviced",
              "had serviced",
              "had been serviced",
              "is serviced"
            ],
            "answer": "was serviced"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "You can’t come in. She ___ for the TV.",
            "options": [
              "is interviewed",
              "interviews",
              "is being interviewed",
              "was interviewed",
              "has been interviewed"
            ],
            "answer": "is being interviewed"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "I had an unpleasant feeling that I ___ .",
            "options": [
              "watched",
              "was watched",
              "have been watched",
              "was being watched",
              "will be watched"
            ],
            "answer": "was being watched"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "He’ll finish the job tomorrow. The job ___",
            "options": [
              "is finished",
              "would be finished",
              "will be finished",
              "will finish",
              "was finished"
            ],
            "answer": "will be finished"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "After a thorough examination the patient ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "was sent",
              "were sent",
              "are sent",
              "to send",
              "sends"
            ],
            "answer": "was sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "I ___ for shopping yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "is sent",
              "was sent",
              "am sent",
              "are sent",
              "has been sent"
            ],
            "answer": "was sent"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "How much money ___ yesterday?",
            "options": [
              "is stolen",
              "stole",
              "will steal",
              "will be stolen",
              "was stolen"
            ],
            "answer": "was stolen"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "This work ___ tomorrow.",
            "options": [
              "is finished",
              "was finished",
              "had finished",
              "have been finished",
              "will be finished"
            ],
            "answer": "will be finished"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "The delegation ___ at the station by the students yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "meet",
              "is met",
              "have been met",
              "was met",
              "are met"
            ],
            "answer": "was met"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "Today acupuncture ___ effectively in our country.",
            "options": [
              "were used",
              "are used",
              "is used",
              "has been used",
              "had used"
            ],
            "answer": "is used"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "Some scrap metal ___ and ___ in the school yard by the evening last Sunday.",
            "options": [
              "was gathered/heaped",
              "has been gathered/heaped",
              "will be gathered/heaped",
              "had been gathered/heaped",
              "would be gathered/heaped"
            ],
            "answer": "was gathered/heaped"
          },
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "The first coins in America ___ in 1752. They were not regular in shape.",
            "options": ["are made", "made", "were made", "was made", "is made"],
            "answer": "were made"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "Many magnificent palaces and museums ___ in our city lately.",
            "options": [
              "have built",
              "has built",
              "has been built",
              "have been built",
              "were built"
            ],
            "answer": "have been built"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "A lot of books by this writer ___ into many languages of the world.",
            "options": [
              "translated",
              "is translated",
              "were translated",
              "has been translated",
              "had been translated"
            ],
            "answer": "has been translated"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "The great English scientist Isaac Newton ___ not far from Cambridge.",
            "options": ["born", "is born", "are born", "were born", "was born"],
            "answer": "was born"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "He ate everything that ___ on the table.",
            "options": [
              "is leaving",
              "was left",
              "were left",
              "is left",
              "are left"
            ],
            "answer": "was left"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "He made a rush at the door without realizing it ___ by me earlier.",
            "options": [
              "locks",
              "is locked",
              "was locked",
              "am locking",
              "had been locked"
            ],
            "answer": "had been locked"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Indirect speech",
    "link": "indirect-speech",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "The teacher promised ___ .",
            "options": [
              "that we can learn three English songs.",
              "if we learn three English songs.",
              "we would learn three English songs.",
              "whether we would learn three English songs.",
              "who will learn three English songs."
            ],
            "answer": "we would learn three English songs."
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "Bill: “Have you seen any interesting comedy lately, Nancy?”\nBill asked Nancy ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if he will see an interesting film",
              "if he saw an interesting comedy lately",
              "what comedy Nancy saw lately",
              "if she had seen any interesting comedy lately",
              "if she would see an interesting comedy"
            ],
            "answer": "if she had seen any interesting comedy lately"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "Nick: “Did you see a bird in the tree?”\nNick wonders ___ in the tree.",
            "options": [
              "if I saw a bird.",
              "that I saw a bird.",
              "if I had seen a bird.",
              "whether I see a bird.",
              "if I have seen a bird."
            ],
            "answer": "if I saw a bird."
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "Dick to Lucy: Have you received my telegram ?\nDick asked if ___ .",
            "options": [
              "Lucy had received his telegram.",
              "Lucy has received his telegram",
              "Lucy would receive his telegram",
              "Lucy will receive his telegram",
              "Lucy received his telegram"
            ],
            "answer": "Lucy had received his telegram."
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "Ann: Write down my address.\nAnn asked me ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he wrote down my address",
              "to write down her address",
              "he had written her address",
              "she writes down her address",
              "she wrote down his address"
            ],
            "answer": "to write down her address"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "He said, “I’m very busy today.”\nHe said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he had been very busy that day",
              "he is very busy today",
              "he was very busy that day",
              "I’m very busy today",
              "I had been very busy that day"
            ],
            "answer": "he was very busy that day"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "Lena said, “Where have you been yesterday?”\nLena asked ___ .",
            "options": [
              "where she had been the day before.",
              "where she had been yesterday.",
              "where she was the day before.",
              "where she could be the day before.",
              "where she hasn’t been before."
            ],
            "answer": "where she had been yesterday."
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "He thought: “What am I going to do?”\nHe thought ___ .",
            "options": [
              "what was he going to do",
              "what he was going to do",
              "what he is going to do",
              "it he was going to do",
              "what is he going to do"
            ],
            "answer": "what he was going to do"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "Mother asked me ___ .",
            "options": [
              "why I have spent all the money",
              "that I had spent all the money",
              "if I had spent all the money",
              "when I spend all the money",
              "if I will spend all the money"
            ],
            "answer": "if I had spent all the money"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "“Don’t play in the street!”\n",
            "options": [
              "My mother told me don’t play in the street.",
              "My mother said to play in the street.",
              "She asked me to play in the street.",
              "My mother told me not to play in the street.",
              "My mother said I should play in the street."
            ],
            "answer": "My mother told me not to play in the street."
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "Ann: “Is your sister good at English?”\nAnn asked me ___ .",
            "options": [
              "that my sister is good at English",
              "if my sister was good at English",
              "whether my sister is good at English",
              "my sister is good at English",
              "her sister was good at English"
            ],
            "answer": "if my sister was good at English"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "Tom: “Don’t forget to bring my book, Ann”.\nTom asked Ann: ___ .",
            "options": [
              "that she didn’t forget to bring his book",
              "that she doesn’t bring his book",
              "not to forget to bring his book",
              "not to forget to bring her book",
              "if she didn’t forget to bring the book"
            ],
            "answer": "not to forget to bring his book"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "Mother: “We are going to have supper”.\nMother says ___ .",
            "options": [
              "they are going to have supper",
              "they were going to have supper",
              "that they would have supper",
              "they won’t have supper",
              "they haven’t had supper yet"
            ],
            "answer": "they are going to have supper"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "Jack said: “I was at home yesterday.”\nJack said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he was at home.",
              "Jack said he was at home the day before",
              "he will be at home.",
              "he had been at home a week ago.",
              "he had been at home the day before."
            ],
            "answer": "Jack said he was at home the day before."
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "“Do you go in for sports?”, he asked.\nHe asked ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he went in for sports.",
              "if I went in for sports.",
              "if I’ll go in for sports.",
              "I should go in for sports.",
              "if I had gone in for sports."
            ],
            "answer": "if I went in for sports."
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "“Will Tom help me?” she said.\nShe asked ___ .",
            "options": [
              "will Tom help her",
              "if Tom would help her",
              "whether he will help her",
              "whether would he help her",
              "that Tom would be helping her"
            ],
            "answer": "if Tom would help her"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Peter said, “Alice, are you busy now?”\nPeter asked Alice ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she was busy.",
              "if she was busy then.",
              "she would be busy.",
              "if she wasn’t busy then.",
              "if she is busy."
            ],
            "answer": "if she was busy then."
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "My sister said: “I hope we shall go on an excursion to the lake”.\nMy sister said that ___ on an excursion to the lake”.",
            "options": [
              "she hopes we will go",
              "she didn’t hope that we shall go",
              "she hoped they would go",
              "she hoped we were going",
              "she hoped we can go"
            ],
            "answer": "she hoped they would go"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "Jim and Julia have been in the restaurant for an hour and they have not been served yet. Julia is angry. “You said ___ a good place’’",
            "options": [
              "it is",
              "it has been",
              "it will be",
              "it was",
              "it can’t be"
            ],
            "answer": "it was"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "“Did you work at a factory 3 years ago?” she asked her friend.\nShe asked her friend if she ___ .",
            "options": [
              "worked at a factory 3 years ago.",
              "had worked at a factory 3 years before.",
              "really worked at a factory 3 years before.",
              "work at a factory.",
              "worked at a factory for 3 years."
            ],
            "answer": "had worked at a factory 3 years before."
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "She said she ___ her friend for ages.",
            "options": [
              "didn’t",
              "hadn’t seen",
              "hasn’t seen",
              "doesn’t see",
              "saw"
            ],
            "answer": "hadn’t seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "He asked her “Did anybody call this morning?”\nHe asked her ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if anybody called this morning",
              "if somebody had called that morning",
              "if somebody called that morning",
              "who called that morning",
              "had called anybody that morning"
            ],
            "answer": "if somebody had called that morning"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "Teacher: “Tom, read the story, please”.\nTeacher asked Tom ___ .",
            "options": [
              "to read the story",
              "read the story",
              "that he reads it",
              "whether he reads the story",
              "it he read the story"
            ],
            "answer": "to read the story"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "He said “I met him in 1950”.\nHe said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "I met him in 1950",
              "he had been met by him in 1950",
              "he used to meet him in 1950",
              "he had met him in 1950",
              "he was meeting him in 1950"
            ],
            "answer": "he had met him in 1950"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "Jane asked Bob: “What did you buy yesterday?”\nJane asked Bob what ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he would buy the next day",
              "he bought yesterday",
              "he had bought the day before",
              "he has just bought",
              "his friend had already bought"
            ],
            "answer": "he had bought the day before"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "He said, “I do not want to see this film”.\nHe said that ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he did not want to see that film.",
              "he doesn’t want to see a film.",
              "he didn’t want to see this film.",
              "he wanted to see that film.",
              "not to see that film."
            ],
            "answer": "he didn’t want to see this film."
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "He says “What do the pupils study?”\nHe asks ___ .",
            "options": [
              "what do the pupils study.",
              "what the pupils study.",
              "what the pupils studied.",
              "what the pupils have studied study.",
              "whether the pupils study something."
            ],
            "answer": "what the pupils study."
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "My mother told me ___ .",
            "options": [
              "did not go there.",
              "that I can go there.",
              "not to go there.",
              "not going there.",
              "let not go there."
            ],
            "answer": "not to go there."
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "The director wondered ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if I know English.",
              "If I knew English.",
              "he knows English.",
              "how I know English.",
              "who has known English."
            ],
            "answer": "If I knew English."
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "Mary says “I clean my room every day.”\nMary says that ___ .",
            "options": [
              "I clean her room every day.",
              "she cleans my room every day.",
              "she cleaned her room every day.",
              "she cleans her room every day.",
              "her room was cleaned every day."
            ],
            "answer": "she cleans her room every day."
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "“Have you seen my daughter?” a woman is asking her neighbor.\nA woman is asking her neighbor ___ her daughter.",
            "options": [
              "has she seen",
              "have I seen",
              "if she has seen",
              "if they have seen",
              "have you seen"
            ],
            "answer": "if she has seen"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "He ___ me if I ___ a taxi yesterday.",
            "options": [
              "will ask / takes",
              "ask / take",
              "is asking / shall take",
              "asked / had taken",
              "will ask / take"
            ],
            "answer": "asked / had taken"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "She asked in surprise ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if he had really read all the books",
              "if this is what her mother buys her",
              "if the cafe is still open",
              "whether I have already read his article",
              "did she caused much trouble"
            ],
            "answer": "if he had really read all the books"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "The doctor asked his nurse ___ .",
            "options": [
              "when is she going to give the medicine to the",
              "if she would come in time the following day",
              "if the patient prepared for the operation",
              "if the tests are ready for applicants",
              "when the patient is asleep tell me"
            ],
            "answer": "if the tests are ready for applicants"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "They ___ us that they ___ from their families for more than a year.",
            "options": [
              "tell / were not hearing",
              "would be told / hear",
              "had told / don’t hear",
              "told / had not heard",
              "told / will be hearing"
            ],
            "answer": "told / had not heard"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "Teachers always tell their pupils ___ .",
            "options": [
              "not to cross street when the traffic light is red",
              "doesn’t cross the road on red traffic light",
              "don’t ask many questions if they are not",
              "when they come to the lesson",
              "they helped their parents"
            ],
            "answer": "not to cross street when the traffic light is red"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "I wondered ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if the train had come on time",
              "had the train come on time",
              "whether the train comes on time",
              "if the train will come on time",
              "when the train is due to come"
            ],
            "answer": "if the train had come on time"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "She promised her friends she ___ and ___ them the next day.",
            "options": [
              "had come / had seen",
              "will come / see",
              "would come / see",
              "comes / sees",
              "came / saw"
            ],
            "answer": "would come / see"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "“You must do what you are told”.\nShe said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "that must do what I was told",
              "what have to do what I was told",
              "what had to do what I was told",
              "that she must do what she was told",
              "she had to do what she was told"
            ],
            "answer": "that she must do what she was told"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "The sergeant said that nothing ___ from the two boys since they\n___ at the Victoria Station.",
            "options": [
              "was heard / saw",
              "will be heard / were seen",
              "had been heard / were seen",
              "had heard / saw",
              "would have heard / were seen"
            ],
            "answer": "had been heard / were seen"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "Nick whispered: “I know that the boys were angry with me”.\nNick whispered that ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he knows that the boys were angry with me",
              "he knew that the boys were angry with him",
              "he knows that the boys were angry with him",
              "I know that the boys were angry with me",
              "he knew that the boys had been angry with him"
            ],
            "answer": "he knew that the boys had been angry with him"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "Alice is told: “Clean your teeth twice a day!”\nAlice is told ___",
            "options": [
              "clean her teeth twice a day",
              "if she cleans her teeth twice a day",
              "clean your teeth twice a day",
              "to clean her teeth twice a day",
              "cleaned her teeth twice a day"
            ],
            "answer": "to clean her teeth twice a day"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "I am always asked ___ .",
            "options": [
              "why am I late",
              "are you late",
              "is he absent",
              "why was I present",
              "if I am on duty"
            ],
            "answer": "if I am on duty"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "Julia continued, “You said ___ good service.”",
            "options": [
              "you knew the owner and always got",
              "you know the owner and have got",
              "you know the owner and get",
              "you know the owner and will get",
              "you know the owner and are going to get"
            ],
            "answer": "you knew the owner and always got"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "Julia continued, “You said ___ .”",
            "options": [
              "you have been here before",
              "you were here yesterday",
              "you will be here tomorrow",
              "you are here now",
              "you had been here before"
            ],
            "answer": "you had been here before"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "He wanted to know ___ .",
            "options": [
              "whether she knows him",
              "if she knew him",
              "that she knew him",
              "what she knew him",
              "did she know him"
            ],
            "answer": "if she knew him"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "“When will you be there, Tom?” asked Dan.\nDan asked Tom ___ .",
            "options": [
              "when you will be there",
              "when he will be there",
              "when he would be there",
              "when his friend would be there",
              "when you would be there"
            ],
            "answer": "when he would be there"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "He said to me: “I’ll come as soon as I can”.\nHe told me that ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he came as soon as he would be able",
              "he would come as soon as I could",
              "he comes as soon as he can",
              "he would come as soon as he could",
              "I would come as soon as I could"
            ],
            "answer": "he would come as soon as he could"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "He has just said, “I want to speak to you”.\nHe has just said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "he wants to speak to me",
              "he wanted to speak to me",
              "I want to speak to her",
              "he had wanted to speak to me",
              "he will want to speak to me"
            ],
            "answer": "he wanted to speak to me"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "Mother told me “Don’t stay out long’’.\nMother told me ___ .",
            "options": [
              "did not stay out long",
              "not to stay out long",
              "that I mustn’t stay out long",
              "I shouldn’t stay out long",
              "stay out long"
            ],
            "answer": "not to stay out long"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "“Where did they spend the vacation?”\nTom said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "they came back.",
              "they had spent it at the seaside.",
              "they were young.",
              "they left for an hour.",
              "they have spent it at home."
            ],
            "answer": "they had spent it at the seaside."
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "The secretary said to the visitor: “ When did you graduate from the University?”\nThe secretary asked the visitor ___ .",
            "options": [
              "when he graduates from the University.",
              "when did he graduate from the University.",
              "when he had graduated from the University.",
              "when did she graduate from the University.",
              "he graduated from the University."
            ],
            "answer": "when he had graduated from the University."
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "What will you do if Jack is out when you come?\nShe asked me ___ .",
            "options": [
              "what would I do if Jack was out when I came",
              "what I will do if Jack is out when I come",
              "what I would do if Jack was out when I came",
              "what Jack would do if I was out when he came",
              "what I will do if Jack was out when I came"
            ],
            "answer": "what I would do if Jack was out when I came"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "Jane said, “I shall help you.”\nJane said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she helped us",
              "she will help him",
              "she helps us",
              "she would help us",
              "she had helped us"
            ],
            "answer": "she would help us"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "The manager wondered ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if the customers’ answer can be positive",
              "if the visitors are coming",
              "whether the letters are being posted",
              "if the paper has been typed",
              "if the secretary had come"
            ],
            "answer": "if the secretary had come"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "I ___ I ___ her back.",
            "options": [
              "thought / would get",
              "thought / shall get",
              "think / had got",
              "thinks / am getting",
              "doesn’t think / get"
            ],
            "answer": "thought / would get"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "The father wondered ___ .",
            "options": [
              "what mark his daughter gets",
              "where the mother is",
              "how his son does at school",
              "if his daughter had passed her exams",
              "whether everybody is at home"
            ],
            "answer": "if his daughter had passed her exams"
          },
          {
            "id": 58,
            "question": "The teacher asked her pupils ___ .",
            "options": [
              "where are their textbooks",
              "where their textbooks are",
              "where their textbooks were",
              "be quiet, please, listen to me",
              "why they open the textbooks"
            ],
            "answer": "where their textbooks were"
          },
          {
            "id": 59,
            "question": "I ___ my mother___ want to meet her new son in law for the first time in my presence.",
            "options": [
              "knows / will not",
              "had known / will not",
              "knew / would not",
              "know / had not",
              "shall know / did not"
            ],
            "answer": "knew / would not"
          },
          {
            "id": 60,
            "question": "The man said:” I have brought all my things “.\nThe man said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "I have brought all his things.",
              "that he had brought all his things.",
              "he has brought all his things.",
              "they have brought all his things.",
              "that he brought all his things."
            ],
            "answer": "that he had brought all his things."
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "name": "Exercise 4",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 61,
            "question": "“Don’t make so much noise, Michael,” said Ellen.\nEllen told Michael ___ so much noise.",
            "options": [
              "to make",
              "not to make",
              "do make",
              "don’t make",
              "didn’t make"
            ],
            "answer": "not to make"
          },
          {
            "id": 62,
            "question": "A foreigner asked: “How do English people spend their Sundays?”\nA foreigner asked how ___ their Sundays.",
            "options": [
              "do English people spend",
              "did English people spend",
              "English people spent",
              "English people spend",
              "had English people spent"
            ],
            "answer": "English people spent"
          },
          {
            "id": 63,
            "question": "The film director was asked ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if he likes to play on grass",
              "which airline he works for",
              "if he had ever won an Oscar",
              "that he took part in the concert",
              "why he is nervous before the match"
            ],
            "answer": "if he had ever won an Oscar"
          },
          {
            "id": 64,
            "question": "The police officer asked us ___ .",
            "options": [
              "are we going that way",
              "where we were going",
              "when did the tram stop",
              "if could we stop at the traffic light",
              "whether we speak English"
            ],
            "answer": "where we were going"
          },
          {
            "id": 65,
            "question": "He said that ___ .",
            "options": [
              "his friend is learning English",
              "our classroom will be cleaned tomorrow",
              "they were going to the nearest post office",
              "his car was stolen a few weeks ago",
              "there is nothing to do"
            ],
            "answer": "his car was stolen a few weeks ago"
          },
          {
            "id": 66,
            "question": "He said to her, “Don’t enter the room”.\nHe ordered her ___ the room.",
            "options": [
              "not to enter",
              "to enter",
              "didn’t enter",
              "doesn’t enter",
              "do not enter"
            ],
            "answer": "not to enter"
          },
          {
            "id": 67,
            "question": "“How far do I have to walk?” she asked me.\nShe wanted to know how far ___ to walk.",
            "options": [
              "she had",
              "she has",
              "I have",
              "I had",
              "she will have"
            ],
            "answer": "she had"
          },
          {
            "id": 68,
            "question": "She told him that she ___ to see him the following DAY.",
            "options": ["will come", "come", "came", "would come", "comes"],
            "answer": "would come"
          },
          {
            "id": 69,
            "question": "“Did you sleep well?” I asked him.\nI asked him if ___ well.",
            "options": [
              "he sleeps",
              "he slept",
              "he had slept",
              "you slept",
              "you did sleep"
            ],
            "answer": "he had slept"
          },
          {
            "id": 70,
            "question": "“Were you at the Zoo last night?” asks Jane.\nJane asks ___ at the Zoo last night.",
            "options": [
              "that I was",
              "if I was",
              "if I had been",
              "if I am",
              "whether was I"
            ],
            "answer": "if I was"
          },
          {
            "id": 71,
            "question": "“Whose birthday is it?” said Jane.\nJane asked whose birthday ___ .",
            "options": ["it is", "it", "it was", "is it", "it had been"],
            "answer": "it was"
          },
          {
            "id": 72,
            "question": "“Where do you live?” the boy asked.\nThe boy wanted to know where ___ .",
            "options": [
              "do I live",
              "did I live",
              "I live",
              "I lived",
              "I had lived"
            ],
            "answer": "I live"
          },
          {
            "id": 73,
            "question": "“Where did you live?” my boss asked.\nMy boss wanted to know where ___ .",
            "options": [
              "do I live",
              "did I live",
              "I live",
              "I had lived",
              "I lived"
            ],
            "answer": "did I live"
          },
          {
            "id": 74,
            "question": "“I spoke to Jane last week,” she said.\nShe said ___ .",
            "options": [
              "I spoke to Jane last week.",
              "she had spoken to Jane last week.",
              "she had spoken to Jane a week before.",
              "I had spoken to Jane a week before.",
              "she spoke to Jane a week before."
            ],
            "answer": "she had spoken to Jane last week."
          },
          {
            "id": 75,
            "question": "“Don’t wait for me, Ann,” said Tom.\nTom told Ann ___ .",
            "options": [
              "to wait for him",
              "not to wait for him",
              "didn’t wait for him",
              "don’t wait for him",
              "if she waited for him"
            ],
            "answer": "not to wait for him"
          },
          {
            "id": 76,
            "question": "The manager asks the secretary ___ .",
            "options": [
              "if Mr. Smith would be busy at little next day",
              "if Mr. Smith will be busy at 11 tomorrow",
              "if Mr. Smith had been busy at 11",
              "has Mr. Smith been busy by 11 today",
              "will Mr. Smith be busy at 11 tomorrow"
            ],
            "answer": "if Mr. Smith will be busy at 11 tomorrow"
          },
          {
            "id": 77,
            "question": "He was sure that he ___ this time.",
            "options": [
              "will fail",
              "wouldn’t fail",
              "fails",
              "failed",
              "will not fail"
            ],
            "answer": "wouldn’t fail"
          },
          {
            "id": 78,
            "question": "“Can you open the door for me, my son?” asked an old woman.\nAn old woman asked a young ___ the door for her.",
            "options": [
              "can he open",
              "he opens",
              "does he open",
              "if he can open",
              "to open"
            ],
            "answer": "if he can open"
          },
          {
            "id": 79,
            "question": "She said, “I lost the key of my room.”\nShe said that ___ .",
            "options": [
              "she had lost the key of her room",
              "she lost the key of my room",
              "I had lost the key of my room",
              "I lose the key of my room",
              "she lost the key of the room"
            ],
            "answer": "she had lost the key of her room"
          },
          {
            "id": 80,
            "question": "I asked Nelly, “What are you looking for?”\nI asked Nelly what ___ looking for.",
            "options": ["are you", "she was", "were you", "was she", "she is"],
            "answer": "she was"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "When - while - where - as soon as",
    "link": "when-while-where-as-soon-as",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "___ you tell him about it when you ___ him?",
            "options": [
              "did / see",
              "does / saw",
              "will / see",
              "would / see",
              "do / will see"
            ],
            "answer": "will / see"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "Tomorrow when you ___ the sun ___ .",
            "options": [
              "woke up / shines",
              "have woken up / was shining",
              "wake up / will be shining",
              "will wake up / will shine",
              "woke up / shined"
            ],
            "answer": "wake up / will be shining"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "When my sister ___ at the college 2 years ago she ___ to learn several foreign languages.",
            "options": [
              "was studying / tried",
              "studies / tries",
              "studied / was trying",
              "was studying / was trying",
              "studies / trying"
            ],
            "answer": "was studying / tried"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "When I ___ that morning the sun ___ high in the sky.",
            "options": [
              "will wake up / had shone",
              "have waken up / shines",
              "shall wake up / was shining",
              "woke up / was shining",
              "woke up / will be shining"
            ],
            "answer": "woke up / was shining"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "When I ___ the letter I wondered what ___ .",
            "options": [
              "got / had happened",
              "get / happens",
              "got / happened",
              "had got / had happened",
              "got / has happened"
            ],
            "answer": "got / had happened"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "I ___ to know when you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "don’t want / will come",
              "shall want / come",
              "want / had come",
              "didn’t want / come",
              "didn’t want / are coming"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t want / will come"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "When I ___ home my mother ___ me that my friend ___ me an hour before.",
            "options": [
              "had come / told / had called",
              "came / told / called",
              "came / told / had called",
              "was coming / told / called",
              "came / was telling / had called"
            ],
            "answer": "came / told / had called"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "I ___ still, when you ___ .",
            "options": [
              "am working / will return",
              "shall be working / return",
              "was working / are returning",
              "shall have been working / have returned",
              "was working / are returned"
            ],
            "answer": "shall be working / return"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "When Harris ___ her she ___ Paris.",
            "options": [
              "is meeting / was leaving",
              "met / was leaving",
              "had met / left",
              "meets / left",
              "met / will leave"
            ],
            "answer": "met / was leaving"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "When he ___ in London, it ___ heavily.",
            "options": [
              "arrive / rains",
              "arrives / rained",
              "arrived / was raining",
              "will arrive / rains",
              "arrived / is raining"
            ],
            "answer": "arrived / was raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "It ___ when we ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "rained / came",
              "rained / was coming",
              "was raining / came",
              "will rain / came",
              "rained / shall come"
            ],
            "answer": "was raining / came"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "When we ___ the beach the rain ___ already ___ .",
            "options": [
              "leave / has / started",
              "will leave / have / started",
              "left / had / started",
              "left / have / started",
              "are leaving / was / starting"
            ],
            "answer": "left / had / started"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ when I ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "did / do / returned",
              "are / doing / shall return",
              "will / be doing / return",
              "do / do / return",
              "have done / am returning"
            ],
            "answer": "will / be doing / return"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "When I ___ him up they said that he ___ an hour ago.",
            "options": [
              "call / left",
              "called / has left",
              "should call / has left",
              "call / leaves",
              "called / had left"
            ],
            "answer": "called / had left"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "When you ___ me up yesterday it ___ hard.",
            "options": [
              "rings / will rain",
              "rang / was raining",
              "will rang / will rain",
              "ring / rains",
              "had rung / had rained"
            ],
            "answer": "rang / was raining"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "When the woman was out a postman ___ a letter.",
            "options": [
              "brings",
              "bring",
              "brought",
              "had brought",
              "has brought"
            ],
            "answer": "brought"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "I hope it ___ when you ___ to London.",
            "options": [
              "doesn’t rain / will get",
              "is raining / get",
              "won’t be raining / get",
              "will rain / will get",
              "rained / have got"
            ],
            "answer": "won’t be raining / get"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "When the lesson ___ we ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "are over / go",
              "is over / goes",
              "is over / shall go",
              "will be over / go",
              "will be over / shall go"
            ],
            "answer": "is over / shall go"
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "What ___ you ___ when your father returned?",
            "options": [
              "will / do",
              "were /do",
              "was / do",
              "will / be doing",
              "were / do",
              "were / doing"
            ],
            "answer": "were / doing"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "When we ___ in Seville we ___ sightseeing.",
            "options": [
              "are / went",
              "were / went",
              "shall be / go",
              "are / go",
              "had been / go"
            ],
            "answer": "were / went"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "name": "Exercise 2",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 21,
            "question": "___ when he was painting the ceiling.",
            "options": [
              "He found his passport",
              "He burnt his hand",
              "He bought a new car",
              "He wrote a letter",
              "He fell off the ladder"
            ],
            "answer": "He fell off the ladder"
          },
          {
            "id": 22,
            "question": "It ___ since morning when we ___.",
            "options": [
              "has rained / went out",
              "had been raining / went out",
              "was raining / go out",
              "rained / will go out",
              "rained / went out"
            ],
            "answer": "had been raining / went out"
          },
          {
            "id": 23,
            "question": "When I ___ back to the table, six soldiers ___ there.",
            "options": [
              "came / were sitting",
              "comes / were sitting",
              "has come / sit",
              "came / are sitting",
              "came / will sit"
            ],
            "answer": "came / were sitting"
          },
          {
            "id": 24,
            "question": "When I ___ younger I ___ an idea of a wife who ___ with me in my thoughts as well as aims.",
            "options": [
              "was / had / will be",
              "was / had / would be",
              "had been / had / is",
              "have been / have / will be",
              "was / had had / had been"
            ],
            "answer": "was / had / would be"
          },
          {
            "id": 25,
            "question": "When I ___ school I ___ the university.",
            "options": [
              "shall finish / shall enter",
              "finish / enter",
              "shall finish / enter",
              "finish / shall enter",
              "finish / entered"
            ],
            "answer": "finish / shall enter"
          },
          {
            "id": 26,
            "question": "I visited my sister when she ___ in Moscow.",
            "options": [
              "lived",
              "lives",
              "were lived",
              "is living",
              "were living"
            ],
            "answer": "lived"
          },
          {
            "id": 27,
            "question": "We ___ have our supper when our mother ___ from the market.",
            "options": [
              "shall / comes",
              "/ comes",
              "/ will come",
              "shan’t / come",
              "shall / come"
            ],
            "answer": "/ comes"
          },
          {
            "id": 28,
            "question": "The passengers ___ for the train for 20 minutes when it ___ into the station.",
            "options": [
              "waited / pulls",
              "had waited / pulled",
              "had been waiting / pulled",
              "will wait / had pulled",
              "are waiting / was pulled"
            ],
            "answer": "had been waiting / pulled"
          },
          {
            "id": 29,
            "question": "Yesterday when I ___ her she ___ me about you.",
            "options": [
              "have met / told",
              "was meeting / told",
              "have met / would tell",
              "have met / tell",
              "met / had told"
            ],
            "answer": "was meeting / told"
          },
          {
            "id": 30,
            "question": "When I came in my mother ___ dinner.",
            "options": [
              "cooked",
              "were cooking",
              "will cook",
              "have cooked",
              "was cooking"
            ],
            "answer": "was cooking"
          },
          {
            "id": 31,
            "question": "When I ___ home, I ___ a friend of mine.",
            "options": [
              "was going / met",
              "go / meet",
              "was going / was meeting",
              "are going / meet",
              "were going / met"
            ],
            "answer": "was going / met"
          },
          {
            "id": 32,
            "question": "I ___ terrible when I ___ that morning.",
            "options": [
              "felt / wake up",
              "feels / wake up",
              "felt / woke up",
              "feel / woke up",
              "felt / had woken up"
            ],
            "answer": "felt / woke up"
          },
          {
            "id": 33,
            "question": "When they ___ about it there ___ much trouble.",
            "options": [
              "finds out / be",
              "found out / were",
              "is finding out / is",
              "find out / will be",
              "found out / had been"
            ],
            "answer": "find out / will be"
          },
          {
            "id": 34,
            "question": "Lane ___ through the morning papers when the telephone ___ .",
            "options": [
              "was looking / rang",
              "were looking / rang",
              "are looking / rung",
              "have looked / ring",
              "looked / is ringing"
            ],
            "answer": "was looking / rang"
          },
          {
            "id": 35,
            "question": "A ship ___ near the Malta Islands when the men on board ___ a dolphin in the water.",
            "options": [
              "was fishing / noticed",
              "fished / noticed",
              "was fishing / will notice",
              "is fishing / noticed",
              "fished / notices"
            ],
            "answer": "was fishing / noticed"
          },
          {
            "id": 36,
            "question": "How fast ___ you ___ when the accident ___?",
            "options": [
              "were / driving / happened",
              "did / drive / was happening",
              "will / drive / had happened",
              "are / driving / will happen",
              " / drive / happens"
            ],
            "answer": "were / driving / happened"
          },
          {
            "id": 37,
            "question": "I ___ my hand when I ___ the dinner.",
            "options": [
              "was burning / cooked",
              "had burnt / am cooking",
              "shall burn / shall cook",
              "burnt / was cooking",
              "have burnt / cooked"
            ],
            "answer": "burnt / was cooking"
          },
          {
            "id": 38,
            "question": "We ___ ready when you ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "are / will come",
              "shall / come",
              "shall be / will come",
              "shall be / come",
              "will be / came"
            ],
            "answer": "shall be / come"
          },
          {
            "id": 39,
            "question": "Two hours ago when the children ___ in the yard a terrible storm ___ .",
            "options": [
              "were playing / began",
              "played / began",
              "were playing / were beginning",
              "played / were beginning",
              "play / begins"
            ],
            "answer": "were playing / began"
          },
          {
            "id": 40,
            "question": "It ___ for three hours when we ___ home.",
            "options": [
              "will have been raining / came",
              "is raining / come",
              "rained / came",
              "rains / came",
              "had been raining / came"
            ],
            "answer": "had been raining / came"
          }
        ]
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "name": "Exercise 3",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 41,
            "question": "While we ___ an article mother ___ dinner.",
            "options": [
              "were translated / was cooking",
              "were translating / cooked",
              "have been translating / is cooking",
              "translated / had cooked",
              "are translating / was cooking"
            ],
            "answer": "were translating / cooked"
          },
          {
            "id": 42,
            "question": "He looked at the carpet while ___ for her answer.",
            "options": [
              "to wait",
              "be waiting",
              "waiting",
              "waited",
              "having waited"
            ],
            "answer": "waiting"
          },
          {
            "id": 43,
            "question": "While the woman ___ her children quickly passed her and ___ upstairs.",
            "options": [
              "was talking / was going",
              "was talking / went",
              "talks / went",
              "were talking / went",
              "talked / went"
            ],
            "answer": "was talking / went"
          },
          {
            "id": 44,
            "question": "I understood that while the student ___ I couldn’t enter the room.",
            "options": [
              "would be examined",
              "is examining",
              "was examined",
              "was being examined",
              "is examined"
            ],
            "answer": "was being examined"
          },
          {
            "id": 45,
            "question": "While we ___ sightseeing the students ___ the book.",
            "options": [
              "went / were reading",
              "to go / were reading",
              "went / are reading",
              "go / were read",
              "have gone / have read"
            ],
            "answer": "went / were reading"
          },
          {
            "id": 46,
            "question": "While you ___ a rest, we ___ the task.",
            "options": [
              "were having / did",
              "have / do",
              "shall have / done",
              "have had / did",
              "is having / do"
            ],
            "answer": "were having / did"
          },
          {
            "id": 47,
            "question": "While he ___ to school his elder brother ___ from the Institute. His brother is a teacher now.",
            "options": [
              "had gone / graduated",
              "has been gone / will graduate",
              "is going / has been graduating",
              "went / graduated",
              "goes / graduated"
            ],
            "answer": "went / graduated"
          },
          {
            "id": 48,
            "question": "___ while he was having breakfast.",
            "options": [
              "He climbed the fence",
              "His pen stopped writing",
              "He fell off the ladder",
              "He bit his tongue",
              "He painted the ceiling"
            ],
            "answer": "He bit his tongue"
          },
          {
            "id": 49,
            "question": "Mary ___ Nick where he ___ after graduating from the University.",
            "options": [
              "asked / works",
              "ask / would work",
              "ask / worked",
              "asked / would work",
              "asked / has worked"
            ],
            "answer": "asked / would work"
          },
          {
            "id": 50,
            "question": "We ___ into the room where the old man ___ . He was seriously ill.",
            "options": [
              "go / lies",
              "goes / lie",
              "went / is lying",
              "went / was lying",
              "was going / was lying"
            ],
            "answer": "went / was lying"
          },
          {
            "id": 51,
            "question": "Mrs. Black ___ into the room where her husband ___ and began to cry.",
            "options": [
              "comes / sits",
              "came / was sitting",
              "came / sat",
              "came / were sitting",
              "was coming / sat"
            ],
            "answer": "came / was sitting"
          },
          {
            "id": 52,
            "question": "As soon as he___ to Copenhagen he___ us a letter.",
            "options": [
              "get / send",
              "gets / sends",
              "gets / will send",
              "got / should send",
              "got / has sent"
            ],
            "answer": "gets / will send"
          },
          {
            "id": 53,
            "question": "I ___ you as soon as we ___ the contract.",
            "options": [
              "shall call / sign",
              "call / sign",
              "called / sign",
              "would call / sign",
              "is calling / are signing"
            ],
            "answer": "shall call / sign"
          },
          {
            "id": 54,
            "question": "As soon as I ___ the result I ___ you know.",
            "options": [
              "hear / shall let",
              "will hear / will let",
              "hear / let",
              "heard / let",
              "have heard / let"
            ],
            "answer": "hear / shall let"
          },
          {
            "id": 55,
            "question": "As soon as the guests ___ we ___ our party.",
            "options": [
              "will come / began",
              "comes / begin",
              "will come / begin",
              "come / shall begin",
              "come / begin"
            ],
            "answer": "come / shall begin"
          },
          {
            "id": 56,
            "question": "I was in the supermarket. As soon as I ___ for the goods somebody ___ me.",
            "options": [
              "paid / would push",
              "had paid / pushed",
              "have paid / pushed",
              "pay / will push",
              "have paid / is pushing"
            ],
            "answer": "had paid / pushed"
          },
          {
            "id": 57,
            "question": "As soon as we ___ the house we ___ to it.",
            "options": [
              "shall build / move",
              "build / shall move",
              "will build / shall move",
              "built / shall move",
              "build / move"
            ],
            "answer": "build / shall move"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Tag Questions",
    "link": "tag-questions",
    "lesions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "name": "Exercise 1",
        "exercises": [
          {
            "id": 1,
            "question": "He had no practice in composing music, ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "didn’t he",
              "had he",
              "does he",
              "has he",
              "doesn’t he"
            ],
            "answer": "had he"
          },
          {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "You have a bad headache, ___?",
            "options": [
              "isn’t it",
              "don’t you",
              "does it",
              "haven’t you",
              "won’t we"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t you"
          },
          {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "He never thought what might come out of it, ___?",
            "options": [
              "does he",
              "hasn’t he",
              "didn’t he",
              "did he",
              "won’t he"
            ],
            "answer": "did he"
          },
          {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "You have finished your work, ___?",
            "options": [
              "didn’t you",
              "haven’t you",
              "don’t you",
              "won’t you",
              "have you"
            ],
            "answer": "haven’t you"
          },
          {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "He isn’t a student, ___ he?",
            "options": ["is", "does", "do", "isn’t", "was"],
            "answer": "is"
          },
          {
            "id": 6,
            "question": "There are so many people in the street, ___?",
            "options": [
              "are they",
              "are there",
              "aren’t they",
              "aren’t there",
              "isn't there"
            ],
            "answer": "aren’t they"
          },
          {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "You don’t play the piano, ___?",
            "options": [
              "don’t you",
              "do you",
              "doesn’t it",
              "does it",
              "isn't it"
            ],
            "answer": "do you"
          },
          {
            "id": 8,
            "question": "This winter is not very cold, ___?",
            "options": [
              "isn’t it",
              "is it",
              "does it",
              "won’t it",
              "hasn't it"
            ],
            "answer": "is it"
          },
          {
            "id": 9,
            "question": "The manner of addressing people in Britain is quite different from ours, ___?",
            "options": [
              "it is",
              "isn’t there",
              "is there",
              "is it",
              "isn’t it"
            ],
            "answer": "isn’t it"
          },
          {
            "id": 10,
            "question": "There won’t be any trouble, ___?",
            "options": [
              "wasn’t there",
              "will not there",
              "will there",
              "do there",
              "wouldn’t there"
            ],
            "answer": "will there"
          },
          {
            "id": 11,
            "question": "The boy wasn’t able to do it alone, ___?",
            "options": [
              "didn’t he",
              "wasn’t he",
              "was he",
              "did he",
              "wasn’t it"
            ],
            "answer": "was he"
          },
          {
            "id": 12,
            "question": "They have to ask somebody else to help them, ___?",
            "options": [
              "haven’t they",
              "have they",
              "do they",
              "don’t they",
              "hasn't he"
            ],
            "answer": "don’t they"
          },
          {
            "id": 13,
            "question": "There were many mistakes in your dictation, ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "weren’t they",
              "were there",
              "aren’t they",
              "weren’t there",
              "aren’t there"
            ],
            "answer": "weren’t there"
          },
          {
            "id": 14,
            "question": "He had lunch at home today, ___ ?",
            "options": [
              "hadn’t he?",
              "wasn’t he?",
              "did he?",
              "didn’t he?",
              "had he?"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t he?"
          },
          {
            "id": 15,
            "question": "You lived here 3 months ago, ___?",
            "options": [
              "don’t you",
              "had you",
              "didn’t you",
              "have you",
              "do you"
            ],
            "answer": "didn’t you"
          },
          {
            "id": 16,
            "question": "It isn’t very early now, ___?",
            "options": [
              "isn’t it",
              "it is",
              "doesn’t it",
              "hasn’t it",
              "is it"
            ],
            "answer": "isn’t it"
          },
          {
            "id": 17,
            "question": "Pete doesn’t work hard, ___?",
            "options": [
              "is he",
              "he does",
              "does he",
              "he works",
              "doesn’t he"
            ],
            "answer": "does he"
          },
          {
            "id": 18,
            "question": "A sick man can’t go out, can he?",
            "options": [
              "No, he can’t.",
              "I didn’t know.",
              "Yes, she could.",
              "No, he isn’t.",
              "Yes, he could."
            ],
            "answer": "No, he can’t."
          },
          {
            "id": 19,
            "question": "Nothing can stop us now, ___?",
            "options": [
              "don’t it",
              "doesn’t it",
              "can’t it",
              "can it",
              "does it"
            ],
            "answer": "can it"
          },
          {
            "id": 20,
            "question": "There is neither electricity nor gas on the island, ___?",
            "options": [
              "is there",
              "isn’t there",
              "there is",
              "there isn’t",
              "isn’t it"
            ],
            "answer": "is there"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  }
]
